<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine eloquence, or, An essay upon the tropes and figures contained in the Holy Scriptures and reduced under the proper titles &amp; rhetorick also several texts of Scripture which fall in with the figures are briefly interpreted, especially those which seem to favour the papist or the Socinian.</title>
            <author>Norwood, Cornelius.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30070</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11240425</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11240425</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1447:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine eloquence, or, An essay upon the tropes and figures contained in the Holy Scriptures and reduced under the proper titles &amp; rhetorick also several texts of Scripture which fall in with the figures are briefly interpreted, especially those which seem to favour the papist or the Socinian.</title>
                  <author>Norwood, Cornelius.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by  J.H. for Luke Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Norwood.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Merton College Library, Oxford University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Rhetoric --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47052:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Divine Eloquence: OR, AN ESSAY Upon the <hi>Tropes</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> Contained in the Holy Scriptures; And <hi>reduced</hi> under The <hi>proper</hi> Titles of <hi>Rhetorick:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO <hi>Several</hi> Texts of <hi>Scripture,</hi> which <hi>fall</hi> in with the <hi>Figures,</hi> are <hi>briefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted;</hi> eſpecially <hi>thoſe</hi> that <hi>ſeem</hi> to <hi>favour</hi> the <hi>Papiſt</hi> or the <hi>Socinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Luke Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:47052:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47052:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHAT,</hi> publiſh <hi>a Treatiſe without</hi> any <hi>Name, or ſo much as a</hi> Dedication? <hi>Prithee then,</hi> who <hi>will</hi> but <hi>it, ſays the</hi> Reader? <hi>Why, as to</hi> that <hi>matter, Sir, you may doe as</hi> you <hi>pleaſe; but give</hi> me <hi>alſo</hi> leave, <hi>to uſe</hi> my <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But, pray,</hi> Sir, what <hi>ſignifies any</hi> Name, <hi>at</hi> leaſt, <hi>to a man of</hi> ſence <hi>and</hi> underſtanding, <hi>who does not</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>his</hi> opinion <hi>and judgment of any</hi> Book, <hi>only from the very</hi> Title-page? <hi>And if</hi> this <hi>Eſſay, I now</hi> preſent <hi>to</hi> your <hi>peruſal, is</hi> any <hi>way</hi> valuable,
<pb facs="tcp:47052:3"/>
               <hi>it will then</hi> introduce <hi>and recommend</hi> it ſelf, <hi>to your</hi> good <hi>opinion of it; and if' tis</hi> nothing <hi>worth,</hi> what <hi>Name or</hi> Character <hi>can</hi> ever <hi>juſtifie the</hi> Publication?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But now, Sir, upon this</hi> reſervation <hi>of my name, you will have this one</hi> particular <hi>advantage; for now you can have no kind of</hi> prejudice <hi>or</hi> by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſs <hi>upon</hi> your <hi>thoughts; and ſo</hi> you <hi>cannot but</hi> pronounce <hi>more</hi> imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <hi>upon the</hi> whole <hi>matter, and not according to the</hi> general <hi>cuſtom,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend, <hi>or</hi> approve, <hi>as you are</hi> diſpos'd <hi>in your</hi> fancy, <hi>to</hi> entertain <hi>either a</hi> good, <hi>or a</hi> bad <hi>opinion of our</hi> Author; <hi>and ſo, I think, 'tis no</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage <hi>to</hi> you, <hi>or to my</hi> ſelf, <hi>whether you</hi> know <hi>my</hi> Name, <hi>or</hi> not; <hi>or whether I am</hi> D. D. <hi>or</hi> Eſquire; ſuch <hi>a one, or otherwiſe</hi> dignified <hi>or</hi> diſtinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> now, <hi>as to the very</hi> buſineſs <hi>of a</hi> Dedication, <hi>I muſt very</hi> freely <hi>tell</hi> you, <hi>Sir, I am at</hi> preſent, <hi>as much out of</hi> humour <hi>with</hi> that <hi>alſo;
<pb facs="tcp:47052:3"/>
for, according to the</hi> common <hi>ſtyle, 'tis</hi> nothing <hi>elſe but a</hi> great <hi>many</hi> fine <hi>words, to very</hi> little <hi>purpoſe; for what you</hi> read <hi>there in</hi> Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>of my</hi> Friend <hi>in the</hi> Country, <hi>or of the</hi> Right <hi>Honourable, my</hi> Lord, <hi>&amp;c. has but the</hi> leaſt relation <hi>to them; but if</hi> they <hi>themſelves are ſo</hi> exceedingly <hi>vain, as to</hi> fanſie <hi>their</hi> Pictures <hi>are</hi> very <hi>like them; 'tis only</hi> their private <hi>opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot</hi> deny, <hi>that I have a</hi> friend <hi>or two, as</hi> very Beau's, <hi>as</hi> any <hi>in the</hi> Town, <hi>and</hi> they <hi>have a</hi> Right <hi>and Title to a very</hi> juſt <hi>Commendation, for the</hi> Rhetorical Twirle <hi>of their long</hi> Perriwigs <hi>behind them, or for</hi> their <hi>moſt</hi> admirable <hi>uſe of their</hi> Snuſh-box, <hi>which is always</hi> ſo obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, <hi>as to give my</hi> Sparks <hi>a</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <hi>for a</hi> Sneeze, <hi>inſtead of an</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <hi>to that</hi> Queſtion; <hi>but then, I am</hi> very <hi>much a</hi> Stranger <hi>to</hi> all <hi>their</hi> other <hi>vertues, and I am not</hi> Oratour <hi>enough to ſay</hi> any <hi>thing at</hi> firſt <hi>ſight: and, after all, let me</hi> tell <hi>you Sir, 'tis
<pb facs="tcp:47052:4"/>
no ſuch</hi> eaſie <hi>matter neither, to make a</hi> fine Panegyrick <hi>upon</hi> Nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> now, <hi>Sir, as to the</hi> Reaſons <hi>of this Publication, I cannot in</hi> my <hi>excuſe ſay, that I was at</hi> laſt <hi>prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by the</hi> violent <hi>Importunities of my</hi> Friends, <hi>whom I could not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> civilly <hi>deny: or that upon the</hi> Communications <hi>of</hi> ſome <hi>Copies, I was very</hi> much <hi>afraid;</hi> one, <hi>or</hi> other, <hi>might</hi> ſend <hi>it to the</hi> Preſs; <hi>and ſo I was</hi> unwilling <hi>to give them</hi> that <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: or laſtly, as</hi> ſome <hi>Apology, for the</hi> incompetency <hi>of the very</hi> work <hi>it</hi> ſelf; <hi>ſhall I</hi> inform <hi>you, Sir, that it was only the</hi> diverſion <hi>of my</hi> idle <hi>hours; when I had nothing elſe to do? And</hi> would <hi>not</hi> this, <hi>think you, be a very</hi> civil <hi>Complement to the</hi> Reader's underſtanding; <hi>if what was here</hi> done <hi>for my</hi> own Recreation, <hi>only to</hi> paſs <hi>away the</hi> time, <hi>I now ſhould</hi> publiſh, <hi>for</hi> his <hi>Inſtruction; and ſo</hi> emprove <hi>his thoughts and</hi> meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>Theſe, and many more, are the</hi> common <hi>excuſes,</hi> our <hi>Authors</hi> often
<pb facs="tcp:47052:4"/>
               <hi>make</hi> uſe <hi>of, to</hi> inſinuate, <hi>that</hi> they <hi>are very</hi> modeſt <hi>men; and that they could</hi> ſtill <hi>doe much</hi> better, <hi>if</hi> they <hi>had taken but</hi> more <hi>time and</hi> leiſure <hi>in their</hi> Compoſition; <hi>and this,</hi> they <hi>preſume, is a</hi> ſufficient <hi>Title to the Reader's</hi> Candor <hi>and more</hi> favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Opinion. But</hi> I <hi>can</hi> only <hi>tell my</hi> Reader, <hi>that after I made a</hi> Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>of theſe</hi> Sacred <hi>Figures of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and</hi> ranged <hi>them into</hi> ſome <hi>kind of order, I very</hi> privately <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed this</hi> Scheam <hi>of Rhetorick into the</hi> Stationer's <hi>hands, and he ſeemed to</hi> fanſie <hi>the</hi> Deſign; <hi>and now,</hi> this <hi>is the</hi> reaſon, <hi>why it comes into your</hi> hands; <hi>and, if'tis</hi> any <hi>way</hi> uſefull, <hi>to any</hi> ſort <hi>of Perſons, I am very</hi> well ſatisfied. <hi>I could gather many</hi> more <hi>Flowers of</hi> Rhetorick, <hi>out of the</hi> ſame field<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>but</hi> theſe <hi>I made</hi> choice <hi>of, perhaps are</hi> ſufficient <hi>to</hi> diſcover, <hi>that the Holy</hi> Scripture <hi>is no</hi> barren <hi>nor</hi> unfruitfull <hi>land; but that it</hi> abounds <hi>with</hi> all <hi>ſorts of</hi> Tropes <hi>and</hi> Figures, <hi>and that it is
<pb facs="tcp:47052:5"/>
the</hi> richeſt Treaſury, <hi>containing the</hi> beſt, <hi>and moſt</hi> excellent <hi>forms of</hi> Rhetorick, <hi>of</hi> any <hi>book</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; <hi>that</hi> no Gentleman <hi>has</hi> any <hi>reaſon to be</hi> afraid <hi>of</hi> loſing <hi>the</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy <hi>of</hi> his <hi>ſtyle, by a frequent</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation <hi>with the</hi> holy <hi>Scripture; which has its</hi> peculiar <hi>Graces and</hi> Beauties <hi>of Eloquence; and more</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, <hi>have not</hi> Job <hi>and</hi> Iſaiah <hi>their</hi> lofty <hi>Flights of</hi> Fancy <hi>and</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etry? <hi>which, to ſpeak but very</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, <hi>are not</hi> unequal <hi>to any in our</hi> profane Authors. <hi>I</hi> know, <hi>there are</hi> ſome <hi>of</hi> another <hi>opinion; but then, does not</hi> their immorality <hi>influence</hi> their <hi>mind? and does it not</hi> give <hi>ſuch a</hi> different <hi>colour and a</hi> tincture <hi>to all their</hi> imaginations, <hi>that they can</hi> never <hi>have the ſame</hi> reliſh <hi>and</hi> ſenſation <hi>of</hi> ſacred <hi>matters; and why ſhould</hi> they <hi>entertain any</hi> honourable <hi>thoughts of</hi> that <hi>very Book, when</hi> all <hi>the</hi> precepts <hi>and</hi> inſtitutions <hi>of it are ſuch a</hi> mighty <hi>Contradiction to</hi> their <hi>life and</hi> practice? <hi>why ſhould</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:47052:5"/>
               <hi>eſteem it worthy</hi> their <hi>peruſal? when perhaps</hi> their meditations <hi>upon it, may be no</hi> ſmall <hi>temptation, to</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie <hi>their</hi> vile <hi>Opinions, and diſturb their</hi> preſent Dreams <hi>of Happineſs, and</hi> at laſt, <hi>reduce them to a</hi> Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>of</hi> Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let</hi> others <hi>then</hi> ſtill <hi>admire their</hi> heathen Rhetorick, <hi>let them</hi> ſtill <hi>fanſie the</hi> ſacred <hi>Figures of Scripture not worthy</hi> their <hi>Conſideration; yet, methinks, when I take a</hi> view <hi>of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Rhetorick, and the</hi> Richneſs <hi>of her Eloquence, ſhe</hi> ſeems <hi>to me, not</hi> unlike <hi>the King's</hi> daughter, <hi>who</hi> is all glorious within, her veſture is of gold, wrought about with divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 45. 10, &amp; 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> now <hi>perhaps</hi> this <hi>Eſſay upon the</hi> Tropes <hi>and</hi> Figures <hi>of</hi> Scripture, <hi>may</hi> ſtill <hi>farther</hi> recommend <hi>it ſelf, to your</hi> better <hi>opinion, from the very</hi> uſe, <hi>and</hi> benefit <hi>of</hi> Rhetorick, <hi>in</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; <hi>and is it not</hi> abſolutely <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, to</hi> convey <hi>to</hi> others, <hi>thoſe</hi> ſenſible <hi>Notions or</hi> Idea's <hi>of things
<pb facs="tcp:47052:6"/>
which are</hi> preſent <hi>to</hi> our <hi>minds? for</hi> Diſcourſe <hi>is, or, at</hi> leaſt, ought <hi>to be,</hi> nothing <hi>elſe, but the</hi> Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>and the very</hi> Picture <hi>of</hi> our thoughts; <hi>and what can more</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly <hi>expreſs them to the</hi> life, <hi>than when a</hi> Metaphor <hi>preſents the</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>of the</hi> ſoul <hi>in ſuch an elegant and</hi> comely <hi>dreſs? Beſides, to give our</hi> Paſſions <hi>their</hi> trueſt <hi>air and</hi> feature, <hi>do they</hi> not <hi>require a very different</hi> garb, <hi>and</hi> another <hi>mode of</hi> expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>than our</hi> other <hi>thoughts, which</hi> ſpring <hi>only from the</hi> cooler <hi>debates of</hi> reaſon, <hi>and</hi> argument? <hi>If</hi> you <hi>queſtion</hi> this, <hi>I appeal only to the moſt</hi> natural <hi>Impreſſions of any</hi> Paſſions, <hi>and whether</hi> Nature <hi>her ſelf</hi> diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>no</hi> ſenſible <hi>difference, when</hi> ſhe <hi>expreſſes her ſelf in a</hi> paſſionate <hi>way; as, ſuppoſe now, in a moſt</hi> vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>tranſport of</hi> Anger; <hi>and cannot you</hi> eaſily, <hi>by the</hi> very <hi>Face,</hi> diſcern <hi>what</hi> paſſes <hi>in the</hi> ſoul <hi>of a</hi> furious <hi>man. Obſerve the</hi> fire, <hi>the very</hi> ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>of his eyes, the</hi> wrinkles <hi>of his</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:47052:6"/>
brow, <hi>the moſt</hi> ſudden <hi>changes of his</hi> countenance, <hi>the mighty</hi> eagerneſs <hi>and the</hi> heſitation <hi>of</hi> his <hi>words; are not theſe the</hi> natural <hi>expreſſions of this</hi> angry <hi>Paſſion, which give</hi> us <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the moſt</hi> diſorderly <hi>motions of our ſpirits, and that the very</hi> ſtream <hi>of our</hi> thoughts <hi>are in a moſt</hi> violent <hi>and rapid</hi> motion; <hi>and therefore, to expreſs this</hi> furious <hi>Paſſion to the</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>life; muſt there</hi> not <hi>be as</hi> great <hi>an alteration in all</hi> our <hi>words and</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>as there is in our very</hi> Faces <hi>and</hi> Complexions? <hi>and this is enough to ſhow, that</hi> this, <hi>and</hi> every <hi>Paſſion works very</hi> differently <hi>upon</hi> our <hi>minds, and</hi> requires different <hi>expreſſions and</hi> colours <hi>of ſpeech, to give it a</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>repreſentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rhetorick then is a</hi> natural <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and a</hi> neceſſary <hi>Ornament of Diſcourſe; and many an</hi> honeſt <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man now and then</hi> ſtumbles <hi>upon a</hi> Trope <hi>or a</hi> Figure, <hi>who was never</hi> acquainted <hi>with Mr.</hi> Butler <hi>or</hi> Farna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; <hi>and much</hi> leſs <hi>with ſuch</hi> profane
<pb facs="tcp:47052:7"/>
               <hi>Authours as</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>or</hi> Quinctili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And are not</hi> Metaphors <hi>very</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>in</hi> holy <hi>Scriptures? The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> themſelves <hi>ſeldom give us a</hi> deſcription <hi>of the</hi> fury <hi>of</hi> God's <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; but they give him</hi> arms, <hi>and</hi> hands, <hi>and deſcribe God prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his</hi> mighty <hi>inſtruments of</hi> ruine, <hi>his</hi> lightning, <hi>and</hi> his <hi>thunder; and by ſuch</hi> formidable <hi>repreſentations, as</hi> theſe, <hi>they work more</hi> powerfully <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> our <hi>minds, and there create the</hi> deeper <hi>impreſſions of his</hi> almighty <hi>Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if</hi> Rhetorical <hi>Figures are as</hi> common <hi>as</hi> neceſſary; <hi>muſt not</hi> that <hi>man be</hi> very ridiculous, <hi>who examines</hi> every <hi>thing in a</hi> ſtrict <hi>and</hi> literal <hi>ſence? What</hi> ſtrange, <hi>what mighty</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent <hi>notions muſt</hi> they <hi>then</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>of God</hi> himſelf, <hi>or of his</hi> divine <hi>Attributes? What</hi> groſs <hi>and very</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd <hi>Idea's of his</hi> infinite <hi>Power, if they ſhould fanſie</hi> God <hi>cannot</hi> accompliſh <hi>the</hi> vengeance <hi>of his</hi> high <hi>diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb facs="tcp:47052:7"/>
without</hi> material <hi>organs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> arms <hi>and</hi> legs? <hi>Muſt not</hi> ſuch <hi>a man</hi> transform <hi>himſelf into any</hi> ſhape <hi>of errour and</hi> deluſion? <hi>if</hi> he <hi>pretends to</hi> maintain <hi>the</hi> doctrine <hi>of</hi> literal <hi>explications; muſt he not</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibe <hi>the</hi> falſe <hi>opinion of</hi> every <hi>Sect, as often as</hi> their <hi>pernicious</hi> errours <hi>are</hi> ſounded <hi>upon a</hi> literal <hi>ſence and</hi> meaning? <hi>Thus the</hi> Quaker <hi>muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a</hi> Roman <hi>Catholick, becauſe, according to</hi> his <hi>Principle, he muſt</hi> underſtand theſe <hi>words according to the</hi> very letter; this is my body; <hi>ſo muſt</hi> he <hi>believe the</hi> bread <hi>and</hi> wine <hi>to be</hi> ſubſtantially <hi>changed into the</hi> very <hi>body and</hi> blood <hi>of Chriſt; and ſo at the leaſt</hi> eventually, <hi>if not</hi> deſignedly, <hi>he will maintain the moſt</hi> abſurd <hi>doctrine of</hi> Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation; <hi>and truly, perhaps their</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>light may</hi> prove <hi>as</hi> dangerous, <hi>and not ſo</hi> different <hi>from</hi> Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>But I do not</hi> charge <hi>them, as if</hi> literal <hi>expoſitions of</hi> Scripture, <hi>was their</hi> conſtant <hi>univerſal</hi> Principle:
<pb facs="tcp:47052:8"/>
               <hi>but if</hi> they <hi>expound</hi> any <hi>Text</hi> lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, <hi>though</hi> never <hi>ſo</hi> abſurd, <hi>and ſo</hi> contrary <hi>to</hi> other <hi>places of</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: <hi>they may</hi> as well <hi>explain</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>in the very</hi> ſame <hi>manner, till</hi> at laſt <hi>they become</hi> nothing <hi>but</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take <hi>and</hi> contradiction. <hi>And now, if</hi> they <hi>will</hi> needs <hi>underſtand</hi> this <hi>Text</hi> literally, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 34. Swear not at all; <hi>and not as if it was</hi> only <hi>a</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition <hi>of</hi> raſh <hi>and</hi> voluntary <hi>ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our</hi> common <hi>diſcourſes; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though St.</hi> Paul himſelf <hi>uſeth an</hi> oath <hi>for</hi> confirmation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 9. For God is my witneſs, whom I ſerve, that without ceaſing, I make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of you always in my Prayers. <hi>And again,</hi> Gal. 1. 20. Now the things which I write unto you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, before God, I lye not. <hi>Nay,</hi> even <hi>God</hi> himſelf, <hi>when he could not</hi> ſwear <hi>by a</hi> greater, <hi>he</hi> ſwore <hi>by</hi> himſelf, <hi>Heb. 6. 13. This is</hi> enough <hi>to ſhow, that the</hi> taking <hi>of an</hi> oath <hi>is not</hi> ſinfull <hi>in its</hi> own <hi>nature; when St.</hi> Paul, <hi>and even</hi> God <hi>almighty
<pb facs="tcp:47052:8"/>
makes</hi> uſe <hi>of an</hi> oath: <hi>and therefore, if the</hi> Quaker <hi>will ſtill</hi> expound this <hi>Text according to the</hi> very letter, <hi>in</hi> contradiction <hi>to</hi> other <hi>Texts of</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Scripture, and in</hi> direct <hi>oppoſition to the very</hi> practice <hi>of St.</hi> Paul, <hi>and even of</hi> God himſelf; <hi>he may, with as</hi> much <hi>reaſon, expound</hi> other <hi>Texts in the</hi> ſame <hi>manner; till he</hi> runs <hi>himſelf into the</hi> wildeſt <hi>abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A great</hi> Maſter <hi>of</hi> Eloquence <hi>has long a go made the</hi> obſervation, <hi>That the</hi> Lawgiver <hi>of the</hi> Jews, <hi>meaning</hi> Moſes, <hi>had a moſt</hi> incomparable <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's infinite power, when he</hi> deſcribes <hi>the Almighty thus</hi> giving <hi>his Orders for the</hi> creation, <hi>and God ſays,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Let there be light, and there was light, <hi>as if there was</hi> no diſtinction <hi>between</hi> his <hi>pleaſure, for the</hi> creation <hi>of</hi> any <hi>Being, and the</hi> actual formation <hi>of it: and is not the</hi> expreſſion <hi>it ſelf very</hi> ſtately, <hi>and full of</hi> majeſty? <hi>for he only ſays,</hi> Let there be, and it
<pb facs="tcp:47052:9"/>
was ſo. <hi>There are</hi> other <hi>expreſſions no</hi> leſs <hi>emphatical, repreſenting God moſt</hi> infinite <hi>in power and</hi> operation, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 40. 12. Who hath meaſured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meeted out the heaven with a ſpan, and comprehended the duſt of the earth in a meaſure, and weighed the mountains in Scales, and the hills in a balance? <hi>As</hi> much <hi>as to ſay,</hi> I, the Lord, only have done this. <hi>And verſe</hi> 17. All nations before him are as nothing, and to whom then will you liken me, ſaith the Lord? <hi>And, how does</hi> holy <hi>David</hi> break <hi>forth in a</hi> mighty <hi>admiration of</hi> his <hi>infinite power and</hi> greatneſs? <hi>Pſalm</hi> 104. 1, 2, 3. O Lord, my God! Thou art very great, thou art cloathed with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and majeſty; who covereſt thy ſelf with light, as with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; who ſtretcheſt out the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, like a curtain; who layeſt the beams of his chamber in the waters; who maketh the clouds his chariot,
<pb facs="tcp:47052:9"/>
comes flying upon the wings of the wind. <hi>What can</hi> better <hi>repreſent to us his moſt</hi> incredible ſwiftneſs? <hi>than when he</hi> thus <hi>deſcribes God, not</hi> only flying, <hi>but even</hi> upon the <hi>very</hi> wings of the wind; <hi>which ſtill gives a moſt ſenſible</hi> Idea <hi>of the</hi> quickeſt <hi>motion that is</hi> poſſible.</p>
            <p>Pſalm 50. 11, 12. <hi>How does God</hi> himſelf aſſert <hi>his</hi> own <hi>Supremacy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> all <hi>things?</hi> I know the fowles of the mountains, and the wild beaſts of the field are mine; If I were hungry, I would not tell thee, for the world is mine, and the fulneſs thereof.</p>
            <p>Iſaiah 5. 26. <hi>How does God</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>that he will</hi> accompliſh <hi>things</hi> moſt <hi>difficult, with the</hi> greateſt <hi>eaſe and</hi> facility <hi>to himſelf? I will,</hi> ſays <hi>God,</hi> Lift up a ſign unto the nations a far, I will hiſs unto them, from the ends of the world, and, behold, they ſhall come with ſpeed: <hi>God does not</hi> ſay, <hi>he will</hi> call <hi>them with the</hi> mighty voice <hi>of his</hi> thunder,
<pb facs="tcp:47052:10"/>
               <hi>but with the</hi> leaſt <hi>kind of</hi> noiſe, <hi>as it were, with a</hi> whiſper; <hi>and yet</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>thoſe that are in the</hi> moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>places, in the</hi> remoteſt <hi>corners of the earth, ſhall</hi> obey <hi>the</hi> power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>ſummons of</hi> his <hi>voice, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently</hi> come, <hi>and make</hi> their <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances: Here you have a</hi> deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>with no leſs</hi> elegancy, <hi>of the moſt</hi> unſearchable <hi>ways and councils of the</hi> great <hi>God;</hi> he made dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his ſecret place, his Pavilion round about him were dark wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and thick clouds of the sky: <hi>and the</hi> methods <hi>of his providence are</hi> very <hi>unaccountable, and paſt</hi> our <hi>underſtanding; his ways are</hi> extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>private, in the</hi> dark, <hi>and in the</hi> deep <hi>waters, and his</hi> footſteps <hi>are not</hi> known.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But becauſe</hi> ſome <hi>have the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, and</hi> rigid <hi>notions of God,</hi> ſhall <hi>I give you a</hi> taſt <hi>of the</hi> ſweetneſs <hi>of his love and</hi> kindneſs, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49. 15. Can a woman, <hi>ſays God,</hi> forget her ſucking child? <hi>And the</hi> queſtion
<pb facs="tcp:47052:10"/>
               <hi>is propoſed, to</hi> aſſure <hi>us 'tis, at</hi> leaſt, <hi>extreamly</hi> difficult, <hi>though</hi> not <hi>impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, for a mother to</hi> break <hi>through the</hi> ſtrongeſt <hi>ties and</hi> impreſſions <hi>of</hi> natural <hi>affection; yet</hi> even <hi>then, God</hi> himſelf <hi>aſſures us, though a</hi> woman <hi>may be ſo very</hi> barbarous, <hi>and ſo inhumane to the</hi> child <hi>of her</hi> womb; <hi>yet, that</hi> he <hi>himſelf, had</hi> more Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, more <hi>affection, more</hi> tender compaſſions; <hi>and could never be</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull <hi>of</hi> his <hi>children: nay, ſo</hi> great <hi>is his</hi> care, <hi>his</hi> ſollicitous <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment for them, that in</hi> all <hi>their</hi> ſufferings, <hi>God cannot but have the</hi> ſame <hi>ſence of</hi> Pain <hi>and miſery, and</hi> ſympathize <hi>with them in all</hi> their <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, ſays the</hi> Prophet, He was afflicted, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 47. 7. <hi>Nay, to the</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laſt <hi>degree of kindneſs and</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration; <hi>that</hi> no <hi>relation, how</hi> near ſoever, <hi>can have</hi> more; <hi>for like</hi> as a father hath compaſſion on his children, ſo the Lord hath pity on them that fear him. <hi>And</hi> Pſal. 103. v. 13. <hi>if 'tis yet</hi> poſſible, <hi>to give a</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:47052:11"/>
ſuller <hi>ſenſe of his</hi> infinite <hi>love and affection to us, he aſſures us, that, if</hi> his <hi>Church is under the</hi> leaſt <hi>kind of ſuffering, that</hi> he himſelf <hi>is</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly <hi>ſenſible of it, even as the</hi> moſt tender <hi>part reſents the</hi> ſmalleſt <hi>injury;</hi> They that touch you, touch the apple of my eye.</p>
            <p>Pſalm 7. 11, 12, 13. <hi>God is there</hi> repreſented, <hi>as a</hi> mighty <hi>man of</hi> war, <hi>preparing to</hi> engage <hi>his enemy; but yet, he is ſo</hi> indulgent, <hi>and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, that he ſeems very</hi> unwilling <hi>to</hi> execute <hi>the</hi> fury <hi>of his</hi> wrath, <hi>but is ſtill in</hi> expectation <hi>of our</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, <hi>that we will at</hi> laſt <hi>ſue for a peace, and</hi> repent, <hi>and obey him; but if he will</hi> not <hi>turn, ſays</hi> David, He will whet his ſword, he hath bent his bow, and made it ready, he hath prepared for him the inſtruments of death.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And is there not a</hi> greatneſs <hi>of</hi> ſpirit <hi>and</hi> majeſty <hi>in this</hi> ſhort <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition</hi> God <hi>gives of</hi> himſelf? I am that I am <hi>hath ſent</hi> me <hi>unto</hi> thee;
<pb facs="tcp:47052:11"/>
               <hi>that is, I</hi> am <hi>God</hi> unchangeable, <hi>the</hi> ſame <hi>yeſterday, to</hi> day <hi>and for</hi> ever, <hi>'tis I that</hi> ſend <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now perhaps</hi> theſe <hi>Texts of Scripture, without any</hi> more, <hi>are</hi> ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <hi>to diſcover, that the</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>is not</hi> written <hi>in ſo very</hi> low <hi>and plain a ſtrain as</hi> ſome <hi>ignorantly</hi> imagine, <hi>and perhaps 'tis not the</hi> leaſt <hi>recommendation of the</hi> inſpired <hi>Writings; that no</hi> other <hi>book in all the world, can</hi> furniſh <hi>our minds with more</hi> diſtinct <hi>and</hi> clearer <hi>Revelations of</hi> his <hi>Being, or his</hi> divine <hi>Attributes, no</hi> other <hi>book can ſo</hi> excellently <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the</hi> power, <hi>the</hi> majeſty, <hi>the</hi> infinte <hi>juſtice, the mercy, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of</hi> Almighty <hi>God. And now, if you are</hi> deſirous <hi>to take a</hi> view <hi>of his</hi> wonders <hi>in the</hi> deep; <hi>how ſhould man, without an</hi> expreſs <hi>revelation from</hi> heaven, <hi>have been able, in the</hi> leaſt, <hi>to diſcover the</hi> incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Myſtery of the Trinity? or how ſhould</hi> he, <hi>upon the</hi> fall <hi>of</hi> Adam, <hi>have been</hi> ever capable <hi>to</hi> dive <hi>into the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:47052:12"/>
myſterious <hi>contrivance of</hi> our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption? <hi>or acquaint</hi> himſelf <hi>with the</hi> reaſons <hi>of Chriſt's</hi> Incarnation, <hi>his</hi> Death, <hi>and</hi> Paſſion, Reſurrection <hi>and</hi> Aſcenſion. <hi>And if</hi> you <hi>pleaſe to take into your</hi> ſerious <hi>conſideration, the</hi> Divinity <hi>of its Doctrines, what a</hi> noble <hi>Scheme is the</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of all</hi> moral <hi>vertues, ſuch as a</hi> Seneca <hi>or a</hi> Plutarch <hi>never</hi> dreamt <hi>of; and what are</hi> all their Syſtems <hi>of Morality, in</hi> compariſon <hi>of the</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Inſtitution? what</hi> Charity, <hi>what</hi> Forgiveneſs <hi>of Enemies, what</hi> Provocations <hi>to</hi> mutual <hi>Love, what</hi> tender <hi>Compaſſions to</hi> one <hi>another in</hi> diſtreſſes, <hi>and miſeries, are we</hi> obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>to put in</hi> practice, <hi>upon</hi> every <hi>occaſion? yea,</hi> what <hi>Purity in</hi> all <hi>our thoughts, what</hi> Innocence, <hi>what Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in</hi> all <hi>our</hi> Intentions? theſe <hi>are all ſuch</hi> mighty <hi>Perfections of</hi> moral <hi>Vertues as we can</hi> only <hi>learn from</hi> Scripture. <hi>Perhaps</hi> others <hi>may</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend <hi>the</hi> practice <hi>of Vertue, from</hi> common decency, <hi>and convenience, or
<pb facs="tcp:47052:12"/>
from a</hi> temporal <hi>ſatisfaction attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> exerciſe <hi>of it, but we</hi> derive <hi>our Obligations much</hi> higher; <hi>for if we had only</hi> hopes <hi>of being happy in</hi> this <hi>life, we were of</hi> all <hi>men the</hi> moſt miſerable, <hi>for</hi> how <hi>does the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion</hi> extend <hi>our Proſpect</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>the grave? and give us</hi> thoſe comfortable <hi>hopes of a</hi> Reſurrection, <hi>and of</hi> eternal <hi>happineſs hereafter, which the</hi> heathens <hi>did but</hi> gueſs at.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But perhaps the</hi> ſpirit <hi>and the</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imitable <hi>ſtyle of the Scripture may ſtill</hi> more effectually <hi>recommend it to</hi> your <hi>peruſal; and has it</hi> not, <hi>think you, a</hi> mighty <hi>force, power, and</hi> effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy; <hi>when our Saviour began his</hi> Inſtitution <hi>to the</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy only with this very</hi> plain <hi>and</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Benediction,</hi> Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit, <hi>and,</hi> Bleſſed are they that are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake. <hi>Who can believe</hi> ſuch <hi>kind of Bleſſings, ſuch</hi> Invitations, <hi>to embrace the</hi> terms <hi>of the Goſpel, ſhould be ſo very</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent, <hi>and bring in ſuch a</hi> numerous
<pb facs="tcp:47052:13"/>
               <hi>company of</hi> Proſelytes, Jews <hi>and</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles? <hi>Who can believe that</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity <hi>ſhould advance, and make its way into the world againſt the</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <hi>of ſo</hi> much <hi>wit, and</hi> power, <hi>from</hi> ſuch <hi>ſort of</hi> encouragements? <hi>Thus the very</hi> difficulty <hi>of its</hi> moral <hi>Duties, and the</hi> diſcouragement <hi>of the Propoſals, and the</hi> mighty plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>of its</hi> Principles, <hi>are</hi> ſo <hi>far from being in the</hi> leaſt <hi>diſadvantageous to the</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Religion, that they are</hi> no ſmall <hi>argument of</hi> its <hi>Divinity; it being</hi> impoſſible <hi>it ſhould</hi> ever <hi>make ſuch a</hi> progreſs <hi>in the world,</hi> unleſs <hi>it had been</hi> aſſiſted <hi>by the</hi> power <hi>and the</hi> wiſedom <hi>of God</hi> himſelf; <hi>and thus the</hi> divine <hi>Authority of its</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal <hi>commands our</hi> reſpect <hi>and</hi> reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And after</hi> all; <hi>the</hi> Simplicity <hi>of the Scriptural Style, is not</hi> without <hi>Majeſty. How</hi> plain, <hi>yet how</hi> mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent <hi>is</hi> this <hi>expreſſion?</hi> I am, <hi>that</hi> I am hath ſent me, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now, as to the</hi> Tranſlation <hi>of
<pb facs="tcp:47052:13"/>
the Bible it</hi> ſelf; <hi>I will not</hi> deny, <hi>but as very</hi> many <hi>places are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a</hi> gracefull, <hi>and</hi> elegant <hi>ornament of expreſſion; ſo there are</hi> ſome other <hi>parts,</hi> leſs <hi>artificial, neither is</hi> this <hi>ſo very</hi> ſtrange; <hi>ſince the</hi> original <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages ſometimes carry in them a</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Grace, and</hi> Emphaſis, <hi>hardly</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible <hi>in a</hi> Tranſlation, <hi>at leaſt, with the very</hi> ſame <hi>beautify and</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy <hi>of ſpeech. And if our</hi> Tranſlators, <hi>here and there, fall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the</hi> ſpirit <hi>and the</hi> dignity <hi>of the Original, they are</hi> very excuſable, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were</hi> ſometimes <hi>afraid to</hi> venture <hi>at a</hi> phraſe <hi>or a</hi> fineneſs <hi>of a</hi> period; <hi>leſt they ſhould</hi> deviate <hi>more from the</hi> true ſence <hi>and</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication <hi>of the Text; and, after all, you will</hi> diſcover ſome <hi>elegant</hi> Turns, <hi>and ſome</hi> Beauties <hi>of Rhetorick in the</hi> Tranſlations, <hi>which do not ſo</hi> clearly <hi>ſhine out in the very</hi> Original, <hi>which I have</hi> purpoſely <hi>inſerted</hi> ſometimes, <hi>to let</hi> my <hi>Reader</hi> ſee, <hi>that if</hi> our <hi>Tranſlators</hi> loſe <hi>in one</hi> place, <hi>yet they</hi> gain <hi>in</hi> another.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:47052:14"/>
               <hi>As to my</hi> own <hi>part, I ſhall</hi> only <hi>tell you</hi> this; <hi>that I was</hi> extreamly <hi>pleaſed, when any</hi> Figure <hi>was</hi> lodg'd <hi>upon</hi> any <hi>Text of Scripture, that ſeem'd to</hi> favour <hi>and countenance any</hi> falſe <hi>doctrines, eſpecially the</hi> Romiſh, <hi>or the</hi> Socinian, <hi>that I might take an</hi> occaſion <hi>to make a</hi> little inroad <hi>into them, and</hi> recover <hi>them from the</hi> unkind <hi>and</hi> falſe impriſonment <hi>of the</hi> enemy: <hi>and when ſeveral</hi> other <hi>Texts of Scripture were in</hi> darkneſs, <hi>and obſcurity, or under</hi> any <hi>difficulty, I have</hi> endeavour'd, <hi>to</hi> let <hi>in</hi> more light <hi>into them, by an eaſie</hi> explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>or a ſhort</hi> paraphraſe <hi>upon the</hi> words; <hi>which perhaps were not</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>ſo very</hi> plain, <hi>and</hi> obvious, <hi>at</hi> leaſt, <hi>to</hi> every <hi>man's</hi> capacity <hi>and</hi> apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I will now</hi> trouble <hi>you</hi> no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>but I</hi> hope, <hi>you will receive it</hi> kindly, <hi>as if in</hi> this <hi>Eſſay</hi> ſome <hi>things, at</hi> leaſt <hi>were</hi> tolerable.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47052:14"/>
            <head>Divine Eloquence: OR, AN ESSAY Upon the <hi>Tropes &amp; Figures</hi> Contained in the Holy Scriptures.</head>
            <div n="trope" type="part">
               <head>A TROPE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Trope</hi> is nothing elſe, but the <hi>change</hi> of a word, from its <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Signification, into another, whereby the <hi>Idea</hi> of any thing is more <hi>ſenſible</hi> to us. Inſtance,</p>
               <p>Matt. 4. 19. <hi>And I will make you</hi> Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>of men:</hi> that is, Inſtruments of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and converting men unto God; and our Saviour uſeth the term by, way of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47052:15"/>
alluſion to them, that being their former Employ.</p>
               <p>Pſal. 65. 14. <hi>The valleys,</hi> ſays our Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>ſhall ſtand ſo thick with Corn, that they ſhall Laugh and Sing:</hi> that is, A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plentifull harveſt is the occaſion of joy and pleaſantneſs; laughing or ſinging are the proper expreſſions of a <hi>gay</hi> and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Spirit; and ſo thoſe terms applied to <hi>other</hi> things by way of <hi>Analogy,</hi> repreſent to us the exceſſive <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> of Plenty.</p>
               <p>Luke 13. 32. <hi>Go, and tell that Fox,</hi> meaning <hi>Herod,</hi> that crafty and politick Diſſembler: and the application of the term, gives us a <hi>fuller</hi> notion of his <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>I ſhall here ſet down only <hi>three</hi> Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions belonging to a Trope, leaving the <hi>fourth,</hi> to thoſe who are more <hi>induſtrious</hi> to find it out: <hi>viz. Hyperbole, Allegory, Metalepſis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>HYPERBOLE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to <hi>exceed.</hi> This Figure <hi>repreſents</hi> things <hi>greater, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> or <hi>better,</hi> than they <hi>are</hi> in their <hi>own</hi> natures; and <hi>this</hi> ſort of Trope is <hi>extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> uſefull, when our <hi>ordinary</hi> terms are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47052:15"/>
ſo very <hi>weak,</hi> that they <hi>carry</hi> in them <hi>no proportion,</hi> with the <hi>notices</hi> of our <hi>mind;</hi> and ſo the <hi>ſoul,</hi> for fear of ſpeaking too <hi>little,</hi> preſently <hi>flies</hi> out, and enlargeth too <hi>much;</hi> but let no one <hi>fanſie,</hi> that the <hi>uſe</hi> of this Figure is in the <hi>leaſt</hi> unlawfull; for if we ſometimes <hi>expreſs</hi> ourſelves in the <hi>higheſt,</hi> or in the <hi>loweſt</hi> degree <hi>imaginable,</hi> yet 'tis no <hi>Lye,</hi> for we have not the <hi>leaſt</hi> intention to <hi>deceive</hi> any one; but we on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fly ſo <hi>extravagantly</hi> high, that our <hi>diſcourſe</hi> may come <hi>down</hi> with more <hi>force</hi> into the <hi>minds</hi> of our <hi>audience,</hi> and give them ſuch a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of what we are <hi>talking,</hi> as may <hi>oblige</hi> them to <hi>conceive</hi> 'tis highly <hi>impoſſible;</hi> or elſe to <hi>enlarge</hi> their <hi>thoughts</hi> about it.</p>
                     <p>2 Sam. 1. 23. of the <hi>latter</hi> kind, <hi>Saul and Jonathan were ſwifter than Eagles, they were ſtronger than Lions:</hi> and by ſuch <hi>ſenſible Idea's,</hi> and familiar Reſemblances, you <hi>conceive</hi> ſtill but an <hi>higher</hi> notion of their <hi>mighty ſtrength</hi> and <hi>activity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gen. 32. 12. <hi>Thy Seed ſhall be as the Sand of the ſea, which cannot be numbred for multitude;</hi> and the <hi>Compariſon</hi> only implies, that his <hi>family</hi> ſhould be <hi>exceeding</hi> numerous.</p>
                     <p>Pſal. 107. 26. <hi>The Waves of the ſea Mount up to Heaven, and go Down again
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47052:16"/>
to the Deep;</hi> that is, the <hi>foaming</hi> Waters are carried up <hi>exceedingly high,</hi> and they <hi>tumble</hi> down again into the <hi>loweſt</hi> places of the Earth. See <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 15. to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>Rom 9. 3. <hi>I could Wiſh that my ſelf were Accurſed from Chriſt, and as One cut off from the Communion of his Church, for my Brethren and Kinſmen according to the fleſh;</hi> which Wiſh was <hi>abſolutely</hi> a thing <hi>impoſſible;</hi> yet ſuch a kind of <hi>Imprecation</hi> could not but <hi>give</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> an <hi>infinite</hi> Aſſurance of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>exceſſive</hi> Love and <hi>Charity</hi> to them. See <hi>John</hi> 21. 25. <hi>the World it Self could not Contain the books that ſhould be written;</hi> a <hi>figurative</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion very <hi>large.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gen. 11. 4. <hi>Let us Build a Tower, whoſe Top may reach up unto Heaven:</hi> that is, riſe up <hi>exceeding</hi> high, and lofty.</p>
                     <p>There are two ſorts of this Figure <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole; Auxeſis,</hi> and <hi>Meioſis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Aaxeſis.</head>
                        <p>James 4. 1. <hi>From whence come Wars and fightings among you? Wars</hi> is a word that carries in the very <hi>ſound</hi> of it a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Diſpute and <hi>Engagement</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> againſt one another; but the term here is only made <hi>uſe</hi> of, by way of <hi>amplification,</hi>
                           <pb n="5" facs="tcp:47052:16"/>
and ſignifies the <hi>private</hi> quarrels and <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> among <hi>themſelves.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Judges 5. 4, 5. <hi>Lord, when thou Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedſt out of Edom, the earth Trembled, and the heavens Dropped, the clouds alſo Dropped with water, the mountains Melted before the Lord:</hi> Not that all theſe <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> Effects did then <hi>actually</hi> come to paſs; but they are here <hi>ſpecified,</hi> to give us a <hi>mighty</hi> notion of God's <hi>preſence,</hi> and how the moſt <hi>ſacred</hi> Majeſty of it ſtrikes an <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal</hi> Fear, and <hi>Conſternation</hi> every where.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Meioſis.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Meioſis,</hi> a Figure of <hi>diminution,</hi> when we uſe a <hi>leſs</hi> word or expreſſion, than the <hi>matter</hi> requires.</p>
                        <p>James 4. 17. <hi>To him that Knoweth to doe Good, and doth it Not, to Him it is Sin;</hi> but not a <hi>ſin</hi> of the <hi>leaſt</hi> degree, as the <hi>phraſe</hi> at <hi>firſt</hi> ſight, ſeems to <hi>import;</hi> but of a very <hi>great</hi> Aggravation, being <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Reaſon and <hi>Reflection,</hi> and ſo a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>dangerous</hi> and preſumptive <hi>ſin.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Matt. 5. 19. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall break one of the leaſt of theſe commandments, and ſhall teach men ſo, ſhall be the Leaſt in the king dom of Heaven:</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. a very ſoft ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and much milder than ſuch ſort of falſe Teachers can pretend to deſerve;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47052:17"/>
but indeed it ſignifies, ſuch ſhall be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as nothing, and inſignificant, in the Church of God.</p>
                        <p>1 Cor. 10. 5. <hi>But with Many of them God was not Well pleaſed:</hi> A very <hi>ſoft</hi> and <hi>favourable</hi> expreſſion, God was not <hi>well pleaſed,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> whereas it is very <hi>plain</hi> by the Conſequence, that he was <hi>extremely</hi> angry, inſomuch that in the <hi>fury</hi> of his <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> they were <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently</hi> cut off and deſtroyed in the <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Matt. 3. 11. <hi>But he that Cometh after Me is Mightier than I, whoſe Shooes I am not Worthy to Bear:</hi> This was ſpoken by St. <hi>John,</hi> not without the <hi>greateſt</hi> ſenſe of his own <hi>unworthineſs;</hi> even to that <hi>degree,</hi> that he thinks himſelf not <hi>worthy</hi> to perform the <hi>offices</hi> of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, for his Bleſſed Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>1 Sam 24. 15. <hi>After whom is the King come out? after a Dead dog, and after a Flea:</hi> The moſt <hi>inconſiderable</hi> ſort of <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> See 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9. 8. and 16. 9.</p>
                        <p>Numbers 13. 33. <hi>We ſaw Men, and were as Graſhoppers before them:</hi> A peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>leaſt</hi> ſize and figure in <hi>compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of them.</p>
                        <p>Matt. 2. 6. <hi>And thou Bethlehem, in the land of Juda, art not the Leaſt among the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47052:17"/>
Princes of Juda:</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is by no means a term of <hi>diminution;</hi> but, on the contrary, it rather ſignifies, thou art very <hi>great</hi> and honourable, upon the <hi>Birth</hi> of our Saviour, being the <hi>place</hi> of his <hi>Nativity.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Iſaiah 40. 17. <hi>All Nations before me are as Nothing; and they are counted to him, Leſs than Nothing and vanity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> As if in reſpect of God's <hi>Superlative</hi> Greatneſs, it was not <hi>ſufficient,</hi> to ſay the whole <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe</hi> was <hi>nothing:</hi> But ſtill the Prophet goes <hi>farther,</hi> and ſays, it was <hi>leſſer,</hi> even than Nothing; to give us a <hi>fuller</hi> ſenſe, if <hi>poſſible,</hi> what an <hi>Inconſiderable</hi> thing the whole World is.</p>
                        <p>Pſal. 22. 6. The Royal <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſtyles himſelf <hi>a Worm, and no Man.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Gen. 18. 27. <hi>Now have I taken upon me to Speak unto the Lord, which am but Duſt and Aſhes:</hi> A Preface of the <hi>higheſt</hi> ſenſe of his <hi>own</hi> Unworthineſs; as if <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> had ſaid, What, ſhall I <hi>preſume</hi> to <hi>plead</hi> with the great God, who am <hi>vile</hi> Earth, and, which is <hi>worſe,</hi> a moſt <hi>miſerable</hi> Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner?—Oh, let not the <hi>Lord</hi> be <hi>angry.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:47052:18"/>
                     <head>AN <hi>ALLEGORY.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>An <hi>Allegory</hi> is the <hi>Continuation</hi> of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor, and as <hi>that</hi> conſiſteth, in the <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of <hi>one</hi> word, from the proper ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it; ſo the Allegory tranſlates <hi>many</hi> terms, from their native ſenſe and meaning; this Figure muſt not be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted according to the <hi>ſtrict</hi> and literal ſignification, but with reſpect to a meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical ſence <hi>eminently</hi> contained in it.</p>
                     <p>Matt. 3. 12. <hi>Whoſe Fan is in his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hand, and he will throughly Purge his Flour, and Gather the Wheat into his Garner, but he will Burn up the Chaff with Unquenchable fire:</hi> this is all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpoken in <hi>alluſion</hi> to the <hi>righteous</hi> and to the <hi>wicked,</hi> who are here termed the <hi>wheat</hi> and the <hi>chaff:</hi> and the Figure explains what a <hi>diſcrimination</hi> and difference, God will at the laſt day make between them, upon his <hi>impartial</hi> diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Rewards, and Puniſhments.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 1. <hi>He ſhall be as a Tree planted by the rivers of waters, that bringeth forth fruit in his ſeaſon, his Leaf alſo ſhall not wither, and whatſoever he doth, it ſhall proſper;</hi> intimating to us, under this ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Allegory, the happy and flouriſhing condition of the godly Man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:47052:18"/>Galat. 4. 25. <hi>This Agar is mount Sinai, in Arabia, and anſwereth to Jeruſalem that now is:</hi> that is, <hi>Agar</hi> bears ſome <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> to the <hi>earthly Jeruſalem</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Age; for as the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo all that ſpring from <hi>Agar,</hi> are under a <hi>ſervile</hi> ſtate. But then, Verſ. 26. <hi>Jeruſalem which is from Above, is free, which is the Mother of us all:</hi> but there is <hi>another</hi> Church, namely, the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> anſwerable to <hi>Sarah;</hi> and as all born of <hi>Sarah</hi> were free, ſo all <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> now living under the <hi>milder</hi> diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of the Goſpel, are perfectly ſet free from <hi>ſpiritual</hi> bondage. In ſhort, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,</hi> by way of Allegory, repreſents to us the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, who are in a <hi>ſervile</hi> condition; but <hi>Sarah</hi> denotes the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, which is in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtate of freedom, and not in the leaſt obliged to obſerve the ceremonial Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matt. 13. where you obſerve, <hi>the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Seed</hi> repreſents the diſſeminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Word of God; which <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> or <hi>miſcarried,</hi> in proportion, as the <hi>heart</hi> of the Believer was <hi>more,</hi> or leſs <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared</hi> for it. But <hi>ſome fell on the Good ground:</hi> that is, ſome were of a good and vertuous diſpoſition of mind, and <hi>there</hi> the Doctrines of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> here called the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47052:19"/>
                        <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Seed, did <hi>ſpring</hi> up in their <hi>ſouls,</hi> and thrive and grow <hi>exceedingly</hi> well; and they became extraordinary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Eccleſ. 12. there is a very elegant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the many Infirmities of Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age carried on Allegorically: Verſe 2. <hi>While the Sun is not dark;</hi> that is, while thy Reaſon and Underſtanding is bright and vigorous within thee. Verſ. 3 <hi>When the Keepers of the houſe ſhall tremble;</hi> that is, the Hands which keep and defend the Body, ſhall grow weak and languiſhing.—<hi>and the ſtrong men ſhall bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> that is, the Leggs, through the Infirmity of Age, ſhall not be able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelves, but ſink under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and fail.—<hi>and the Grinders ſhall ceaſe, becauſe they are few;</hi> that is, not ſo many in Number, and very much decayed in their ſtrength and firmneſs.—<hi>and they wax dark that look out at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows;</hi> which very well expreſſeth the dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſight, and the Eyes being, as it were, the <hi>windows</hi> of the Body.—Verſe 4. <hi>and the Doors ſhall be ſhut without, by the baſe ſounding of the Grinding;</hi> that is, the <hi>Mouth,</hi> and Lips, and Jaws, ſhall fall in, and <hi>cloſe</hi> and <hi>contract</hi> themſelves, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to keep their diſtances, and open
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47052:19"/>
and chew any more; as being much more tired, through the failure of Teeth, that they cannot without much time and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour perform their Offices—<hi>and he ſhall riſe up at the voice of the bird;</hi> that is, the <hi>old</hi> man ſhall be more <hi>watchfull,</hi> and without ſoundneſs of Sleep, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently awaken at the <hi>leaſt</hi> noiſe, at the voice of the Cock-crowing.—<hi>and the Daughters of muſick ſhall be brought low,</hi> that is, the Organs of the voice decay, and now are unable to create, and ſend out the pleaſant and harmonious ſounds in ſinging<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>—<hi>and the man ſhall be afraid of high places;</hi> that is, the poor old man ſhall tremble to go up into any high place, for fear his Head, through weakneſs, turns giddy, and he fall and tumble down again. Verſ. 5. <hi>And the Almond-tree ſhall flouriſh,</hi> that is, his Head ſhall be as white with Gray-hairs, as the Bloſſoms of an Almond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree.—<hi>and the graſs-hopper ſhall be a burthen;</hi> that is, the old man ſhall be ſo much decayed, and ſo extremely weak, that he cannot ſuſtain the weight of the lighteſt burthen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 15. You have there an Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Inſtance of God's Mercy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to Penitent Sinners, very lively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, under the notion of a tender and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47052:20"/>
affectionate Father, to his prodigal Son, upon his Recovery and Reformation of his former life.</p>
                     <p>And, What is the whole Book of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> but a continued Metaphor? where the ſweet Conference between Chriſt and his Church, is repreſented in ſuch words and expreſſions, as ſeem only proper to Man and Wife, and therefore Chriſt condeſcends to expreſs himſelf in the ſame familiar dialect, to give us the beſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his infinite Love and Affection to his Church.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. 1. Where you have the ſtate of the Church repreſented in the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Wedding, and with the uſual Ceremonies belonging to it; and the whole Allegory, as to the Morality of it, may ſuggeſt thus much; that 'tis not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for us to be <hi>once</hi> prepar'd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to follow Chriſt, unleſs we alſo <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere</hi> in our Courſe after him. Now then, the <hi>Bridegroom</hi> is <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, the <hi>time</hi> of the Wedding is at his <hi>laſt</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, the <hi>night</hi> is the melancholy ſtate and condition of the Church in the World; the <hi>Virgins</hi> are they that make <hi>profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>purity</hi> of the Goſpel, and the <hi>wiſe</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins are the <hi>true</hi> Believers, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly <hi>provided</hi> in their Hearts, to receive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47052:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him at his coming, making an holy Life and Practice their daily Buſineſs, through the aſſiſtance of Divine Grace, which is the <hi>Oil</hi> that burneth, howſoever it be not always in actual exerciſe; but the <hi>fooliſh</hi> ones are they in the Church, who have been very negligent to excite and cheriſh the Gifts and Graces of the Holy Spirit: the Lamps are their Hearts, which are unprovided, the Slumber is their Remiſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Ceſſation from continual exerciſe of Piety, without expectation of Chriſt's ſudden appearance, cauſed chiefly through the Infirmity of the Fleſh, that is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive and tired out through his long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays of coming.</p>
                     <p>The Holy Scripture is very full of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legories of all ſorts: See <hi>Job</hi> 20. 12, 13.—c. 27. v. 20.—c. 28. v. 9. <hi>Pſal</hi> 23. v. 1.—69. 1, 2, 3.—75. 8.—80. v. 8, 9, 10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7.—30. 30. Matt. 3. 10, 12.—5-13.—7 3, 4, 5, 6.—9. 14. Luk 9. 62. Rom. 11. 16, 17, 18. But I ſhould be too tedious ſhould I give you an accurate view of the particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances belonging to this Figure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:47052:21"/>
                     <head>METALEPSIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Metalepſis</hi> multiplies a Trope in one word, when one improper term ſerves to expreſs another by it, till you arrive at the moſt proper one of all.</p>
                     <p>Matt. 21. 20. <hi>All the City was moved:</hi> The word <hi>City</hi> here ſignifies <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> the general term comprehending the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, by <hi>Synecdoche generis,</hi> and <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> denotes the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of it, by a <hi>Metonymy of the Subject.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lament. 4. 4. <hi>The tongue of the ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for very thirſt:</hi> here firſt, by the extreme thirſt of the ſucking Infant, is ſignified the <hi>barren</hi> and dry <hi>breaſts</hi> of the Mother; and by her Want of Milk, <hi>extreme Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>Famine;</hi> and by Famine, the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Poverty</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> of the People.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Four kinds of a Trope.</head>
                  <p>There are four ſorts of a Trope, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonymy, Irony, Metaphor, Synecdoche.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>METONYMY.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Metonymy,</hi> of the <hi>cauſe,</hi> when the <hi>name</hi> of the very Perſon ſerves to expreſs the <hi>act,</hi> or operation, proceeding from him: thus,</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:47052:21"/>The <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> ſometimes ſignifies on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>regeneration,</hi> or <hi>a new</hi> birth, which is the <hi>peculiar</hi> efficacy of the third Perſon in the Bleſſed Trinity.</p>
                     <p>Pſal. 51. 10. <hi>Renew a Right ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me:</hi> and to the very ſame purpoſe ſee <hi>Ezek. 36. 26. Eph. 4. 23. Rom.</hi> 12. 2. all which places ſeem to imply nothing leſs than a <hi>moral</hi> change wrought in our Souls by the <hi>Influence</hi> of divine <hi>grace,</hi> whereby we become regenerate or <hi>born again.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 19. 'tis the admonition of St. <hi>Paul, not to quench the Spirit,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, a <hi>ſimilitude</hi> borrowed from the <hi>fire</hi> of the ancient Altars, which was continually to be <hi>preſerved</hi> alive; and ſo here, he muſt not <hi>extinguiſh</hi> the <hi>Gifts</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> but keep them in conſtant exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, ſuch are <hi>Grace, Charity, meekneſs,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. 8.</p>
                     <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 6. The very ſame Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to ſtir up the <hi>Gift</hi> of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> that is, <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or ſome other divine Quality which is excited in us by the mighty <hi>energy, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> or <hi>operation</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Spirit</hi> alſo ſometimes ſignifies a divine <hi>power</hi> or <hi>energy</hi> reigning in the Soul of the regenerate Man: See <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 46, 47.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47052:22"/>
                        <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirit hath rejoiced in God my Saviour.</hi> There are not a few other places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture where you will find the word, <hi>Spirit,</hi> is often made uſe of, to expreſs the <hi>new</hi> Man, and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> ſtrength, <hi>Rom. 1. 9. Galat. 3. 3. Acts</hi> 17. 16.</p>
                     <p>2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 9. It was the earneſt requeſt of <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Elijah, let a double portion of thy Spirit be upon me;</hi> that is, give me an extraordinary <hi>meaſure</hi> of the <hi>gift</hi> of Prophecy, and <hi>power</hi> in working Mire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which are here called the <hi>portion of thy Spirit,</hi> as being the peculiar gifts of the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> conferred upon us. See <hi>Num. 11. 25. 2 Kings</hi> 4. 1, and 42.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dan. 5. 12. Daniel</hi> had a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>ſpirit,</hi> that is, a more <hi>eminent</hi> gift of the ſpirit, more <hi>knowledge,</hi> and <hi>more underſtanding.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Numb. 11. 25. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord reſted upon the ſeventy Elders;</hi> that is, the Gift of Prophecy and Prediction.</p>
                     <p>Acts 19. 2. <hi>We have not ſo much as heard, whether there be Any Holy Ghoſt:</hi> that is, we are very much Strangers to the <hi>virtue,</hi> power, or influence of <hi>him.</hi> And you find afterwards, <hi>they received the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt;</hi> that is, the <hi>divine</hi> Inſpirations of him, which did <hi>eminently</hi> appear in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47052:22"/>
Gift of <hi>languages</hi> and of <hi>power</hi> of working Miracles, and other kind of Wonders. To the ſame purpoſe, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 5. Jo. 7. 39.</p>
                     <p>Rev. 1. 10. <hi>I was in the Spirit;</hi> that is, in a Rapture or Ecſtaſie, in which the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is exalted after a wonderfull manner, to the Contemplation of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things.</p>
                     <p>Ezek. 37. 1. <hi>The hand of the Lord car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me out in the Spirit of the Lord;</hi> that is, by a <hi>viſion</hi> occaſioned by him; where you ſee, in both theſe places, the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>efficient</hi> Cauſe, is put for the <hi>Effect,</hi> proceeding from <hi>him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Luke 16. 29. <hi>They have Moſes and the Prophets;</hi> that is, the <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Moſes;</hi> where by a Metonymy of the <hi>efficient</hi> Cauſe, the <hi>Author</hi> is put for his <hi>Writings.</hi> See <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 27.</p>
                     <p>Eph. 4. 20. <hi>But ye have not ſo learned Chriſt;</hi> that is, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> delivered by him.</p>
                     <p>Acts 2. 4. <hi>They began to ſpeak with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongues;</hi> that is, with <hi>different</hi> ſorts of <hi>languages.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 25. 15. <hi>A Soft Tongue breaketh the Bones;</hi> that is, a <hi>mild</hi> and courteous way of ſpeaking, <hi>ſoftens</hi> the <hi>hardeſt</hi> Heart, and moſt <hi>obſtinate</hi> Reſolutions; where you ſee, in <hi>both</hi> theſe places of Scripture, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47052:23"/>
                        <hi>inſtrumental</hi> Cauſe ſignifies the <hi>Effect</hi> it ſelf <hi>produced</hi> by it.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 11. 1. <hi>And the whole earth was of One lip;</hi> that is, of <hi>one</hi> language, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niform way of ſpeaking; <hi>Inſtrumentum</hi> pro <hi>Effectu</hi> ipſo.</p>
                     <p>Job 31. 6. <hi>Let God weigh me in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Balance;</hi> the <hi>inſtrument</hi> of Equity and Juſtice, for <hi>equity</hi> it ſelf; and ſo <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> a Metaphor, the Phraſe ſignifies no more, but, Let God try and <hi>examine</hi> me <hi>impartially.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ezek. 7. 15. <hi>the Sword is without, and the Peſtilence and the Famine within;</hi> that is, <hi>death,</hi> and ruin, is <hi>ſcattered</hi> every where; and is ſignified by thoſe which are the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy <hi>inſtruments</hi> of it.</p>
                     <p>Matt. 10. 34. <hi>I came not to ſend Peace, but a Sword;</hi> that is <hi>variance,</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> and <hi>perſecution; inſtrumentum,</hi> pro <hi>Re ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta.</hi> Not that our Saviour's Coming was the <hi>proper</hi> Cauſe of <hi>ſuch</hi> Unhappineſs; but ſo it ſhould <hi>eventually</hi> happen out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his appearance in our Nature, becauſe his Kingdom was of <hi>another</hi> World, and ſo extreamly contrary to all the <hi>deſigns</hi> and intereſt of the preſent World.</p>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Metonymy of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Metonymia Materiae,</hi> when the very <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> ſignifies the very <hi>thing</hi>
                           <pb n="19" facs="tcp:47052:23"/>
made and <hi>faſhioned</hi> out of it: thus,</p>
                        <p>Pſal. 115. 4. <hi>Their Idols are Silver and Gold.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Dan. 5. 4. <hi>They praiſed the Gods of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron and Braſs;</hi> that is, made out of thoſe metals.</p>
                        <p>Gen. 3. 19. <hi>Duſt thou art,</hi> that is, thou art formed out of it.</p>
                        <p>Pſal. 105. 18 <hi>He was laid in Iron,</hi> that is, in Chains of Iron.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Metonymy of the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Metonymy</hi> of the <hi>effect,</hi> when the thing cauſed is put for the <hi>efficient</hi> Cauſe of it.</p>
                        <p>Gen. 4. 13. <hi>My Puniſhment,</hi> ſays <hi>Cain, is greater than I can bear,</hi> that is, my <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> is greater than can be <hi>forgiven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> There, <hi>puniſhment</hi> ſignifies the very <hi>ſin</hi> it ſelf, as the <hi>immediate</hi> Conſequence of it.</p>
                        <p>2 Kings 4. 40. <hi>there is Death in the Pot;</hi> meaning ſome moſt <hi>deſtructive</hi> and <hi>poiſonous</hi> thing, which <hi>cauſeth</hi> Death.</p>
                        <p>John 17. 3. <hi>And this is life Eternal, that they may know Thee, the only true God;</hi> that is, the Knowledge of God and his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is the <hi>principal</hi> Cauſe of everlaſting Salvation to all that live <hi>ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably</hi> to thoſe <hi>notices.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Luke 2. 30. <hi>My eyes have ſeen thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> that is, our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf, the <hi>Author</hi> of it. So <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 18.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47052:24"/>
                           <hi>I have waited for thy Salvation;</hi> that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>promiſed Meſſiah.</hi> So <hi>Iſai. 49. 6. All fleſh ſhall See the Salvation of God;</hi> that is, a <hi>Saviour.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Gen. 25. 13. <hi>Two Nations are in thy womb;</hi> that is, the <hi>Fathers</hi> of two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Rom. 7. 7. <hi>Is the law ſin?</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle; that is, Is the Law it ſelf the proper <hi>cauſe</hi> of Sin? or, Is there any ſuch <hi>malignity</hi> in the very <hi>nature</hi> of it, as <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth</hi> any ſuch Effect?</p>
                        <p>1 Cor. 10. 13. <hi>Let every one Pleaſe his Neighbour for Good, to Edification;</hi> that is, ſo <hi>behave</hi> himſelf in all things of <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency,</hi> that ſuch a <hi>deportment</hi> may be the <hi>cauſe</hi> of their good <hi>will</hi> and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and purchaſe their <hi>favour</hi> and kind <hi>opinion</hi> of us. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Metonymy of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</head>
                        <p>A <hi>Metonymy</hi> of the <hi>Subject;</hi> when the Subject is made uſe of, to ſignifie the <hi>accident</hi> or quality <hi>inherent</hi> in it.</p>
                        <p>Prov. 6. 32. <hi>whoſo committeth Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with a woman, wanteth a Heart;</hi> that is, <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>underſtanding:</hi> ſo he that truſteth in his own <hi>heart, i. e.</hi> in his own <hi>diſcretion</hi> and prudence.</p>
                        <p>Pſal. 7. 9. the <hi>heart</hi> is put for the <hi>thoughts</hi> and inclinations of it, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 62. 8. - 142. 2.</p>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:47052:24"/>
                        <p>Continens, <hi>pro</hi> Re contenta.<note place="margin">The thing containing for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing it ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Luke 22. 17. <hi>He took the Cup, and gave thanks,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> where the <hi>cup</hi> is put for the <hi>liquor</hi> contained in it, as is more plain from <hi>v. 18 I will not drink of the Fruit of the Vine.</hi> Thus in the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, this <hi>cup</hi> is the N. Teſt. in my <hi>blood,</hi> not the <hi>veſſel</hi> it ſelf, but the <hi>liquor</hi> in it.</p>
                        <p>The <hi>Place</hi> ſignifies the <hi>Thing</hi> or <hi>Perſon</hi> in that place.<note place="margin">The place ſerves to denote any thing in that place.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Matt. 8. 34. <hi>The Whole city went out to meet him: Locus,</hi> pro <hi>Incolis.</hi> So <hi>Mark</hi> 1. 33. Iſai. 38. 18. <hi>The Grave cannot Praiſe thee:</hi> they that are <hi>dead,</hi> and buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are incapable of it.</p>
                        <p>Gen. 7. 1. <hi>Come thou, and All thy houſe, into the ark;</hi> thou and all thy <hi>family.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pſal. 69. 22. <hi>Let their Table be made a Snare to them;</hi> that is, Let their <hi>meats</hi> and drink, prove dangerous to their health and happineſs.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Wo unto thee Corazim, wo unto thee Bethſaida.</hi> So <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 15. - 3. 5. where the <hi>places</hi> ſignifie the <hi>inhabitants</hi> of them, and thoſe heavy judgments denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt their <hi>impenitency</hi> and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="22" facs="tcp:47052:25"/>Luke 15. 18. <hi>I have ſinned againſt Heaven,</hi> that is, God himſelf; for altho' he is Omnipreſent, and ſo in <hi>all</hi> places of the World at the very <hi>ſame</hi> time, yet if we can ſay God dwells <hi>any</hi> where, we may more <hi>properly</hi> ſay, he is in <hi>heaven.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The <hi>name</hi> of the things <hi>repreſented</hi> is ſometimes uſed to expreſs the <hi>ſign</hi> of it: thus,</p>
                        <p>Ezek. 7. 27. <hi>The Prince ſhall be Cloathed with Sadneſs and deſolation;</hi> that is, with <hi>ſuch</hi> garments, as are the <hi>proper</hi> expreſſions or <hi>ſigns</hi> of mourning and lamentation.</p>
                        <p>Mark 14. 22. <hi>Jeſus took Bread, and bleſſed it, and Brake it, and gave it to his diſciples, ſaying, Take, eat, This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:</hi> where the Verb ſubſtantive, <hi>is,</hi> muſt not be taken in the ſtricteſt ſence; but there it muſt be <hi>expounded</hi> thus, this Bread is <hi>repreſentative</hi> of, or <hi>ſignifies</hi> my Body broken, being to you all, a <hi>ſenſible</hi> ſign or reſemblance of it. <hi>Wine</hi> is ſometimes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſt's <hi>Blood.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Matt. 26. 27, 28. Our Saviour <hi>took the Cup and gave it to them, ſaying, Drink ye all of it; for this is my Blood:</hi> which is a <hi>figurative</hi> expreſſion; <hi>Nomenrei ſignatae,</hi> pro <hi>Signo;</hi> and how very abſurd is the Conſequence, if you ſuppoſe there is no Figure, and that the words muſt be taken
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47052:25"/>
in their literal ſtricteſt ſence? For then the Article, <hi>this,</hi> referrs to the <hi>cup,</hi> and ſo, <hi>this cup</hi> is my blood; which is ſuch an Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, that to avoid ſuch a plain Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, we muſt confeſs, that nothing elſe can with any tolerable ſence, be there ſignified by thoſe words; but that the <hi>wine</hi> contained in the Cup, repreſents, or is a <hi>manifeſt</hi> ſign of my <hi>blood:</hi> And that this is a <hi>true</hi> and proper explication of the words, is ſtill <hi>more</hi> plain from the next Verſe, <hi>v.</hi> 29. where our Saviour aſſures his Diſciples, that although he commands them <hi>all</hi> to drink of it; but, ſays he, <hi>I will drink no more of the Fruit of the vine;</hi> where he himſelf plainly calls it <hi>wine,</hi> immediately after he gave it to his Diſciples, although in <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. he calls it his <hi>blood.</hi> But I referr you to a Treatiſe upon this Subject written by his Grace, the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> where this abſurd Doctrine of Tranſubſtantion is ſufficiently expoſed.</p>
                        <p>Gen. 17. 10. <hi>This is my Covenant, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Male-child ſhall be circumciſed;</hi> where <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> the Sign or <hi>Condition</hi> of it, is yet called the <hi>Covenant</hi> it <hi>ſelf.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>1 Sam. 18. 7. <hi>Saul hath ſlain his Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and David his Ten thouſands:</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonymia Subjecti, <hi>Dux,</hi> pro <hi>Exercitu;</hi> the Armies of theſe two <hi>Generals</hi> had <hi>done</hi> ſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:47052:26"/>
                        <head>Metonymy of the Adjunct.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Metonymy</hi> of the <hi>Adjunct;</hi> when that which belongs to any thing, ſerves to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent</hi> the thing it ſelf: thus,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They ſhall bring down my Gray-hairs with ſorrow to the Grave;</hi> that is, <hi>me,</hi> that now am <hi>Gray</hi> and <hi>old</hi> in years.</p>
                        <p>Gen. 31. 53. <hi>Jacob ſware by the Fear of his father Iſaac;</hi> that is, by the <hi>God,</hi> whom <hi>Iſaac feared.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>2 Kings 20. 1. <hi>Set thine houſe in order;</hi> meaning his <hi>houſhold affairs.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The <hi>time</hi> is put for <hi>things</hi> that are <hi>done,</hi> or are <hi>in</hi> time.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>My Times are in thy Hands;</hi> that is, my <hi>life</hi> and <hi>continuation</hi> of it is in thy Power.</p>
                        <p>John 12. 27. <hi>Save me from this hour;</hi> that is, from that <hi>Agony</hi> and <hi>Paſſion</hi> I muſt undergo at <hi>that</hi> very time.</p>
                        <p>Eph. 5. 16. <hi>The Days are evil;</hi> that is, The <hi>men</hi> of theſe times are ſo.</p>
                        <p>Job 32. 7. <hi>I ſaid, Days ſhould ſpeak, and Multitude of years ſhould Teach wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> that is, <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>great</hi> age and <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> ſhould inſtruct us.<note place="margin">The Sign for the Thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by it.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The <hi>Sign</hi> is commonly uſed to expreſs the very <hi>Thing</hi> ſignified by it.</p>
                        <p>A <hi>Throne</hi> is put for a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> Pſalm 89. 4.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="25" facs="tcp:47052:26"/>
                           <hi>Sceptre</hi> ſignifies <hi>regal</hi> Power, <hi>Gen. 49. v. 10. The Sceptre ſhould not depart from Judah.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Rom. 13. 4. <hi>He beareth not the Sword in vain;</hi> that is, <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Phil. 2. 10. <hi>At the Name of Jeſus eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knee ſhall bow;</hi> that is, at the <hi>Perſon,</hi> when his <hi>name</hi> is mentioned.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The Goſpel of Uncircumciſion was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to me, as the Goſpel of Circumciſion was to Peter;</hi> that is, <hi>Paul</hi> had the <hi>ſame</hi> Commiſſion, to go and inſtruct the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> had, to teach the <hi>Jews;</hi> theſe two terms being ſigns of <hi>diſtinction</hi> between them, <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>Uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>His enemies lick the Duſt;</hi> a ſign of <hi>ſlavery</hi> and ſubjection, and ſo ſignifies their enemies ſhould be <hi>ſlaves</hi> to them.</p>
                        <p>Lament. 2. 10. <hi>The elders of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Sion ſit upon the Ground, and keep Silence; they have caſt up dirt upon their heads, they have girt themſelves with ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath, the virgins of Jeruſalem hang down their heads to the ground:</hi> meaning, they were in mighty <hi>ſorrows</hi> and afflictions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed very ſenſibly by all theſe <hi>mournfull</hi> ſigns and repreſentations.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:47052:27"/>
                           <hi>Antecedent,</hi> or that which goes before, is put for the Conſequent of it: Thus;</p>
                        <p>Rom. 2. 5. <hi>After thy impenitent heart, treaſureſt up wrath unto thy ſelf;</hi> that is, <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> as the natural reſult of our diſobedience.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>He that eateth or drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation:</hi> but the word <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> implies no more than judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment or condemnation, which are <hi>antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> to his damnation hereafter.</p>
                        <p>Pſal. 105. 44. <hi>He gave their labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the locuſt;</hi> where <hi>labour</hi> ſignifies, the <hi>profit</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> ariſing from it, the very <hi>fruits</hi> of all their <hi>labour</hi> and induſtry.</p>
                        <p>Prov. 24. 27. <hi>It is not good to know the face in judgment;</hi> not that the <hi>bare</hi> notice, or the acquaintance with a Perſon, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient in it ſelf: but there is an unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Conſequence often attends, which is <hi>favour</hi> and <hi>partiality,</hi> to him, in matters of <hi>judgment</hi> and juſtice.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>IRONIE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ironie</hi> is a ſort of a Trope or Figure, by which we ſpeak contrary to our very Thoughts; ſaying one thing, but meaning what is very different to it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:47052:27"/>2 Sam. 6. 20. <hi>How glorious was the King of Iſrael to day?</hi> that is, how <hi>ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?</hi> how <hi>diſhonourable?</hi> See the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text.</p>
                     <p>Job 12. 2. <hi>No doubt but ye are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and wiſdom ſhall die with you:</hi> as if he ſaid; You, ſurely, fanſie your ſelves to be <hi>extreamly</hi> wiſe; and that all wiſdom ſhall <hi>periſh</hi> with <hi>you;</hi> which is a tacit reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their imprudent cenſure, in accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Job</hi> of <hi>ſome</hi> impiety, as if God's judgments upon him was an <hi>infallible</hi> ſign of his <hi>wicked</hi> life; this very opinion is <hi>condemned,</hi> Luke 13. 4.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 37. 19. <hi>Behold this Maſter of dreams cometh:</hi> this was ſaid not without the <hi>higheſt</hi> ſcorn and deriſion of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when their <hi>opinion</hi> of his Interpretation about them, was <hi>otherwiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Amos 4. 4. <hi>Come to Bethel, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs at Gilgal, multiply tranſgreſſions, and bring your ſacrifices every morning:</hi> As if the Prophet ſaid, Come, Make <hi>haſt,</hi> and make <hi>preparation</hi> to offer Sacrifices in your worſhip of Idols: but then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, you ſhall not go <hi>unpuniſhed</hi> for theſe Offences. And if at firſt ſight the words ſeem to be ſome kind of Invitation to the practice of Idolatry; yet really they are the <hi>higheſt</hi> diſſuaſion from it <hi>imaginable.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:47052:28"/>Eccleſ. 11. 9. <hi>Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart chear thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the ſight of thy eyes:</hi> Now what <hi>literal</hi> Expoſitor would not <hi>preſently</hi> take this <hi>advice</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi> to the <hi>young</hi> man, to be a very <hi>great</hi> encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, now he is in the <hi>flower</hi> of his youth, to make the very beſt <hi>uſe</hi> of his time, and to <hi>purſue</hi> all kind of <hi>ſenſual</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? and yet, Are they not the ſevereſt <hi>check</hi> imaginable, to ſtop the <hi>courſe</hi> of his ſinfull Life?—<hi>But know thou, that for all theſe things, God will bring thee into judgment:</hi> This indeed was an <hi>amazing</hi> Sentence; and ſufficient, one would <hi>think,</hi> to <hi>ſtrike</hi> his Soul, and <hi>force</hi> her to conſider the <hi>dangerous</hi> conſequence of Sin. Go on, but yet <hi>remember,</hi> there is a day of <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> when you muſt give a moſt <hi>ſevere</hi> account, of all your Exceſs and Senſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to the <hi>ſupream</hi> Judge of Men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
                     <p>1 Kings 18. 27. Thus <hi>Elijah</hi> adviſeth the Prophets of <hi>Baal, Cry aloud, for he is a God, either he is talking, or he is purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or he is in a journey, or peradventure he ſleepeth, and he muſt be awaked:</hi> As if the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaid, Cry <hi>aloud,</hi> ye <hi>Prophets,</hi> for perhaps your God is <hi>full</hi> of <hi>thought</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:47052:28"/>
and <hi>contemplation,</hi> and diſcourſing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; or poſſibly your God cannot preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>hear</hi> the ſound of your Voices. Cry <hi>aloud,</hi> perhaps your God is in a full <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit</hi> of his <hi>enemies;</hi> or poſſibly he may be <hi>ſleepy</hi> and <hi>drowzie,</hi> and you muſt <hi>awaken</hi> him by your exceſſive Noiſes. And it came to paſs, that <hi>Elijah mocked;</hi> and the Event was a very ſufficient <hi>demonſtration</hi> of it.</p>
                     <p>2 Cor. 12. 13. <hi>What was it wherein<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you were inferiour to other Churches, except it be, that I my ſelf was not burthenſome to you? forgive me this wrong:</hi> as if S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, You differ from <hi>no</hi> Church planted by <hi>any</hi> of the Apoſtles, but only in this <hi>one</hi> particular, that I put you to <hi>no</hi> kind of <hi>charges</hi> for the <hi>relief</hi> of <hi>my</hi> Neceſſities; and this, I hope, was ſuch a kind of <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſuch a <hi>trouble,</hi> as you, I ſuppoſe, can <hi>eaſily</hi> pardon. Forgive me this wrong, that I was not <hi>ſo</hi> very <hi>chargeable</hi> to you, as <hi>ſome</hi> of the Apoſtles have been to <hi>other</hi> Churches. This was a very <hi>gentile</hi> and pleaſant way of <hi>reprehenſion,</hi> and carries with it more force and <hi>power</hi> of Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than a more <hi>ſerious</hi> way of argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                     <p>2 Cor. 10. 12. <hi>For we dare make our ſelves of the number, or compare our ſelves
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47052:29"/>
with ſome, that commend themſelves:</hi> tho' Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had very <hi>great</hi> qualifications, and therefore had much more <hi>tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to compare <hi>himſelf</hi> with other men, eſpecially with <hi>thoſe,</hi> who in all reſpects, were <hi>ſo</hi> very much <hi>inſeriour</hi> to our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; yet ſtill we <hi>dare</hi> not preſume, to make the leaſt <hi>compariſons. How</hi> pleaſantly does St. <hi>Paul reprove</hi> the <hi>Pride,</hi> the <hi>Arrogance,</hi> the vain <hi>preſumption</hi> of ſome <hi>falſe</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who pleaſed themſelves with falſe <hi>applauſes</hi> of their <hi>own</hi> merits; and flatter'd themſelves, that <hi>others</hi> were in <hi>no</hi> reſpect <hi>comparable</hi> to them.</p>
                     <p>—<hi>Maſter, we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the way of God in truth neither careſt thou for any man: for thou regardeſt not the perſon of man:</hi> Now that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the moſt <hi>ſincere</hi> Lover of <hi>truth,</hi> not <hi>handling</hi> the Word of God <hi>deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in <hi>compliance</hi> to <hi>humane</hi> paſſions, and <hi>infirmities,</hi> cannot be <hi>denied</hi> without the <hi>higheſt</hi> Blaſphemy; yet the hypocritical <hi>Phariſee</hi> ſaid this, in a way of <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>deriſion</hi> of him; and not as if it was in the <hi>leaſt</hi> conformable to <hi>their</hi> opinion of our <hi>Saviour</hi> Chriſt; but all this <hi>ſolemn</hi> Preface was only made uſe of as a more <hi>artificial</hi> expedient to <hi>betray</hi> Chriſt, to deliver his <hi>opinion</hi> with <hi>more</hi> freedom,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47052:29"/>
concerning the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of giving <hi>tribute</hi> to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> for the <hi>queſtion</hi> was very <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous,</hi> and to <hi>determine</hi> either for, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> was almoſt <hi>equally</hi> dangerous; if he declares in <hi>favour</hi> of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> then he is no longer a <hi>friend</hi> to the <hi>common</hi> People; and if Chriſt <hi>anſwered,</hi> that the <hi>payment</hi> of tribute was <hi>unlawfull;</hi> he had been <hi>preſently</hi> found <hi>guilty</hi> of <hi>Sedition;</hi> this was <hi>their</hi> Motive to this <hi>inſidious</hi> Queſtion, and that <hi>pompous</hi> Introduction to it, was only look'd upon by them as a more effectual and <hi>plauſible</hi> way to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him. But Jeſus <hi>perceived</hi> their <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> their <hi>diſſimulation,</hi> their vile <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie;</hi> and ſays, <hi>Why</hi> do ye endeavour, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this <hi>ſpecious</hi> pretence of <hi>reſpect</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, to <hi>enſnare</hi> me? <hi>Why tempt</hi> ye me, ye <hi>Hypocrites?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matt. 2. 8. <hi>Go,</hi> ſays <hi>Herod</hi> to the Wiſe Men, <hi>and ſearch diligently for the young child, and when you have found him, bring me word again, that I may come, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him:</hi> Thus the <hi>Tyrant</hi> diſguiſeth his moſt <hi>villainous</hi> deſign, under the <hi>colour</hi> of an <hi>honourable</hi> reſpect; when his <hi>intention</hi> was to <hi>deſtroy</hi> and murther him, as appears from <hi>Verſe</hi> 16.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:47052:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>A <hi>METAPHOR.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A <hi>Metaphor</hi> is an <hi>artificial</hi> Tranſlation of a word, from the <hi>proper</hi> ſignification of it to <hi>another,</hi> becauſe there is <hi>ſome</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion between the <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> and the very thing <hi>ſignified.</hi> This kind of Trope is <hi>extreamly</hi> pleaſant, and not without <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</hi> uſe; for it <hi>inriches</hi> our mind with <hi>two</hi> Idea's at the very <hi>ſame</hi> time, with the <hi>truth,</hi> and the <hi>ſimilitude.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Deut. 32. 42. <hi>I will make my arrows drunk with bloud, and my ſword ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour fleſh:</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> Metaphor is borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>exceſſive</hi> and intemperate <hi>drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> intimating to us the mighty <hi>effuſion</hi> of blood, and the exceeding <hi>greatneſs</hi> of their ruin and deſtruction. The <hi>ſecond</hi> is taken from the moſt eager and <hi>hungry</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of a beaſt; which makes the <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of death come much more <hi>lively</hi> to the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and how impoſſible it is for us to eſcape the <hi>edge</hi> of the Sword, when God himſelf is concerned in <hi>our</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and execution.</p>
                     <p>Zech. 9. 14 <hi>His Arrows ſhall go forth as lightning.</hi> A very <hi>proper</hi> ſimile to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their <hi>ſwift</hi> death and <hi>execution.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:47052:30"/>Hoſ. 5. 12. <hi>I will be unto Ephraim, as a Moth;</hi> which expreſſion repreſents to us <hi>inſenſible</hi> decay and ruin; as a Moth <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly</hi> fretting a Garment, ſo <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſhall ſilently <hi>conſume</hi> away, by the moſt ſecret and <hi>unaccountable</hi> ways.</p>
                     <p>Matt. 5. 13. <hi>Ye are the Salt of the Earth;</hi> for as 'tis the property of Salt to <hi>preſerve</hi> any thing from its <hi>Putrefaction,</hi> ſo the <hi>doctrines</hi> of the Apoſtles were to <hi>ſeaſon</hi> our minds, and preſerve and <hi>purifie</hi> us from all <hi>immoral</hi> Corruptions or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities.</p>
                     <p>Pſal. 91. 5, 6. <hi>Thou ſhalt not be afraid for the terror by night, nor for the arrow that flieth by day, nor for the Peſtilence that walketh in darkneſs;</hi> and the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſtill gives us a more lively and ſenſible notion of the <hi>ſecret</hi> Malignity of the Plague, and how it ruins and deſtroys us after <hi>inviſible</hi> ways and degrees; ſo that the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of it becomes <hi>irreſiſtible.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Job 6. 4. <hi>For the arrows of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are within we; the poiſon thereof drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up my ſpirit; the terrors of the Lord ſet themſelves in array againſt me;</hi> the term is <hi>military;</hi> when an Army of Men put themſelves in a <hi>poſture</hi> to <hi>attack</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſs</hi> their Enemies.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:47052:31"/>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 16. God is ſaid to <hi>dwell in Light, which no man can approach unto:</hi> Which Metaphor conveys to our Mind a <hi>ſtronger</hi> notion of his <hi>incomprehenſible</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and forbids our <hi>reaſon</hi> to make cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>enquiries</hi> after God, who is <hi>inacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> is to our <hi>Eye</hi> when it <hi>ſhines</hi> out in its brighteſt <hi>glory.</hi> Why then doſt thou <hi>dive</hi> into <hi>abſtruſe</hi> and myſterious Truths <hi>concerning</hi> the Bleſſed Trinity? for with <hi>Job</hi> the Queſtion is, <hi>Chap. 11. v.</hi> 7. reſolved, that all <hi>ſuch</hi> Enquiries are <hi>unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; Canſt thou find out God unto Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;</hi> that is, 'tis all in <hi>vain,</hi> for 'tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> ſo to doe.</p>
                     <p>Numb. 6. 25. <hi>The Lord make his face to ſhine upon thee;</hi> that is, the Lord be <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> and <hi>favourable</hi> to thee, as the Sun looks moſt <hi>kindly</hi> upon us when it <hi>appears</hi> in its brighteſt <hi>luſtre</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>—<hi>But unto you that fear my name, ſhall the Sun of righteouſneſs ariſe with Healing in his wings:</hi> This is a very <hi>live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Compariſon between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Sun, which by his <hi>refreſhing</hi> influence, <hi>warms</hi> every thing into <hi>life.</hi> So our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> alſo, by the <hi>comfortable</hi> heat and <hi>effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of his <hi>perfect</hi> Righteouſneſs, brings <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and quickens, and <hi>revives</hi> all who were <hi>ſpiritually</hi> dead, and who
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47052:31"/>
before <hi>his</hi> appearance ſate in <hi>darkneſs</hi> and in the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſometimes called a <hi>Star,</hi> Num. 24. 17. becauſe his <hi>appearance</hi> brought more <hi>light</hi> of Knowledge into the <hi>world.</hi> He is ſometimes called a <hi>Sceptre,</hi> to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his <hi>royal</hi> Office; and ſometimes a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to expreſs his <hi>love</hi> and <hi>affection;</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Shepherd,</hi> which <hi>kind</hi> appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion declares his <hi>care</hi> and watchfulneſs over us. He is termed the <hi>ſpiritual Rock,</hi> of which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did drink in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17. 6. 1 Cor. 10. 4. <hi>for they drank of that ſpiritual rock that followed them, and that rock was Chriſt;</hi> that is, did <hi>ſacramentally</hi> repreſent <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who being <hi>ſmitten</hi> by his Father, did by the <hi>precious</hi> effuſion of <hi>his</hi> blood, <hi>deliver</hi> us from death.</p>
                     <p>Judges 5. 20. <hi>They fought from heaven, the ſtars from heaven fought againſt Siſera;</hi> which is a <hi>military</hi> Expreſſion, but here it may ſignifie no more, than that the very <hi>ſtars</hi> by their <hi>ſecret</hi> influences did ſome way or other <hi>contribute</hi> to their <hi>overthrow,</hi> perhaps by cauſing <hi>great</hi> Falls of <hi>Rain</hi> or <hi>Snow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Coloſ. 2. 17. Which are but a ſhadow of things to come;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>tranſitory</hi> ſigns or <hi>repreſentations,</hi> but the <hi>body,</hi> or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:47052:32"/>
or the <hi>reality</hi> of theſe Myſteries, are <hi>oppoſite</hi> to <hi>ancient</hi> Ceremonies, as much as <hi>body</hi> is to <hi>ſhadow;</hi> for what are <hi>ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> but as it were the firſt <hi>drawings</hi> or ſhadows of a <hi>Picture,</hi> which <hi>ſtrokes</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineations all <hi>vaniſh</hi> and diſappear as the <hi>life</hi> and perfection of it is <hi>coming</hi> on.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 139. 2. <hi>Thou underſtandeſt my thoughts afar off:</hi> A Metaphor taken from a <hi>proſpect</hi> of any thing at a <hi>great</hi> diſtance from us; but in a proper ſence, the phraſe <hi>aſſures</hi> us, that God by the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite</hi> power of his <hi>preſcience,</hi> knows our <hi>thoughts</hi> before they <hi>ſpring</hi> up in the <hi>ſoul;</hi> and yet this <hi>infinite</hi> view of them gives no <hi>determinations</hi> to them; for by his <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> underſtanding, how does God <hi>foreſee</hi> all the <hi>various</hi> turns and reflections of the mind, and how the <hi>ſoul</hi> after many ways of thinking, will at <hi>laſt</hi> reſolve to put <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> deſign in <hi>execution;</hi> ſo that this <hi>infinite</hi> proſpect of <hi>our</hi> thoughts derives no <hi>neceſſary</hi> power and <hi>influence</hi> upon <hi>them.</hi> To uſe a lower Inſtance; And if you your ſelf could <hi>foreſee</hi> that your friend after <hi>many</hi> changes of <hi>his</hi> mind, would <hi>certainly</hi> travel into <hi>Italy,</hi> ſuch a <hi>previous</hi> knowledge of his <hi>affairs</hi> and deſigns, by <hi>no</hi> means gives any <hi>byas</hi> to them; neither is he obliged by any power
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47052:32"/>
of yours, to <hi>proſecute</hi> his journey.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>SYNECDOCHE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend:</hi> This Trope is a <hi>form</hi> of ſpeaking, when we make uſe of words that are <hi>more</hi> comprehenſive, for others which are <hi>leſs:</hi> and ſo on the <hi>contrary,</hi> when we put the <hi>name</hi> of a <hi>part</hi> to ſignifie the <hi>whole,</hi> or elſe the name of the <hi>whole</hi> to expreſs any <hi>particular</hi> part of it; as if you ſay, the Plague is in <hi>France,</hi> when perhaps 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Paris.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are four <hi>ſorts</hi> or ſpecies belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Figure.</p>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Synecdoche Generis.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. <hi>Synecdoche Generis,</hi> when a <hi>general</hi> word <hi>comprehends</hi> a <hi>particular,</hi> or when the <hi>univerſal</hi> denotes the <hi>ſpecial</hi> term. Thus:</p>
                        <p>Luke 2. 1. <hi>It came to paſs that all the world was to be taxed;</hi> meaning the <hi>whole Roman</hi> Empire, a ſmall, though very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, part of the World.</p>
                        <p>Exod. 9. 6. <hi>And all the cattel of Egypt died;</hi> which ſignifies not univerſally, as if <hi>every</hi> kind of Beaſt were deſtroyed, but only, or at leaſt <hi>chiefly,</hi> thoſe that then were in the <hi>fields;</hi> for that <hi>ſome</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved alive is plain enough from <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="38" facs="tcp:47052:33"/>Thus, <hi>All fleſh,</hi> Gen. 6. 12. and <hi>All Creatures,</hi> Mark 16. 15. ſignifie <hi>man</hi> only.</p>
                        <p>And, <hi>Every Creature,</hi> implies only <hi>ſome</hi> of each ſort, and not <hi>all</hi> of <hi>every</hi> kind, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. 8.</p>
                        <p>So, <hi>All manner of four footed beaſts,</hi> ſignifies a very <hi>great</hi> number, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 12.</p>
                        <p>Exod. 20. 10. <hi>Thou ſhalt not doe any manner of work on the Sabbath day;</hi> that is, no <hi>toilſome</hi> and ſervile labour, which is the <hi>buſineſs</hi> of <hi>every</hi> other day; where the <hi>univerſal</hi> term of <hi>negation</hi> is limited and <hi>reſtrained</hi> to a particular Negative. So,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ye ſhall not ſwear at all,</hi> is a <hi>prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> not excluding all <hi>manner</hi> of Oaths, but ſuch only as are <hi>raſh</hi> and not <hi>requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> in a <hi>judicial</hi> way by the <hi>ſupreme</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
                        <p>Matt. 27. 44. <hi>The thieves alſo,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>which were crucified with him upbraided him;</hi> where the <hi>plural</hi> Number denotes the <hi>ſingular,</hi> for only <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>two</hi> Thieves did <hi>vilifie</hi> our Saviour, as appears from <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 39.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Synecdoche Speciei.</head>
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>Synecdoche Speciei,</hi> when a <hi>particular</hi> word or expreſſion of a more <hi>narrow</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification does imply one of a <hi>general</hi> and larger <hi>notification.</hi> Thus,</p>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:47052:33"/>
                        <p>James 1. 27. <hi>Pure religion is this, to viſit the fatherleſs and the widow in their affliction;</hi> which are but a very <hi>narrow</hi> compaſs of Religion; but they are taken <hi>more</hi> generally, for <hi>any</hi> Perſons under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ſort</hi> of <hi>Calamity.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Exod. 3. 8. <hi>A Land flowing with milk and honey;</hi> that is, abounding with <hi>all</hi> things <hi>good</hi> and <hi>deſirable.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> two proper Names, ſignifie the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> a word of <hi>larger</hi> extent, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63. 16.</p>
                        <p>Exod. 20. <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother,</hi> is a duty <hi>more</hi> univerſal, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to pay <hi>obedience</hi> and reverence to <hi>all</hi> Superiours, eſpecially <hi>thoſe</hi> in <hi>high</hi> Authority.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Synecdoche Totius.</head>
                        <p n="3">3. <hi>Synecdoche Totius,</hi> when the Name of the <hi>whole</hi> ſerves to denote a <hi>part</hi> of it. Thus,</p>
                        <p>Luke 23. 43. <hi>To day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe;</hi> where the word <hi>thou</hi> ſeems to comprehend the <hi>whole</hi> man; but it ſignifies his <hi>ſoul</hi> only, <hi>without</hi> his <hi>body.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>2 Pet. 3. 6. <hi>The whole world being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed with water;</hi> that is, the <hi>earth,</hi> the <hi>loweſt</hi> part of the world.</p>
                        <p>Dan. 2. 4. <hi>O King, live for ever:</hi> where all <hi>duration</hi> of time, even to Eternity, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47052:34"/>
a <hi>long</hi> part of time, <hi>for ever,</hi> that is, for a <hi>long</hi> time.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="subsection">
                        <head>Synecdoche Partis.</head>
                        <p n="4">4. <hi>Synecdoche Partis,</hi> when the Name of a <hi>Part</hi> or Member is made uſe of to notifie the <hi>whole</hi> thing or perſon.</p>
                        <p>Acts. 27. 37. <hi>And we were all in the Ship, two hundred threeſcore and ſixteen ſouls:</hi> where the <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> comprehends the <hi>whole</hi> man.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And the evening and the morning were the firſt day;</hi> where the <hi>principal</hi> parts of the day ſignifie the <hi>entire</hi> ſpaces of <hi>day</hi> and <hi>night.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="figure" type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Figures in the <hi>Repetition</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> Sound.</head>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>EPIZE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>XIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epizeuxis,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>to join to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> This Figure repeats the <hi>ſame</hi> word in the ſame Sentence, by way of <hi>emphaſis,</hi> and ſo gives <hi>more</hi> life and <hi>paſſion</hi> to our <hi>diſcourſes:</hi> Thus:</p>
                     <p>How does Holy <hi>David</hi> expreſs himſelf in an <hi>infinite</hi> Paſſion, upon the <hi>death</hi> of his Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 Sam. 18. 33. <hi>O my ſon Abſalom, my ſon, my ſon Abſalom, would God I had died for thee, O Abſalom my
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47052:34"/>
ſon, my ſon:</hi> How often are the very <hi>ſame</hi> words over and over again; to ſignifie, if <hi>poſſible,</hi> the <hi>mighty</hi> grief and <hi>anguiſh</hi> of his Soul, for the <hi>irreparable</hi> loſs of his <hi>dearly</hi> beloved Son.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 22. 1. <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> See <hi>Matth.</hi> 27. 46. The words are <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Complainings,</hi> moſt earneſtly lamenting, that God <hi>himſelf</hi> was <hi>departed</hi> from him, even when his <hi>Divine</hi> preſence was moſt <hi>needfull</hi> to preſerve him from the <hi>approach</hi> of ſome <hi>imminent</hi> danger, but in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt</hi> figured by <hi>David,</hi> they are the expreſſions of his <hi>Humanity,</hi> repreſenting the <hi>extreme</hi> Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Paſſion, and the <hi>inexpreſſible</hi> Pains and Torments. See <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. 38, 39. <hi>My ſoul,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, is exceeding ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, even unto death.</hi> See alſo <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 44.</p>
                     <p>Luke 23. 21. <hi>But they cryed, ſaying, Crucifie him, Crucifie him;</hi> repreſenting to us their <hi>moſt</hi> violent <hi>Importunities,</hi> and <hi>loud</hi> Clamours of the People againſt his <hi>Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Acts 9. 4. <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me:</hi> A very earneſt and paſſionate Expoſtulation from <hi>heaven,</hi> to move and <hi>perſuade Saul,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>no</hi> longer <hi>breath</hi> out <hi>threatnings</hi> and <hi>ſlaughters</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:47052:35"/>Matt. 23. 37. <hi>Oh Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem;</hi> How is the <hi>ſame</hi> word repeated <hi>over</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain very <hi>emphatically,</hi> to give us the <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conception</hi> of God's <hi>trouble</hi> and mighty <hi>concernment</hi> for their <hi>impenitency</hi> and <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> diſobedience? See <hi>Pſalm</hi> 145. 18. <hi>Joel</hi> 1. 15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>ANADIPLOSIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anadiploſis,</hi> derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>duplico.</hi> This Figure pronounceth the <hi>ſame</hi> word in <hi>different</hi> Sentences: when the <hi>laſt</hi> word of the <hi>preceding</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is <hi>repeated</hi> in the <hi>beginning</hi> of the following: thus;</p>
                     <p>Rom. 14. 8. <hi>For whether we live, we live unto the Lord; or whether we die, we die unto the Lord:</hi> and therefore in <hi>either</hi> ſtate, 'tis <hi>our</hi> buſineſs to <hi>preſerve</hi> in our minds a <hi>lively</hi> ſenſe of <hi>God</hi>'s providence; and <hi>refer</hi> our ſelves to <hi>his</hi> care and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi> of our <hi>ſouls</hi> and <hi>bodies;</hi> ſince whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we <hi>live</hi> or <hi>die, we are the Lord's.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17.</p>
                     <p>Phil. 2. 8. <hi>He became obedient to death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even the death of the Croſs:</hi> and was it not <hi>ſtill</hi> an <hi>higher</hi> inſtance of his <hi>great</hi> Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Condeſcenſion; becauſe <hi>ſuch</hi> a ſort of <hi>death</hi> was by all <hi>reputed</hi> the moſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47052:35"/>
                        <hi>infamous</hi> and <hi>ſhamefull</hi> way of dying.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Knowing that tribulation worketh pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and patience experience, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed:</hi> thus is there a <hi>gradual</hi> progreſs from the practice of <hi>one</hi> Vertue, to <hi>another,</hi> altho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> through ſome <hi>accidental</hi> indiſpoſition of our minds. <hi>One</hi> Vertue may not <hi>promote</hi> the exerciſe of <hi>another.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>CLIMAX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Climax, gradatio;</hi> when the words are in <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Poſition,</hi> that there is a gradual <hi>aſcent</hi> from <hi>one</hi> to <hi>another:</hi> till you arrive at the <hi>laſt</hi> ſtep of the <hi>period:</hi> Thus;</p>
                     <p>Matt. 10. 40. <hi>He that receiveth you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth me; and he that receiveth me, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him that ſent me:</hi> There is here a <hi>gradual</hi> advancement in <hi>every</hi> period, and the <hi>laſt</hi> is the higheſt of all. In as much as the <hi>reſpect</hi> and honour given to God the <hi>Father,</hi> upon the <hi>reception</hi> of his Son, is much <hi>greater,</hi> than <hi>any</hi> that is paid to the <hi>Son,</hi> who, in reſpect of his <hi>humanity</hi> and his <hi>miſſion</hi> from Heaven, was <hi>inferiour</hi> to God the Father.</p>
                     <p>John 1. 11. <hi>In the beginning was the word, and the word was with God, and the word was God:</hi> In the <hi>beginning,</hi> that is,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47052:36"/>
before the <hi>creation</hi> of the world, the <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> had then his <hi>being;</hi> for if he was <hi>not</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>all</hi> things; how then could <hi>all</hi> things be <hi>made</hi> by him? The <hi>firſt</hi> word then ſignifies his <hi>eternity,</hi> the <hi>next</hi> his <hi>perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: And the word was with God;</hi> which phraſe expreſſeth a <hi>diſtinct</hi> mode or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>ſubſiſtence</hi> of the <hi>Son,</hi> from the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> becauſe <hi>no</hi> Perſon is ſaid to be <hi>with</hi> himſelf, but with <hi>another</hi> Perſon. And the <hi>laſt</hi> words expreſly aſſert his <hi>Divinity; And the word was God:</hi> See this Text expounded in a Sermon of his Grace, the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>1 Cor. 3. 22, 23. <hi>All are yours, and you are Chriſt's, and Chriſt is God's.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 8. 30. <hi>Moreover, whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called; and whom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he called, them alſo he juſtified; and whom he juſtified, them alſo he glorified.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matt. 5. 27, 28. <hi>Ye have heard, it hath been ſaid by them of old time, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I ſay unto you, That whoſoever looketh on a woman, to luſt after her, hath committed adultery with her already in his heart:</hi> So that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>morality</hi> is much more <hi>refined;</hi> and reaches not only to the <hi>external</hi> actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but even <hi>thoſe</hi> of the mind, the moſt <hi>ſecret</hi> imaginations.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:47052:36"/>Matt. 11. 9. <hi>But what went ye out for to ſee; a Prophet? yea, I ſay unto you, and more than a Prophet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matt. 8. 20. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto them, The foxes have holes, and the birds of the air have neſts; but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here, in theſe <hi>Verſes,</hi> there is a <hi>noble</hi> riſe in the ſence of the words, and without much <hi>impropriety</hi> they are <hi>reducible</hi> to this Figure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>ANAPHORA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anaphora,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>to bring back again:</hi> 'tis a <hi>repetition</hi> of a word in the <hi>beginning</hi> of <hi>ſeveral</hi> Sentences: Thus;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The voice of the Lord is powerfull, the voice of the Lord is full of majeſty,</hi> Pſal. 29. 4.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Praiſe the Lord from the Heavens, praiſe him in the height, praiſe him all his Angels, praiſe him Sun and Moon:</hi> where the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Pſalmiſt affectionately calls upon the <hi>whole</hi> order of <hi>created</hi> Beings, to ſing <hi>Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to their Maker.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is kind, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity envieth not, charity vaunteth not her ſelf:</hi> where the <hi>abſtract</hi> is made uſe of for the <hi>concrete,</hi> the <hi>charitable</hi> Perſon, <hi>Pſal. 118. v.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:47052:37"/>Jer. 50. 35, 36, 37. <hi>A Sword is upon the Chaldeans, ſaith the Lord, a ſword is upon the Inhabitants of Babylon, and upon her Princes, and upon her wiſe men, a ſword is upon her mighty men; and they ſhall be diſmayed, a ſword is upon their horſes, and upon their chariots:</hi> This <hi>induction</hi> of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, with the <hi>continual</hi> application of the <hi>ſame</hi> term to every period, renders the <hi>diſcourſe</hi> much more <hi>emphatical,</hi> and <hi>infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> into the mind a <hi>notion</hi> of <hi>univerſal</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and deſolation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>EPISTROPHE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epiſtrophe, converſio,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>verto.</hi> This Figure returns the <hi>ſame</hi> word at the end of <hi>ſeveral</hi> Clauſes: Thus;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Are they Iſraelites, ſo am I? Are they the ſeed of Abraham, ſo am I?</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 22.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Have we not propheſied in thy Name, and done miracles in thy Name?</hi> Matt. 7. 22.</p>
                     <p>See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. where, <hi>His mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever,</hi> is the <hi>concluſion</hi> of <hi>every</hi> Verſe, and very proper to expreſs the <hi>endleſs</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Mercy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>SYMPLOCE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Symploce, complicatio,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47052:37"/>
                        <hi>fold together;</hi> when the <hi>ſame</hi> ſort of words are in the <hi>beginning</hi> and in the <hi>end</hi> of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sentences.</p>
                     <p>Jer. 9. 23. <hi>Let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdom, neither let the mighty man glory in his might; let not the rich man glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his riches:</hi> And this is the very Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of God himſelf, That we ſhould not in the <hi>leaſt</hi> place our hope and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon the <hi>beſt</hi> of <hi>worldly</hi> things, but only upon <hi>God</hi> Almighty, who is only <hi>able</hi> to ſave, and <hi>defend</hi> us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>EPANALEPSIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epanalepſis, reſumptio,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>accipio.</hi> This Figure makes uſe of the <hi>ſame</hi> word or expreſſion in the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> and <hi>ending</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> Sentence.</p>
                     <p>Phil. 4. 4. <hi>Rejoice in the Lord always, and again, I ſay, Rejoice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 Sam. 18. 33. O <hi>Abſalom, my ſon, my ſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>EPANADOS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epanados, regreſſio.</hi> This Figure em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys the <hi>ſame</hi> word at the <hi>beginning</hi> and <hi>middle</hi> of a Sentence, or in the <hi>middle</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of it; as if they were <hi>inverted,</hi>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:47052:38"/>
and the contrary ſence turned upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 5. 20. <hi>Wo unto them who call good evil, and evil good; who put light for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and darkneſs for light.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 7. 19. <hi>For the good that I would, I doe not; but the evil which I would not, that I doe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How are the terms here <hi>inverted? good</hi> is the <hi>object</hi> of his will, but ſtill 'tis <hi>impracticable;</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> tho' <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>his</hi> will and <hi>intention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> yet <hi>that</hi> he puts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>practice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>John 8. 47. <hi>He that is of God, heareth God's word; ye therefore hear it not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye are not of God;</hi> that is, becauſe ye are not <hi>regenerate</hi> by his <hi>Spirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 Cor. 2. 15, 16. <hi>For we are unto God a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh; to the one we are the ſavour of death unto death, and to the other the ſavour of life unto life:</hi> that is, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is preached to <hi>all</hi> perſons, without <hi>any</hi> diſtinction, but the bleſſed <hi>efficacy</hi> of it, is <hi>extreamly</hi> diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and varies according to the <hi>diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>receiver;</hi> for 'tis <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the <hi>believer;</hi> but to the <hi>faithleſs</hi> and diſobedient, <hi>inevitable</hi> death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:47052:38"/>
                     <head>PARONOMASIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paronomaſia,</hi> a likeneſs of words; deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which in <hi>compoſition,</hi> ſignifies with <hi>alteration,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>a name,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>to change</hi> or <hi>allude to a name.</hi> This Figure employs the <hi>ſame</hi> word to a very <hi>different</hi> purpoſe, and ſometimes it changes <hi>one</hi> letter or ſyllable of a word to <hi>another ſence</hi> and ſignification.</p>
                     <p>Matt. 8. 22. <hi>Let the dead, bury their dead:</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> words ſignifie a <hi>moral</hi> death, thoſe that are <hi>dead</hi> in <hi>treſpaſſes</hi> and ſins; but the <hi>laſt</hi> imply a <hi>natural</hi> death, ſuch as are dead and <hi>departed</hi> this life.</p>
                     <p>2 Cor. 10. 3. <hi>Though we walk in the fleſh, yet we do not war after the fleſh:</hi> though we are <hi>men,</hi> and made in the <hi>ſame</hi> faſhion like <hi>other</hi> men; yet in <hi>this</hi> reſpect we <hi>differ</hi> from them, for we <hi>place</hi> no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the <hi>arm</hi> of fleſh, no <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> from the <hi>world,</hi> but all our <hi>ſufficiency</hi> is from God.</p>
                     <p>2 Cor. 6. 9. <hi>As unknown, and yet well known; as dying, and behold we live:</hi> tho' <hi>ſome</hi> may look upon us, as if they were not ſo <hi>deſirous</hi> to know us in our afflictions; yet others eſteem and value us the <hi>more,</hi> and are <hi>willing</hi> to know us in the <hi>greateſt</hi> of our Calamities.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:47052:39"/>
                     <head>PLOCE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ploce,</hi> derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>to bind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> This Figure <hi>pronounceth</hi> a word ſo <hi>emphatically,</hi> that it denotes not only the <hi>thing</hi> ſignified, but alſo the very <hi>quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of it; thus 'tis no <hi>unuſual</hi> thing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the <hi>proper</hi> name of a man, to expreſs ſome <hi>remarkable</hi> vertue belonging to him; as we may ſay, In <hi>that</hi> action <hi>Alexander</hi> was <hi>Alexander,</hi> that is, a mighty Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 27. 36. <hi>Is he not rightly called Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eſau, for he hath ſupplanted me theſe two times.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>POLYPTOTON.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Polyptoton,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>variatio caſuum.</hi> This Figure employs <hi>words</hi> of the ſame derivation, but <hi>alters</hi> the <hi>termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> or the Mood, Caſe, or Gender.</p>
                     <p>Rom. 2. 21. <hi>Thou that preacheſt, a man ſhould not ſteal, doſt thou ſteal?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 11. 16. <hi>For of him, and through him, and to him, are all things;</hi> that is, God is <hi>ſupream,</hi> and diſpoſeth <hi>every</hi> thing to <hi>ſerve</hi> the wiſe ends of his <hi>providence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:47052:39"/>2 Tim. 3. 13. <hi>But evil men and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived.</hi> See the <hi>various</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the ſame words, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 14.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Figures in <hi>reference</hi> to a <hi>ſentence,</hi> are ſuch as affect the <hi>whole</hi> ſentence, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>ſome</hi> emotion of the <hi>Soul.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>ECPHONESIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ecphoneſis,</hi> Exclamation. This is a moſt <hi>pathetical</hi> ſort of Figure, whereby the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator</hi> diſcovers the <hi>exceſſive</hi> paſſion of his <hi>own</hi> mind, and ſo makes a <hi>ſuitable</hi> impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon the <hi>affections</hi> of his Audience.</p>
                     <p>This Figure is varied many ways. Firſt, In a way of <hi>wonder</hi> and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's infinite Perfections<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom 11. 33. <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God! How unſearchable are his judgements, and his ways paſt finding out?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, In a way of <hi>ſorrow</hi> and mourning, for God's <hi>abſence,</hi> or of his <hi>diſregard</hi> to the <hi>voice</hi> of our Petitions.</p>
                     <p>Pſal. 22. 1, 2. <hi>My God, my God, Why haſt thou forſaken me? O my God, I cry
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47052:40"/>
in the day time, but thou heareſt not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 6. 5. <hi>Wo is me, for I am undone;</hi> Thus, in a way of <hi>deſperation,</hi> how is the Prophet <hi>extreamly</hi> ſenſible of his <hi>own</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, as if he thought the <hi>forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of his ſin was now <hi>impoſſible;</hi> this was the <hi>dreadfull</hi> apprehenſion of men in <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> times, when God did more <hi>ſignally</hi> manifeſt himſelf, <hi>Deut. 5. 25. Judg.</hi> 6. 22. and 13. 22.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, In a way of <hi>expoſtulation</hi> with God himſelf, for his Mercy and Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ob remember that my life is wind;</hi> Thus he makes the <hi>ſhort</hi> continuance of his being, a very great <hi>inducement,</hi> that God ſhould be more <hi>indulgent</hi> to him, and preſerve him from <hi>ſudden</hi> ruin and deſtruction.</p>
                     <p>Rom. 7. 24. <hi>O wretched man that I am, Who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Job 6. 11, 12. <hi>What is my ſtrength, that I ſhould hope? and, What is my end, that I ſhould prolong my life?</hi> How does holy <hi>Job</hi> here <hi>complain</hi> of his <hi>inſufferable</hi> miſeries, and <hi>longs</hi> moſt paſſionately to be at <hi>reſt</hi> in his grave, as if he <hi>deſpaired</hi> of any <hi>ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> from his <hi>pains</hi> and afflictions ſo long as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47052:40"/>
he was <hi>alive. On that I might have my requeſt, and that God would grant me the thing that I long for!</hi>—</p>
                     <p>Rom. 9. 20. <hi>Nay, but O man, who art thou, that replieſt egainſt God? A ſevere</hi> reprehenſion to our peeviſh <hi>murmurings</hi> and complaints, as if God had not an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> power over us, to puniſh us, unleſs we our ſelves gave our <hi>conſent</hi> to the <hi>infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> of it.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, In a way of <hi>cenſure</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Acts 12. 10. <hi>O full of ſubtilty, thou child of the devil, thou enemy of all righteouſneſs.</hi> And, Can there poſſibly be a worſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter than this?</p>
                     <p>Fifthly, In a way of moſt <hi>earneſt wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſalm 55. 6. <hi>O that I had the wings of a Dove! that I might flee away, and be at reſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sixthly, In a way of infinite <hi>commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and pity of our <hi>unhappy</hi> condition.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Oh Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together, as a hen doth gather her thickens under her wings, and ye would not?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:47052:41"/>How does God <hi>himſelf</hi> mourn for the <hi>miſery</hi> of <hi>his</hi> People? that they ſo <hi>neglected</hi> all the <hi>means</hi> to <hi>their</hi> ſalvation; when he himſelf <hi>infinitely</hi> deſired to <hi>preſerve</hi> them, even with the very <hi>ſame</hi> degrees of <hi>tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as the moſt <hi>affectionate</hi> creature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to <hi>ſave,</hi> and <hi>hover</hi> over her <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lament. 1. 1, 2. <hi>How is the golden city ſpoiled? how doth the city ſit ſolitary, that was full of people? how is ſhe become a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow?</hi> And ſo the Prophet goes on in a moſt <hi>elegant</hi> manner to deſcribe the <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of her <hi>ruin</hi> and fall from her <hi>proſperity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Seventhly, In a way of <hi>triumph</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>1 Cor. 15 55. <hi>Oh death, where is thy ſting? oh grave, where is thy victory?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Eighthly, In a tranſport of <hi>love</hi> and <hi>admiration.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſal. 84. 1. <hi>Oh how amiable are thy ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, thou Lord of hoſts!</hi> As if the Royal Pſalmiſt was in ſuch a <hi>rapture,</hi> that he could give no <hi>adequate</hi> notion of his <hi>love</hi> and delight in God's houſe; by a <hi>cold</hi> affirmation of the pleaſure of it, but was forced to run himſelf into an <hi>Ecſtaſie,</hi> and ſo leaves the queſtion <hi>undetermined,</hi> as if it was <hi>unexpreſſible.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:47052:41"/>
                     <head>EPIPHONEMA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epiphonema</hi> is an Acclamation, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome very <hi>remarkable</hi> ſentence at the <hi>cloſe</hi> of our diſcourſe; it is, as it were, the <hi>laſt finiſhing</hi> ſtroke which we deſire to leave upon the <hi>affections</hi> of our Audience. Thus; St. <hi>Paul</hi> after he had <hi>confuted</hi> ſeveral <hi>falſe</hi> opinions concerning the <hi>manner</hi> of the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> at laſt he <hi>recommends</hi> the <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of it, adviſing them, upon the <hi>certain</hi> hopes and <hi>expectations</hi> of <hi>another</hi> life, to be conſtant in all <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Therefore, my beloved brethren, be ye ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, for aſmuch as ye know that your labour is not in vain in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 58.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. 21. Our Saviour here endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to <hi>call</hi> off their affections from an <hi>exceſſive</hi> purſuit of the world; for if they did engage their <hi>thoughts</hi> ſo <hi>exceedingly,</hi> they would leave no <hi>room</hi> for Heaven; and then at laſt, to leave his diſcourſe ſtill more <hi>warm</hi> upon their ſpirits; thus he concludes, <hi>For where your treaſure is, there will your heart be alſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 Cor. 10. 18. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> endeavouring to <hi>diſcourage</hi> the <hi>vanity</hi> of <hi>ſelf-commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:47052:42"/>
leaves this <hi>ſenſible</hi> impreſſion upon them, as the beſt <hi>diſſuaſive</hi> from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it; <hi>for not he that commendeth himſelf is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 9. 17, 18. <hi>Stolen waters are ſweet, and bread eaten in ſecret, is pleaſant.</hi> This is the <hi>inſinuation</hi> of the <hi>adulterous</hi> woman, concerning the <hi>high</hi> reliſh of her <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> pleaſures; but then ſee the <hi>concluſion</hi> of ſuch unhappy <hi>ſatisfactions; but he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that the dead are there, and that her gueſts are in the depths of hell.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Eccleſ. 7. 31. <hi>Lo, only this have I found, that God hath made man upright, but they have ſought out many inventions.</hi> The only thing I <hi>fully</hi> apprehend, after <hi>all</hi> my <hi>enquiries,</hi> is this, That God at <hi>firſt</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed man with a <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>right</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his <hi>certain</hi> guide and <hi>direction</hi> to happineſs; but he loſt this <hi>noble</hi> talent through ſin, which is the cauſe of all his <hi>vain</hi> thoughts and <hi>imaginations.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When our Bleſſed Saviour had <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi> many <hi>wonderfull</hi> Cures, how do the People, with <hi>one</hi> voice, conſpire in <hi>this</hi> Acclamation, He hath done <hi>all</hi> things well; <hi>he maketh both the deaf to hear, and the dumb to ſpeak.</hi> Mark 7. 37.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:47052:42"/>
                     <head>EPANORTHOSIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epanorthoſis,</hi> from a Greek word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to <hi>correct</hi> or amend. When we are in a <hi>paſſion</hi> we are <hi>ſeldom</hi> ſatisfied with what we <hi>ſay,</hi> or <hi>doe;</hi> inſomuch that we are apt to fanſie our <hi>expreſſions</hi> are no ways <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual</hi> to our thoughts, and ſo we ſtill <hi>add</hi> freſh, and <hi>more</hi> words to correct, as <hi>we</hi> think, the <hi>inſufficiency</hi> of the <hi>former.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Acts 26. 27. <hi>King Agrippa, believeſt thou the Prophets? I know that thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveſt.</hi> Does not our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſeem as it were to <hi>queſtion</hi> the <hi>faith</hi> of King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> as if he were not yet <hi>ſufficiently</hi> convinced concerning the <hi>divine</hi> authority of the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Scriptures: but then St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as if he was <hi>afraid</hi> of the <hi>incivility</hi> of the <hi>queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> does not <hi>ſcruple</hi> to ſay, that there was the <hi>leaſt</hi> reaſon to ſuſpect the <hi>belief</hi> of King <hi>Agrippa;</hi> and the <hi>inſinuation</hi> of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was very <hi>powerfull,</hi> even almoſt to his very <hi>converſion,</hi> Verſe 28. then <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> ſaid, <hi>Almoſt thou perſuadeſt me to be a Chriſtian.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>I would to God, that not only thou, but all that hear me this day, were both almoſt, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch as I am, except theſe bonds.</hi> And what <hi>expreſſion</hi> can be more Courtly, more
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47052:43"/>
                        <hi>Genteel,</hi> what more <hi>effectual</hi> to prevail upon their <hi>affections,</hi> than thus to wiſh them, in all reſpects, like <hi>himſelf;</hi> but not <hi>ſo</hi> miſerable, not ſo unhappy, as to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any <hi>confinement</hi> of Chains or <hi>impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as he <hi>himſelf</hi> was at <hi>that</hi> time?</p>
                     <p>1. Cor. 15. 10. <hi>I laboured more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly than they all, yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.</hi> Obſerve here with what <hi>care</hi> and caution St. <hi>Paul diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſts</hi> his <hi>own natural</hi> ſtrength and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as very <hi>unſufficient</hi> to his <hi>converſion,</hi> and ſo preſently <hi>corrects</hi> himſelf, and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes</hi> it more eſpecially to the <hi>influence</hi> and the <hi>conduct</hi> of <hi>divine</hi> Grace. As if he had ſaid, Though I was not wanting to the <hi>beſt</hi> of my power, to become a <hi>true</hi> Diſciple of Chriſt, yet muſt I freely ſay, that my <hi>converſion</hi> is principally to be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed</hi> to <hi>another</hi> Cauſe: for the Incitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>will,</hi> and the <hi>power,</hi> and the <hi>occaſions,</hi> and the <hi>means</hi> to make uſe of it, is <hi>derived</hi> from the <hi>inſpirations</hi> of the <hi>holy</hi> Spirit, which <hi>animates</hi> and gives life and vigour to <hi>all</hi> our thoughts, and ſo <hi>diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> us to <hi>repentance</hi> and amendment of life. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
                     <p>Mark 9. 24 <hi>Lord, I believe, help thou my unbelief.</hi> How does he <hi>reprehend</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as if it was almoſt a <hi>preſumption</hi> in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47052:43"/>
him to ſpeak with <hi>ſo</hi> much <hi>confidence</hi> of his <hi>ſtrength</hi> of faith, even to our Saviour <hi>himſelf;</hi> and therefore as if he were now <hi>diffident</hi> again, and that his belief was <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect,</hi> and had ſome <hi>degree</hi> of weakneſs and <hi>infirmity;</hi> he at laſt <hi>humbly</hi> implores the <hi>divine</hi> aſſiſtance, to <hi>encreaſe</hi> and fill up the <hi>meaſure</hi> of his faith; <hi>Lord, help thou my unbelief.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>1 Cor. 7. 10. <hi>And unto the married I command, yet not I, but the Lord.</hi> He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>recolle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ts</hi> himſelf, and aſſures his <hi>Corinthians</hi> that he gave them not theſe <hi>directions</hi> as a <hi>mere</hi> man, but as an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> and a perſon of <hi>divine</hi> Inſpiration, and ſo, <hi>not I, but the Lord commandeth;</hi> and this he ſaid, to give the <hi>more</hi> force and efficacy to their <hi>obedience</hi> of the Precept.</p>
                     <p>Luke 11. 27, 28. <hi>A certain woman ſaid unto him, Bleſſed is the womb that bare thee, and the paps that gave thee ſuck. But he ſaid, Yea, rather bleſſed are all they, that hear the word of God and keep it.</hi> As if our <hi>Saviour</hi> was <hi>ſenſible</hi> ſome might, through a <hi>miſtaken</hi> principle, aſcribe <hi>too</hi> much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect to the <hi>bleſſed</hi> Virgin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>mother</hi> of our <hi>dear</hi> Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and therefore, how does Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt <hi>induſtriouſly</hi> give the <hi>preference</hi> to <hi>thoſe,</hi> who <hi>live</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>precepts</hi> of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47052:44"/>
Goſpel? <hi>Yea, rather bleſſed are they;</hi> ſo that the <hi>moral</hi> birth of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt in the <hi>ſoul,</hi> is a <hi>greater</hi> bleſſedneſs, than the <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> birth of him was to the <hi>Virgin Mary:</hi> to <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> him, than to be the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> Mother of our <hi>Saviour.</hi> So that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf lays no <hi>great</hi> matter of <hi>ſtreſs</hi> or privilege upon <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>relation,</hi> but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures them in <hi>another</hi> place, to <hi>anticipate</hi> all miſtake upon <hi>ſuch</hi> an opinion; That he that <hi>lives</hi> in <hi>obedience</hi> to his <hi>Commands,</hi> is <hi>equally</hi> dear, and <hi>related</hi> to him, without any <hi>diſtinction, the ſame is my ſiſter, and father, and mother.</hi> Matt. 12. 49, 50.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>APOSIOPESIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Apoſiopeſis,</hi> a Greek word; and I have <hi>more</hi> manners, than to <hi>pretend</hi> to give <hi>you</hi> the <hi>derivation</hi> of it.</p>
                     <p>This Figure, through ſome <hi>violent</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, either of <hi>ſorrow, fear, ſhame</hi> or <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> obligeth us to <hi>break</hi> off our <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> and though we <hi>ſeem</hi> to <hi>conceal</hi> ſome part of it; yet, through the <hi>exceſs</hi> of paſſion, we do but the <hi>more</hi> ſenſibly <hi>diſcover</hi> our <hi>reſentments.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>1 Kings 217. <hi>And Jezebel his wife ſaid unto him, Doſt thou</hi> now <hi>govern the Kingdom of Iſrael?</hi> The words are ſpoken with a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47052:44"/>
                        <hi>mighty</hi> emphaſis, and ſignify much more than is there expreſſed; doſt <hi>thou,</hi> or art thou <hi>worthy</hi> of the name of a <hi>King?</hi> thou that art ſo <hi>mean</hi> ſpirited, as to <hi>grieve</hi> thy ſelf upon this <hi>refuſal</hi> of <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard: and, where is thy <hi>princely</hi> power and <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? Doſt thou now govern the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Iſrael?</hi> is <hi>this</hi> any <hi>mark</hi> of thy <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> Office? is this a <hi>ſign</hi> of thy <hi>indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> power? thus tamely to <hi>ſit</hi> down, <hi>thus</hi> to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>denial; Doſt thou now govern?</hi>—</p>
                     <p>Gen. 3. 22.—<hi>And now, leſt be put forth his hand, and take alſo of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever.</hi> Theſe words are <hi>ſpoken</hi> in a way of <hi>commination,</hi> and <hi>puniſhment,</hi> to <hi>Adam,</hi> for his <hi>high</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to God's <hi>command;</hi> and they imply <hi>thus</hi> much; ſince thou haſt <hi>been</hi> ſo <hi>rebellious</hi> againſt me, I will now <hi>preſently</hi> drive thee <hi>out</hi> of my <hi>garden,</hi> and ſuffer thee <hi>no</hi> longer to be in a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thy ſelf <hi>happy,</hi> or to be in my <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Luke 19. 42. <hi>If thou, even thou, hadſt known, at leaſt in this thy day, the things which belong to thy peace! but now they are hid from thy eyes:</hi> which contain a moſt <hi>dreadfull denunciation</hi> of ſome <hi>future</hi> judgments that were to <hi>befall</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh</hi>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:47052:45"/>
Nation, that the <hi>time</hi> for their <hi>repentance</hi> was now <hi>paſt,</hi> beyond all <hi>recovery,</hi> and therefore they were <hi>now</hi> to expect nothing elſe but <hi>ruine,</hi> and <hi>deſolation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſal. 6. 3. <hi>My ſoul is ſore vexed: but thou, O Lord, how long?</hi> The <hi>ſence</hi> is imperfect and <hi>interrupted; but thou, O Lord, how long?</hi> that is, ſhall thy <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>infliction</hi> of puniſhments <hi>endure? how</hi> long wilt thou <hi>delay</hi> to <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>refreſh</hi> my ſoul, and take away the <hi>ſad</hi> occaſions of my <hi>grief?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Heb. 13. 1. <hi>I ſware in my wrath, if they ſhall enter into my reſt:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> which words contain a mighty kind of <hi>reſolution,</hi> though the <hi>expreſſion</hi> is more <hi>ſoft</hi> and <hi>gentle:</hi> as if God ſhould ſay, in his <hi>high</hi> diſpleaſure, I will not be <hi>found</hi> to ſpeak the <hi>truth,</hi> if now they <hi>enter</hi> into my <hi>reſt;</hi> which is the higheſt <hi>aſſeveration</hi> that is <hi>poſſible.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>APOSTROPHE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Apoſtrophe,</hi> a turning away, or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>from</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>verto:</hi> 'tis a <hi>diverſion</hi> of our <hi>diſcourſe</hi> to <hi>another</hi> perſon, than we intended <hi>firſt</hi> perſon, than we intended <hi>firſt</hi> of all, to make our <hi>applications;</hi> thus a Man, who is in a <hi>violent</hi> tranſport of paſſion, turns
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:47052:45"/>
himſelf on <hi>all</hi> ſides, and makes his <hi>addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> from this, to <hi>another</hi> perſon, whom he <hi>thinks</hi> at <hi>leaſt,</hi> will be more <hi>favourable</hi> to the <hi>cauſe</hi> of his complaining; nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he <hi>appeals</hi> to the moſt <hi>inſenſible</hi> things, to the <hi>heavens,</hi> to the <hi>earth;</hi> and in the <hi>fury</hi> of his <hi>paſſion,</hi> makes no difference and <hi>diſtinction;</hi> and ſometimes, like a mere <hi>child,</hi> quarrels with <hi>any</hi> thing, without <hi>cauſe</hi> or <hi>reaſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 Sam. 1. 21. <hi>Ye mountains of Gilboa, let there be no dew, neither let there be rain upon you, nor fields of offering.</hi> How does Holy <hi>David,</hi> in the <hi>violence</hi> of his ſorrow and <hi>lamentation,</hi> curſe <hi>theſe</hi> very places with <hi>barrenneſs,</hi> as if they were any way in the leaſt, <hi>acceſſory</hi> to the <hi>occaſions</hi> of his <hi>mourning,</hi> and therefore <hi>cruelly</hi> wiſhes them to be <hi>dry</hi> and <hi>fruitleſs,</hi> without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth any <hi>more</hi> fruit, or <hi>offerings</hi> of <hi>ſacrifice;</hi> but, what is <hi>all</hi> this <hi>expreſſion,</hi> what is this ſevere malediction, but only a <hi>more pathetical</hi> inſtance or <hi>aggravation</hi> of <hi>David</hi>'s infinite <hi>ſorrow,</hi> for the <hi>loſs</hi> of his <hi>deareſt</hi> friend <hi>Jonathan?</hi> Verſ. 26. <hi>Thy love to me was wonderfull, paſſing the love of women:</hi> as if there was a <hi>more</hi> infinite <hi>tye</hi> of <hi>friendſhip,</hi> than in the very <hi>affections</hi> of the husband to his <hi>wife.</hi> Ibid. <hi>I am diſtreſſed for thee, my brother Jonathan:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:47052:46"/>
very pleaſant haſt thou been:</hi> How does <hi>mournfull David</hi> diſcourſe to his <hi>deareſt Jonathan,</hi> as if now he was <hi>ſenſible,</hi> or could give <hi>attention</hi> to the <hi>voice</hi> of his <hi>mourning?</hi> and how goes he on to <hi>recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> the paſt <hi>endearments</hi> of his <hi>converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> recalling to his <hi>mind</hi> the joys, the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placencies,</hi> and all thoſe <hi>innocent</hi> familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which rendred his <hi>company</hi> moſt <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull</hi> to him, the ſenſe of which had made ſuch a very <hi>ſtrong</hi> and mighty <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> on his ſoul; that to <hi>remember,</hi> he was <hi>once</hi> ſo very <hi>happy</hi> in his deareſt <hi>friendſhip,</hi> and not to be <hi>always</hi> ſo, makes him <hi>now</hi> but the more <hi>miſerable,</hi> and the more <hi>ſenſible</hi> of his infinite <hi>loſs,</hi> of his <hi>deareſt</hi> friend?—<hi>Ye daughters of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, weep over Saul:—Oh Jonathan, thou waſt ſlain in the high places.—very pleaſant haſt thou been.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 1. 2. <hi>Hear, O heavens, and give ear, O earth, for I have nouriſhed and brought up children, and they have rebelled againſt me.</hi> The <hi>thoughts</hi> of ſo <hi>much</hi> tenderneſs and ſo much <hi>indulgence,</hi> and ſuch <hi>ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> upon it, ſo highly <hi>provokes</hi> the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> to that <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>wonder</hi> and <hi>amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that in his <hi>tranſport</hi> of paſſion, he ſeems to <hi>fanſie</hi> the moſt <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were <hi>capable</hi> to be <hi>judges</hi> of ſuch
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:47052:46"/>
                        <hi>ſtrange</hi> ungratefulneſs; and therefore <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals</hi> to them, to make their <hi>remarks</hi> upon ſuch <hi>extravagant</hi> and <hi>unnatural</hi> rebellions.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes, for want of <hi>other</hi> objects, we turn our <hi>diſcourſe</hi> upon <hi>our</hi> own ſelves; and ſo the <hi>ſame</hi> perſon <hi>reproves,</hi> and is <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> by his <hi>own</hi> ſelf. Thus, in <hi>Pſal. 43. 5. Why art thou caſt down, O my ſoul? and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? Oh truſt in God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sometimes again we make our <hi>addreſſes</hi> and applications to <hi>inſenſible</hi> things, as if it was in <hi>their</hi> power to <hi>hear,</hi> and <hi>favour</hi> our petitions; <hi>Then ſhall they begin to ſay to the mountains, Fall on us; and to the hills, Cover us.</hi> Luke 23. 30. And the apprehenſions of their <hi>dangers,</hi> and the <hi>extravagance</hi> of their <hi>fears</hi> may juſtifie, in <hi>ſome</hi> degree at leaſt, ſuch kind of <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> though in <hi>themſelves</hi> very <hi>vain,</hi> and moſt <hi>unreaſonable.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How does St. <hi>Paul</hi> triumph over <hi>death,</hi> and the <hi>grave?</hi> as if they heard his <hi>inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> eloquence, or were <hi>ſenſible</hi> of their <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow. O death, where is thy ſting? O Grave, where is thy victory?</hi> 1 Cor. 15. v. 55.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 114. 5. <hi>What ailed thee, O thou ſea, that thou fleddeſt? or thou Jordan,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:47052:47"/>
that thou waſt driven back?</hi> The Prophet asks the <hi>waters</hi> themſelves what was the <hi>reaſon</hi> of the <hi>wonderfull</hi> ebb of the <hi>red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea;</hi> or the <hi>ſtanding</hi> ſtill or <hi>partitions</hi> of the <hi>river Jordan:</hi> and in the <hi>vehemency</hi> of his paſſion, ſeems to <hi>expect</hi> from them a <hi>ſuitable</hi> anſwer; Why, ſays he, were <hi>you</hi> ſo very <hi>ſenſible</hi> of fear, when like <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling</hi> and <hi>amazed</hi> perſons, you left your <hi>places,</hi> and as it were, made up a <hi>wall</hi> on either ſide; as if you had <hi>forgot</hi> your <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and were no longer <hi>fluid</hi> and <hi>mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> tell me <hi>then, What ailed you?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>PROSOPOPOEIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Proſopopoeia, fictio perſonae,</hi> derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>perſona,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>facio.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Figure ſuppoſeth <hi>another</hi> perſon ſpeaking <hi>our</hi> ſence and <hi>meaning,</hi> and ſo we <hi>introduce</hi> him into our <hi>diſcourſe.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo this Figure makes <hi>inanimate</hi> things to <hi>hear</hi> or <hi>ſpeak,</hi> as if they were <hi>real</hi> perſons.</p>
                     <p>Prov 8. 1. <hi>Doth not <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>wiſdom cry, and underſtanding put forth her voice?—Unto you, O men, I call, and my voice is to the ſons of men.</hi> Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> introduceth wiſdom under the <hi>character</hi> of a <hi>perſon</hi> ſpeaking and giving <hi>inſtructions,</hi> how they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:47052:47"/>
ſhould <hi>practiſe,</hi> her <hi>kind</hi> admonitions. <hi>Some,</hi> though I think, <hi>erroneouſly,</hi> underſtand the <hi>Son</hi> of God, the ſecond <hi>perſon</hi> in the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> under this <hi>repreſentation</hi> of Wiſdom, who is called the <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But ask now the beaſts of the field, and they ſhall teach thee; and the fowls of the air, and they ſhall tell thee:</hi> where holy <hi>Job</hi> adviſeth his friends to go to the <hi>beaſts</hi> and <hi>birds</hi> for better <hi>information;</hi> and even they ſhould be able to <hi>tell</hi> them, that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity</hi> or <hi>afflictions</hi> were <hi>accidental</hi> to the <hi>pious,</hi> or to the <hi>ungodly</hi> man, and that <hi>no</hi> man ought to <hi>eſteem</hi> any <hi>one</hi> wicked, from the <hi>ſufferance</hi> of any <hi>calamity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 30. 24, 25. <hi>The Ants are a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not ſtrong, but they are exceeding wiſe, and they prepare their meat in the ſummer.</hi> And now, <hi>who</hi> would not, at the <hi>firſt</hi> ſight, almoſt <hi>fanſie</hi> this was a <hi>deſcription</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> and a <hi>character</hi> of their <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>forecaſt</hi> in <hi>political</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; rather than a <hi>commendation</hi> of the <hi>wiſdom</hi> and providence of thoſe <hi>little</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects, which here are not <hi>inelegantly</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a <hi>people</hi> extreamly <hi>wiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sometimes we <hi>introduce</hi> mute and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible</hi> Beings, <hi>reaſoning</hi> and <hi>diſcourſing</hi> after the <hi>manner</hi> of Men, <hi>Judges</hi> 9. 8. See alſo 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. verſes.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:47052:48"/>
2 Kings 14. 9. <hi>The Thiſtle that was in Lebanon, ſent to the Cedar that was in Lebanon, ſaying, Give thy daughter to my ſon to wife; and there paſſed by a wild beaſt that was in Lebanon, and trod down the Thiſtle.</hi> How does <hi>Jehoaſh,</hi> under this <hi>ſenſible</hi> repreſentation, deride the <hi>folly</hi> and the preſumption of <hi>Amaziah,</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> who being a petty and <hi>inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> Prince in compariſon of <hi>himſelf,</hi> therefore <hi>ſtyles</hi> himſelf the <hi>Cedar;</hi> as if there was no leſs <hi>difference</hi> between them, than there is <hi>between</hi> the <hi>Cedar,</hi> the <hi>great</hi> Monarch of the <hi>foreſt;</hi> and the <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> a very mean and <hi>inglorious vegetable;</hi> and therefore, not without the higheſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation,</hi> he ſcorns the <hi>very</hi> thoughts of ſuch a <hi>poor</hi> and deſpicable Relation.</p>
                     <p>Song of <hi>Solomon,</hi> c. 2. v. 7. <hi>I charge you, O daughters of Jeruſalem, by the roes and by the hinds of the field, that ye ſtir not up, nor awaken my Love, until he pleaſe.</hi> How do theſe very <hi>expreſſions</hi> diſcover, what a mighty <hi>tenderneſs</hi> Chriſt has for his <hi>belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> Church, that he would not have the <hi>leaſt</hi> thing to <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>diſcompoſe</hi> her? <hi>I charge you by the roes,</hi> by the <hi>example</hi> of theſe <hi>fearfull</hi> Creatures, which the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> endeavour to <hi>ſteal</hi> gently upon, and not to <hi>terrifie</hi> and affright them, and <hi>force</hi>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:47052:48"/>
them to fly, and <hi>run</hi> away, by <hi>noiſe</hi> and <hi>ſudden</hi> ſurprizes.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 4. 10. <hi>The voice of thy brother's blood crieth unto me from the earth.</hi> Thus when any <hi>ſin</hi> is exceeding great, as that of <hi>Murther</hi> moſt <hi>certainly</hi> is, 'tis an <hi>elegant</hi> way of ſpeaking, to give it a <hi>voice</hi> and <hi>language</hi> to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> and cry <hi>aloud</hi> to the God of <hi>heaven</hi> for <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>puniſhment</hi> upon the <hi>Author</hi> of it.—Verſe 11. <hi>And now thou art curſed from the earth, which hath opened her mouth to receive thy brother's blood from thy hand:</hi> Thus the <hi>earth</hi> it ſelf, though <hi>inſenſible,</hi> yet by this Figure is ſaid to <hi>curſe,</hi> as if ſhe was in very <hi>great</hi> wrath and indignation, upon this <hi>inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> action.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſalm</hi> 108 2 Does not Holy <hi>David</hi> call upon his <hi>inſtruments</hi> of <hi>muſick, Awake lute and harp.</hi>—and 14. How does he <hi>deſire</hi> the <hi>ſun,</hi> and the <hi>moon,</hi> and the <hi>ſtars</hi> to praiſe the <hi>Lord,</hi> and alſo the <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>bail, ſnow</hi> and <hi>vapours,</hi> which fulfill his word. And again, he <hi>calls</hi> upon the more <hi>ſenſible</hi> parts of the Creation, upon the <hi>beaſts</hi> and all <hi>cattel,</hi> and <hi>creeping</hi> things, and <hi>feathered fowl,</hi> to ſing their <hi>praiſes</hi> to God their <hi>Maker.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſalm 77. 16. <hi>The waters ſaw thee, O God, the waters ſaw thee, and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:47052:49"/>
the depths alſo were troubled.</hi> Thus <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>fears,</hi> and <hi>diſquietneſs</hi> are appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to things <hi>inſenſible,</hi> to give us a <hi>live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſenſe of God's <hi>majeſty</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> which ſtrike <hi>terror</hi> and <hi>amazement</hi> into <hi>all</hi> things. Pſalm 114. 3 <hi>The waters ſaw thee, and fled;</hi> as if they were under <hi>great</hi> fears and <hi>apprehenſions</hi> of his <hi>coming,</hi> and ſo with great <hi>precipitation retired</hi> ſuddenly.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Figures which we ſometimes make uſe of in a way of <hi>Dialogue.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>APORIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aporia,</hi> a word derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to be doubtfull in mind, when we <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>conſider</hi> with our ſelves, as if we were <hi>uncertain</hi> either what to ſay, or <hi>doe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Luke 16. 3. <hi>Then the unjuſt ſteward ſaid within himſelf, What ſhall I doe? for my Lord taketh away from me the ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardſhip: I cannot dig, to beg I am aſhamed.</hi> Thus the <hi>ſteward</hi> debates with himſelf what <hi>courſe</hi> of life is moſt <hi>ſuitable</hi> to his own <hi>humour</hi> and diſpoſition, and that <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> or poverty were <hi>equally</hi> diſagreeable.</p>
                     <p>Mark 11. 31, 32 <hi>And they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, If we ſay, The baptiſm of John was from heaven, he will
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:47052:49"/>
ſay, Why then did ye not believe? but if we ſay, Of men, they feared the people: for all men counted John, that he was a prophet indeed: and they anſwered, We cannot tell.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>ANACOENOSIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anacoenoſis,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to communicate with others. This Figure teacheth us to adviſe, <hi>deliberate,</hi> or argue with others concerning the <hi>expedience</hi> of our actions.</p>
                     <p>Phil. 1. 22, 23, 24. <hi>What I ſhall chuſe, I wot not, for I am in a ſtrait between two, having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better; nevertheleſs to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the fleſh is more needfull for you.</hi> How is our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here very dubious and <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering</hi> in his mind? Sometimes he <hi>debates</hi> within <hi>himſelf</hi> his own <hi>particular</hi> profit, and preſently <hi>concludes,</hi> it was highly <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous</hi> for him to <hi>die</hi> and to <hi>be</hi> with his <hi>dear</hi> Saviour. And ſometimes alſo he <hi>conſiders</hi> the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> which <hi>ſeems</hi> yet to require his more <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate</hi> Care and <hi>perſonal</hi> preſence; and thus what was ſo <hi>expedient</hi> to his <hi>private</hi> intereſt, was very <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>publick</hi> ſafety and <hi>proſperity</hi> of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:47052:50"/>
Church. And <hi>theſe</hi> thoughts, and theſe <hi>conſiderations ſway</hi> his <hi>inclinations here,</hi> and <hi>there,</hi> to the <hi>great</hi> diſtraction of his mind.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 139. 7. <hi>Whither ſhall I go from thy ſpirit? or whither ſhall I flee from thy preſence?</hi> The <hi>queſtion</hi> perhaps ſeems to <hi>inſinuate</hi> that God's <hi>preſence</hi> was confined to <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place;</hi> but if you <hi>obſerve,</hi> 'tis rather a <hi>ſtronger</hi> Confirmation that God is every <hi>where preſent</hi> to <hi>all</hi> perſons in all manner of <hi>places,</hi> and that no <hi>man</hi> can <hi>be,</hi> where God is <hi>not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Luke 11. 18. <hi>If Satan be divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Satan, how ſhall his king dom ſtand?</hi> Thus from the <hi>evil</hi> Conſequences of <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion,</hi> and from the <hi>manifeſt</hi> abſurdity that ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> a being as the <hi>Devil</hi> is, ſhould ever <hi>conſpire</hi> to deſtroy <hi>himſelf,</hi> our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>prooes</hi> his <hi>miracles</hi> to be <hi>performed</hi> by a <hi>divine</hi> power.</p>
                     <p>Acts 4. 19. <hi>But Peter and John ſaid unto them, Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you more than God, judge ye.</hi> And the <hi>Appeal</hi> it ſelf was ſo <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>equitable,</hi> that even in <hi>their</hi> own <hi>partial</hi> opinion, they could not but <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide</hi> the <hi>queſtion</hi> in <hi>favour</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mal. 1. 6. <hi>If then I be a father, when is my honour? if I be a maſter, where is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:47052:50"/>
my fear?</hi> If then you <hi>grant</hi> me the <hi>ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent,</hi> why are you ſo <hi>abſurd,</hi> as to deny me the <hi>conſequence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Jerem. 23. 23. <hi>Am I a God at hand, ſaith the Lord, and not a God afar of?</hi> Is not this the <hi>ſevereſt</hi> reprehenſion to <hi>thoſe,</hi> who conceive ſuch <hi>narrow</hi> thoughts of <hi>God,</hi> as to think the <hi>diſtance</hi> of <hi>places</hi> can <hi>hinder</hi> his <hi>knowledge,</hi> or void his preſence, or render his <hi>power ineffectual?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>PROLEPSIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prolepſis, anticipatio:</hi> by this Figure we give a <hi>diverſion</hi> to any thing that may be <hi>objected</hi> againſt us, by <hi>anſwering</hi> by way of <hi>prevention,</hi> the very <hi>objection</hi> our ſelves.</p>
                     <p>Rom. 11. 19, 21, 22. <hi>Thou wilt ſay then, The branches were broken off, that I might be graffed in. Well, becauſe of unbelief they were broken off, and thou ſtandeſt by faith. Be not high minded, but fear. For if God ſpared not the natural branches,</hi> take heed <hi>leſt he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> here <hi>obviates</hi> the <hi>objection</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> who were <hi>inſerted</hi> into the <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>unbelieving Jews,</hi> who are here <hi>ſtyled</hi> the <hi>broken</hi> branches, were <hi>rejected:</hi> this he tells the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> was a <hi>mighty</hi> favour of God, ſo
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:47052:51"/>
to <hi>incoporate</hi> them with his <hi>Church;</hi> but then he alſo <hi>aſſures</hi> them, that they muſt not ſo <hi>far preſume</hi> upon their <hi>preſent</hi> ſtate and vocation; <hi>For if God ſpare not the natural branches,</hi> that is, the <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, take heed <hi>leſt he alſo ſpare not the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> For if by your <hi>diſobedience</hi> you now incurr God's <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> you cannot in <hi>reaſon,</hi> but expect to <hi>ſuffer</hi> the ſame unhappy <hi>fare</hi> with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation.</p>
                     <p>St. <hi>Paul, diſcourſing</hi> of the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> reſolves a <hi>difficult</hi> queſtion concerning the <hi>mode</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of the reſurrection, and what <hi>ſort</hi> of body ſhall be <hi>raiſed</hi> up from the <hi>grave. But ſome will ſay, How are the dead raiſed up? and with what body do they come?</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 35, 36. <hi>Thou ſoul.</hi> Our Saviour <hi>ſtifles</hi> their <hi>objection,</hi> by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering <hi>another,</hi> ſo very <hi>difficult,</hi> that they were <hi>unwilling</hi> to anſwer it. Matth. 21. 24, 25. <hi>I will alſo ask you one queſtion, which if you tell me, I likewiſe will tell you by what authority I doe theſe things. The baptiſm of John, whence was it? from heaven, or of men?</hi> This was ſuch a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma,</hi> and the <hi>reſolution</hi> of it ſo highly inconvenient, that they pretend <hi>ignorance,</hi> and <hi>anſwer, We cannot tell.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 9. 19, 20. <hi>Thou wilt ſay them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, Why doth he yet find fault? for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:47052:51"/>
who hath reſiſted his will? Nay but, O man, who art thou, that replieſt againſt God?</hi> Thus St. <hi>Paul anticipates</hi> their <hi>falſe</hi> opinion, aſſuring them that the <hi>work</hi> of grace is of God's <hi>mere</hi> free-will; and, if he doth <hi>deprive</hi> ſome of it, he is not in the <hi>leaſt</hi> guilty of any <hi>injuſtice</hi> to them, ſince he is under no <hi>obligations</hi> to <hi>conferr</hi> it upon them; and this very <hi>ſubtraction</hi> of his <hi>grace,</hi> upon their <hi>impenitency,</hi> and continuance in a vicious <hi>courſe</hi> of life, is no <hi>cauſe</hi> of their <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs;</hi> but on the contrary, their <hi>diſobedience</hi> and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life is the <hi>reaſon</hi> why God <hi>withdraws</hi> the <hi>influence</hi> of his holy <hi>ſpirit</hi> from them; and ſo our <hi>ſins</hi> chaſe away the holy <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and render its <hi>operation ineffectual</hi> to our <hi>converſion,</hi> and ſo the <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is hardned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>EPITROPE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epitrope,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>concedo.</hi> By this Figure we often grant a thing not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly</hi> to obtain <hi>another,</hi> and ſhow more <hi>effectually</hi> the <hi>inconveniency</hi> of ſuch a Practice or Principle.</p>
                     <p>Romans 2. 17. <hi>Behold, thou art cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Jew, and reſteſt in the law, and makeſt thy boaſt of God; and art confident
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:47052:52"/>
that thou thy ſelf art a guide to the blind. Thou therefore that teacheſt another, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou not thy ſelf?</hi> As if he ſaid, I grant thou art <hi>an Inſtructer of the fooliſh,</hi> and <hi>a teacher of babes;</hi> but then, Why is thy <hi>converſation</hi> ſo <hi>unſuitable</hi> to thy <hi>doctrine?</hi> Where is thy <hi>example?</hi> Where is thy <hi>practice?</hi> and, Why are they ſo <hi>diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to thy <hi>external</hi> profeſſion? thus, How does our Apoſtle ſeem to <hi>concede</hi> all they <hi>deſire?</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> at laſt upon them; that their <hi>practice</hi> was not <hi>conſonant</hi> to their <hi>principles;</hi> and from that <hi>abſurdity,</hi> more ſeverely <hi>reprehends</hi> them.</p>
                     <p>Judges 10. 14. <hi>Go and cry unto the gods which ye have choſen; let them deliver you in the time of trouble:</hi> This ſeems no ſmall <hi>encouragement</hi> to their <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>idolatry;</hi> but in <hi>reality,</hi> 'tis the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> diſſuaſion from it; and <hi>virtually</hi> implies the <hi>diſability</hi> of <hi>other</hi> gods to <hi>ſave</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them in <hi>times</hi> of danger.</p>
                     <p>1 Kings 22. 15. <hi>The King ſaid to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caiah, Shall we go againſt Ramoth gilead to battel, or ſhall we forbear? and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, Go and proſper:</hi> Where the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſeems to <hi>encourage</hi> them to the <hi>battel,</hi> though he eaſily <hi>foreſaw</hi> the <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> conſequence of the <hi>war.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:47052:52"/>1 Cor. 14 38. <hi>But if any man be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, let him be ignorant ſtill:</hi> that is, If after ſuch a plain and <hi>poſitive</hi> proof of my <hi>miniſtery,</hi> he will <hi>nevertheleſs</hi> reſolve to continue <hi>ignorant</hi> of it, let it be at his <hi>own</hi> peril; where the <hi>conceſſion</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>diſcouragement</hi> to his <hi>want</hi> of underſtanding, and reflection in a <hi>matter</hi> of ſo <hi>high importance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See <hi>Amos</hi> 4. 4, 5. where the <hi>Prophet,</hi> in a way of <hi>deriſion,</hi> ſeems to approve of their <hi>idolatrous</hi> practives.</p>
                     <p>Prov. 6. 10. <hi>Yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands to ſleep:</hi> As if he ſaid, You do <hi>well</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge your ſelf in <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>ſlothfulneſs;</hi> but then at <hi>laſt,</hi> how does the <hi>wiſe</hi> Man <hi>ruturn</hi> upon the <hi>Sluggard; ſo ſhall thy</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty <hi>come, as one that</hi> travelleth, <hi>and thy</hi> want <hi>as an</hi> armed <hi>Man;</hi> and ſo more fully <hi>convinceth</hi> him of the great <hi>inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences</hi> of an <hi>idle</hi> way of living.</p>
                     <p>James 2. 19. <hi>Thou believeſt that there is one God, thou doeſt well; the devils alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and tremble:</hi> Where after this ſort of <hi>commendation</hi> of their faith, he at laſt tells them, that ſuch a <hi>belief,</hi> without a <hi>ſuitable</hi> practice, is vain and <hi>ineffectual,</hi> and that even the <hi>devils</hi> themſelves have a <hi>ſpeculative</hi> faith.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:47052:53"/>Matth. 5. 46. <hi>If ye love them that love you, what reward have you? do not even the Publicans the ſame?</hi> I will, if you <hi>pleaſe,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> allow the <hi>matter</hi> of fact; yet, what <hi>uſe</hi> can you make of <hi>it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> where is the <hi>commendation?</hi> where is the <hi>vertue</hi> of ſuch a <hi>practice,</hi> if the <hi>worſt</hi> of men doe the very <hi>ſame?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Theſe following are called <hi>ſecondary</hi> Figures of a word.</head>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>PLEONASMUS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pleonaſmus,</hi> you know, Sir, is a Greek word, and 'tis <hi>uncivil</hi> to explain it in your <hi>company.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Figure makes uſe of <hi>more</hi> words than are <hi>neceſſary;</hi> but they give a much <hi>ſtronger</hi> accent and <hi>emphaſis</hi> to our <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Deuter. 33. 6. <hi>O fooliſh people, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe!</hi> Which ſort of expreſſion ſtill more <hi>eminently</hi> denotes their <hi>want</hi> of wiſdom, and diſcretion.</p>
                     <p>Prov. 27. 2. <hi>Let another man praiſe thee, and not thy own mouth; a ſtranger, and not thine own lips:</hi> And this <hi>variety</hi> of words is not ſo <hi>unuſefull</hi> to engage our thoughts, to <hi>conſider</hi> with <hi>more</hi> attention,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:47052:53"/>
the <hi>ſubject</hi> matter of our <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> and the <hi>importance</hi> of it.</p>
                     <p>See <hi>Deuter.</hi> 13. 4.—</p>
                     <p>John 1. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>All things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made:</hi> And the <hi>variation</hi> of the <hi>ſence</hi> in other words was very <hi>convenient</hi> to <hi>aſſure</hi> us, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was before the <hi>world;</hi> and that <hi>all</hi> things in it, were the <hi>works</hi> of his <hi>hand;</hi> and from the <hi>univerſality</hi> of his <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> power, he muſt be <hi>omnipotent,</hi> and therefore <hi>God;</hi> for what <hi>leſs</hi> than <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> power it ſelf, can <hi>make</hi> and <hi>produce all things?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>DIALYTON.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dialyton,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to <hi>diſſolve.</hi> This Figure pretends, through a mighty <hi>haſt</hi> and <hi>vehemence</hi> of ſpeech, to uſe no <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction,</hi> to render our diſcourſe the more <hi>emphatical</hi> and <hi>earneſt;</hi> nay, ſhould we <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert</hi> the <hi>Copula,</hi> our diſcourſe would ſeem <hi>too</hi> ſlow and <hi>heavy,</hi> and <hi>loſe</hi> much of its <hi>life</hi> and <hi>vigour,</hi> and expreſſiveneſs.</p>
                     <p>1 Tim. 3. 2, 3. <hi>For men ſhall be lovers of themſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:47052:54"/>
unholy.</hi> Thus the Verſe runs off <hi>preſently,</hi> with more <hi>quickneſs</hi> and <hi>preſently,</hi> than if the Particle <hi>and</hi> was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>interpos'd.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 1. 29. <hi>Being filled with all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, fornication, wickedneſs, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, maliciouſneſs; full of envy, debate, deceit, malignity,</hi> &amp;c. As if the Apoſtle was in ſuch <hi>haſt</hi> to <hi>run</hi> over the <hi>chief</hi> heads of their <hi>immoralities,</hi> that he had no <hi>time</hi> for their <hi>connexion.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe, See <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 11, 12. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 4, 5, 6, 7. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. 1, 2, 3. all which are disjoined and without a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulative. See alſo <hi>Mark</hi> 7. 21, 22.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>POLYSYNDETON.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Polyſyndeton,</hi> derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>conjunctus.</hi> This Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure is <hi>contrary</hi> to the former, and very often <hi>employs</hi> the <hi>copulative,</hi> to tie and <hi>join</hi> words <hi>together.</hi> See 1 Cor. 13. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Though I ſpeak with the tongues of men and angels, and have not charity, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as ſounding braſs, or a tinkling cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal; and though I have the gift of prophecy, and underſtand all myſteries, and all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> &amp;c. where the Copulative <hi>and</hi> is not <hi>inelegantly</hi> ſo often uſed, though the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:47052:54"/>
                        <hi>ear</hi> is the <hi>beſt</hi> Judge of the <hi>harmony</hi> of <hi>ſounds,</hi> when 'tis proper to <hi>uſe</hi> it, or lay it <hi>aſide.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 8. 38, 39. <hi>For I am perſuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God.</hi> I place this <hi>inſtance</hi> under this Figure; but if you think it <hi>rather</hi> belongs to <hi>Dialyton, nor,</hi> being a <hi>disjunctive particle; becauſe</hi> you are my <hi>friend,</hi> I will not <hi>ſtand</hi> with you for ſo <hi>ſmall</hi> a matter.</p>
                     <p>See <hi>Pſal. 18. 2. The Lord is my rock, and my fortreſs, and my deliverer:</hi> The Copulative <hi>and</hi> makes the ſence paſs on <hi>more leiſurely,</hi> and ſo the words ſtill make a deeper impreſſion upon the <hi>mind.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>ANTITHESIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Antitheſis</hi> repreſents terms <hi>contrary</hi> to each other, to convey to the <hi>mind</hi> a more ſenſible and <hi>lively</hi> image of our diſcourſe, by ſuch an oppoſition in the words.</p>
                     <p>Prov. 14 29. <hi>He that is ſlow to wrath, is of great wiſdom; but he that is of an haſty mind, exalteth folly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:47052:55"/>Pſalm 126. 5. <hi>They that ſow in tears, ſhall reap in joy:</hi> where the <hi>oppoſition</hi> of the <hi>terms</hi> more ſenſibly <hi>inſtructs</hi> us, that though <hi>afflictions</hi> are at <hi>preſent</hi> matter of <hi>trouble,</hi> yet in the <hi>end,</hi> they are <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly</hi> beneficial.</p>
                     <p>Matt. 16. 25. <hi>For whoſoever will ſave his life, ſhall loſe it; and whoſoever will loſe his life for my ſake, ſhall ſave it:</hi> though not in <hi>this</hi> world, yet in the <hi>next,</hi> even to all <hi>eternity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 1. and 29. 2.—</p>
                     <p>Prov. 11. 24. <hi>There is that ſcattereth, and yet encreaſeth;</hi> but not through <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality,</hi> and <hi>want</hi> of care, but through the <hi>prudent</hi> offices of <hi>charity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See alſo <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 18. 28. 1. Iſai. 59. 9.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Secondary</hi> Figures in a <hi>Sentence.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>PARRHESIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Parrheſia,</hi> derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> This Figure takes the <hi>courage</hi> and liberty to <hi>ſpeak</hi> freely our <hi>ſence</hi> of things which are <hi>diſpleaſing</hi> to us; but we then muſt uſe this ſort of Figure extream <hi>nicely</hi> in our <hi>reprehenſion</hi> of <hi>Superiours; only in caſes of the greateſt extremity,</hi> and when our duty obligeth us to ſuch a freedom.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:47052:55"/>Gal. 1. 10. <hi>For do I now perſuade men, or God? or do I ſeek to pleaſe men? for if I yet pleaſed men, I ſhould not be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God.</hi> Where he <hi>freely</hi> tells them, that it was a <hi>different</hi> thing to <hi>pleaſe God,</hi> and <hi>men;</hi> and conſequently <hi>inſinuates,</hi> that <hi>their</hi> ways were <hi>diſagreeable</hi> to God's <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> And in <hi>Gal. 3. 1. O fooliſh Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians, who hath bewitched you, that you ſhould not obey the truth?</hi> Was not this a very <hi>harſh</hi> expreſſion, to call their <hi>prudence</hi> ſo much into <hi>queſtion;</hi> and again, <hi>Who hath bewitched you?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth his beloved <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort,</hi> 2 Tim 4. v. 2. <hi>And he taught them as one having authority, and not as the Scribes,</hi> Matth. 7. 29.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>EROTESIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eroteſis,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>interrogo.</hi> This Figure is of <hi>excellent</hi> uſe, and <hi>carries</hi> in it more <hi>force</hi> and vehemence; for bare <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> have <hi>no</hi> life nor ſpirit in them, and are leſs <hi>powerfull</hi> to <hi>influence</hi> our ſenſe and <hi>reaſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gen. 4. 7. <hi>If thou doſt well, ſhalt thou not be accepted?</hi> That is, I will moſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:47052:56"/>
certainly <hi>receive</hi> thee, and thy <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mark 12. 24. <hi>Do you not therefore err, becauſe ye know not the Scriptures, neither the power of God?</hi> Where the queſtion being <hi>expreſs'd</hi> with the ſign of <hi>negation,</hi> gives ſtill the <hi>ſtronger</hi> force and emphaſis to his diſcourſe; and is as much as to ſay, You are <hi>extreamly</hi> miſtaken.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 8. 4. <hi>Lord, what is man, that thou haſt ſuch reſpect unto him?</hi> Where the <hi>queſtion</hi> implies the <hi>greateſt</hi> diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as if man was ſo very <hi>inconſiderable,</hi> and <hi>unworthy</hi> of the <hi>leaſt</hi> notice.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How can this man give us his fleſh to eat?</hi> Where the <hi>interrogation</hi> carries in it a <hi>manifeſt</hi> contradiction to our <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>reaſon:</hi> and 'tis no <hi>wonder</hi> if it was ſo <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd</hi> and ſo <hi>unconceivable</hi> to underſtand the words in their <hi>literal</hi> ſence and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
                     <p>John 3. 4. <hi>Nicodemus ſaid, How can a man be born when he is old?</hi> And truly to conceive that our <hi>Saviour</hi> did ſpeak of a <hi>natural</hi> birth, and not of a <hi>moral</hi> change of life; a ſtate of <hi>regeneration;</hi> was not the <hi>leaſt</hi> abſurdity.</p>
                     <p>Matth. 21. 25. <hi>The baptiſm of John, whence was it, from heaven or of men?</hi> And the <hi>queſtion</hi> carried with it ſuch an
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:47052:56"/>
                        <hi>evident</hi> conviction, that which way ſoever they <hi>anſwered</hi> it, they did equally <hi>confute</hi> their <hi>own</hi> ſelves.</p>
                     <p>Iſai. 14. 12. <hi>How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, ſon of the morning? how art thou cut down to the ground, which didſt weaken the nations?</hi> And in Ver. 10. <hi>Art thou alſo become weak as we? art thou become like us?</hi> Thus to ſee a <hi>mighty</hi> Prince <hi>tumbling</hi> down from the <hi>higheſt</hi> pitch of his <hi>honour</hi> and glory; to ſee his <hi>crown</hi> and <hi>Sceptre</hi> falling to the <hi>ground;</hi> the <hi>mighty</hi> man to become ſo very <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>impotent;</hi> is a conſideration ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>ſurprizing:</hi> What! Is <hi>this</hi> the man that was ſo <hi>powerfull,</hi> that he made the <hi>earth</hi> to tremble, and did <hi>ſhake</hi> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms? What! Is <hi>this</hi> the man? <hi>Bleſs</hi> me! What a <hi>change</hi> is <hi>here! How are the mighty fallen?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Job 3. 11. <hi>Why died I not from the womb? why is light given to a man, whoſe way is hid?</hi> And in Verſe 20. <hi>Wherefore is light given to him that is in miſery, and life unto the bitter in ſoul? who long for death, but is cometh not; and dig for it more than for hid treaſures.</hi> And Verſ. 22. <hi>Which rejoice exceedingly, and are glad when they can find their grave.</hi> Thus, How is holy <hi>Job</hi> full of <hi>expoſtulations;</hi>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:47052:57"/>
breathing out <hi>ſad</hi> complainings, that he cannot find any <hi>reſt,</hi> or any <hi>ceſſation</hi> from his <hi>miſeries;</hi> and enjoy the <hi>kindneſs</hi> of a <hi>grave.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>PARENTHESIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Parentheſis</hi> is nothing elſe but the <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> of <hi>one</hi> or <hi>more</hi> words within <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Sentence, the <hi>ſence</hi> of which, without the <hi>inſertion,</hi> is of <hi>its</hi> ſelf <hi>entire</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>rule,</hi> that a <hi>Parentheſis</hi> ſhould neither be very <hi>long,</hi> nor very <hi>frequent,</hi> leſt our <hi>diſcourſe</hi> grow <hi>obſcure,</hi> and not ſo <hi>intelligible. Are they miniſters of Chriſt? (I ſpeak as a fool) I am more.</hi> 2 Cor. 11. v. 23.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>PERIPHRASIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Periphraſis, circumlocutio.</hi> This Figure deſcribes a thing in <hi>more</hi> words than are <hi>neceſſary,</hi> for the <hi>ſake</hi> of Illuſtration, or to <hi>avoid</hi> ſome <hi>Idea's</hi> not ſo <hi>pleaſing</hi> to the mind.</p>
                     <p>Job 18. 14. <hi>Death</hi> is called <hi>The king of terrors.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>John 21. 20. <hi>The diſciple whom Jeſus loved:</hi> which modeſt <hi>circumlocution</hi> Saint <hi>John</hi> often uſeth, to ſignifie <hi>himſelf,</hi> who
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:47052:57"/>
was the <hi>beloved</hi> Diſciple of his Dear Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 15. 15. <hi>And thou ſhalt go to thy fathers in peace:</hi> which is a <hi>ſofter</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and not ſo <hi>terrifying,</hi> as to ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt die.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 20. where the <hi>wiſe</hi> Man ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth us not to <hi>ſpeak</hi> evil of a King, tho' in the moſt <hi>ſecret</hi> places; becauſe ſuch <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes</hi> are publiſhed very <hi>unaccountably; For a bird in the air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter:</hi> ſtill varying the ſame ſence in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words.</p>
                     <p>Hab. 3. 17. <hi>Although the fig-tree ſhall not bloſſom, neither ſhall fruit be in the vine: although the labour of the olive ſhall fail, and the fields ſhall yield no meat; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there be no herd in the ſtalls; yet will I rejoice in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my ſalvation.</hi> See what a <hi>noble</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence the Prophet has in his <hi>God,</hi> even in the <hi>greateſt</hi> extremities; and how <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly</hi> doth he <hi>expreſs</hi> the Particulars with a decent <hi>Periphraſis?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:47052:58"/>
                     <head>SYNONYMIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Synonymia</hi> is a Figure that uſeth <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> words of the <hi>ſame</hi> ſignification; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we fanſie that <hi>one</hi> word alone, is not <hi>ſufficient</hi> to expreſs our <hi>ſence,</hi> and to make a <hi>deep</hi> Impreſſion upon our <hi>Audience.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſal. 119. 60. <hi>I made haſt, and delayed not to keep thy commandments:</hi> As if the Pſalmiſt could not ſufficiently ſet forth his <hi>readineſs</hi> to obey God, without a <hi>repetition</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> ſence in <hi>other</hi> words.</p>
                     <p>Prov. 4. 14, 15. <hi>Enter not into the path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men;</hi> and the <hi>variety</hi> of the <hi>phraſe</hi> renders the <hi>diſſuaſion</hi> more <hi>forcible</hi> to us.</p>
                     <p>Prov. 6. 4 <hi>Give not ſleep to thy eyes, nor ſlumber to thy eye-lids;</hi> that is, Be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly <hi>watchfull</hi> and reſtleſs in thy <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> to <hi>accompliſh</hi> this deſign.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>HYPOTYPOSIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hypotypoſis,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to <hi>repreſent</hi> or deſcribe to the life. This Figure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the <hi>objects</hi> ſo very <hi>lively</hi> to the <hi>mind,</hi> that we are <hi>apt</hi> to <hi>fanſie</hi> we <hi>hear,</hi> and <hi>ſee</hi> them <hi>continually,</hi> as if they were really <hi>preſented</hi> to our very <hi>ſenſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="89" facs="tcp:47052:58"/>Pſalm 37. 35, 36. <hi>I have ſeen the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in great power, and ſpreading himſelf like a green bay-tree; yet he paſſed away, and lo he was not; yea, I ſought him, but he could not be found.</hi> This is a very <hi>live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Character of the <hi>proſperous</hi> condition of the <hi>ungodly</hi> man, and of the moſt <hi>ſuddain</hi> ruine, and <hi>deſtruction</hi> of him: how does <hi>his</hi> image <hi>vaniſh</hi> away? how is his <hi>memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſoon <hi>forgotten?</hi> oh! how <hi>ſuddenly</hi> does he <hi>periſh,</hi> and come to a <hi>fearfull</hi> end?</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 124. 6. <hi>Our ſoul is eſcaped as a bird out of the hand of the fowler; the ſnare is broken, and we are delivered:</hi> and <hi>what</hi> can give us <hi>ſuch</hi> a lively <hi>ſence</hi> of our <hi>narrow</hi> deliverance, as this <hi>ſenſible</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of a <hi>bird</hi> eſcaping out of the very <hi>hand</hi> of the <hi>fowler;</hi> ſuch an <hi>image</hi> as this <hi>conveys</hi> to the <hi>mind,</hi> that our <hi>preſervation</hi> was as <hi>great,</hi> as our very <hi>danger.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 24. 30. <hi>I paſſed by the field of the ſlothfull, and by the vineyard of the man deſtitute of underſtanding; and lo it was all grown over with thorns, and nettles had covered the face thereof, and the ſtone wall was broken down;</hi> which give us a very <hi>ſenſible notion</hi> of the <hi>ſad</hi> effects of <hi>ſloth</hi> and idleneſs; and how <hi>inſenſible</hi> the man is of his <hi>poverty</hi> and <hi>miſery</hi> coming <hi>upon</hi> him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:47052:59"/>
folding of the hands to ſleep;</hi> till he is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced</hi> to the laſt <hi>extremities</hi> of <hi>want</hi> and <hi>miſery.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Song of <hi>Solomon,</hi> ch. 2. v. 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>My well beloved ſpake, and ſaid unto me, Ariſe my Love, my fair one, and come away; for behold the winter is paſſed, the rain is changed, and is gone away; the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers appear in the earth; the time of the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the birds is come; the voice of the turtle-dove is heard in our land; the fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree hath brought forth her young figs, and the vines with their ſmall grapes have caſt a ſavour: Ariſe my Love, my fair one, and come away.</hi> This is a <hi>moſt</hi> elegant <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> of God's <hi>infinite</hi> kindneſs and love to his <hi>Church,</hi> and with what <hi>tender</hi> Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations he calls and <hi>deſires</hi> holy Men, to <hi>forſake</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>ariſe,</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> him: the <hi>other</hi> parts of this <hi>repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> ſignifie the <hi>coming</hi> of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> who, like the <hi>ſpring</hi> of the year, gives new vigor, new <hi>life</hi> and <hi>pleaſantneſs</hi> to the <hi>world.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 4, 5, 8, 9. which <hi>preſents</hi> to the <hi>fancy</hi> a <hi>ſad,</hi> but <hi>very</hi> lively Image of <hi>famine</hi> and <hi>miſery.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 4. 7, 8. <hi>Ah ſinfull nation, your land is waſte, your cities are burnt with fire, ſtrangers devour your land, and it is deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, like the overthrow of ſtrangers:</hi> that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:47052:59"/>
is, ſo <hi>entirely waſted,</hi> as if they <hi>deſired</hi> no kind of <hi>advantage</hi> by the <hi>preſervation</hi> of it from <hi>ruine</hi> and deſtruction.</p>
                     <p>Iſai. 5. 5, 6. <hi>And the daughters of Sion ſhall remain like a cottage in a vineyard, like a lodge in a garden of cucumbers, and like a beſieged city; and I will take away the hedge thereof, and it ſhall be trodden down; I will lay it waſte, it ſhall not be cut nor digged; but briars and thorns ſhall grow up; I will alſo command the clouds, that they rain no rain upon it.</hi> What a diſmal <hi>ſtate</hi> of miſery is this? Nothing here is <hi>preſented</hi> to thy <hi>view,</hi> but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſcene of <hi>deſtruction,</hi> and <hi>famine,</hi> and <hi>miſery.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>ANTHROPOPATHIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anthropopathia.</hi> This Figure <hi>repreſents</hi> God <hi>ſpeaking</hi> or <hi>doing</hi> after the <hi>manner</hi> of men; and <hi>aſcribing</hi> to him the <hi>parts</hi> of body, or any thing <hi>elſe</hi> belonging to our <hi>humane</hi> nature.</p>
                     <p>Thus Chriſt is called the <hi>head</hi> over all things to the <hi>Church,</hi> Eph. 1. 22. And God is called the <hi>head</hi> of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3. in reſpect of his <hi>humane</hi> nature, and office of <hi>mediation;</hi> for in reſpect of his <hi>divinity,</hi> the Son is <hi>equal</hi> to the Father,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:47052:60"/>
as appears from <hi>John</hi> 5. 18. for Chriſt makes <hi>himſelf equal</hi> with God in <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>operation,</hi> v. 19. for <hi>whatſoever</hi> things the <hi>father</hi> doth, <hi>theſe</hi> alſo <hi>doth</hi> the <hi>ſon;</hi> likewiſe by <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>unity</hi> of eſſence, and <hi>perfect will,</hi> and <hi>operation,</hi> which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>me</hi> and my <hi>father;</hi> and this <hi>equality</hi> of Chriſt, to God the Father is very <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> from <hi>Phil. 2. 6. Who being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God: thought it not;</hi> that is to ſay, Chriſt, <hi>without</hi> the <hi>leaſt</hi> uſurpation, was <hi>truly</hi> equal to <hi>God;</hi> and unleſs <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>truly</hi> God, how otherwiſe will you <hi>make</hi> out his <hi>mighty</hi> humiliation, when he was <hi>made</hi> in the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of man, and made himſelf of <hi>no reputation,</hi> and <hi>took upon him the form of a ſervant:</hi> All this ſeems a <hi>mighty</hi> great diminution of <hi>himſelf;</hi> as if he had now <hi>brought</hi> himſelf, as it were, to <hi>nothing,</hi> by this <hi>low</hi> and mighty <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, evacuavit,</hi> Chriſt did almoſt <hi>annihilate</hi> himſelf, in the <hi>debaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of himſelf to ſuch a <hi>low</hi> and <hi>abject</hi> condition of life, as to be <hi>found in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of a man:</hi> and this profound <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> of Chriſt, upon his <hi>appearance</hi> in our <hi>nature,</hi> can no otherwiſe be <hi>rationally</hi> explained, but from the <hi>extream</hi> diſtance and <hi>oppoſition</hi> that there was <hi>between</hi> his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:47052:60"/>
divine Majeſty and <hi>Glory,</hi> as he was <hi>God;</hi> and the moſt <hi>abject</hi> and <hi>deſpicable</hi> ſtate of his <hi>humanity.</hi> Where otherwiſe can be ſuch a mighty <hi>debaſement</hi> of himſelf, if he was <hi>only</hi> man? Where otherwiſe is there ſuch a <hi>vaſt</hi> diminution, or ſuch a ſtrange <hi>humility;</hi> but only from the <hi>mighty</hi> diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and diſproportion between his <hi>divine</hi> and his <hi>humane</hi> nature; as he was <hi>God,</hi> as well as <hi>man;</hi> which, in compariſon to his infinite nature and eſſence, was <hi>indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> here then was his mighty <hi>conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion</hi> very manifeſt; <hi>here</hi> his great <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation</hi> of himſelf was extreamly <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sometimes <hi>God</hi> is repreſented in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as if he had a <hi>face:</hi> as, <hi>the Lord talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Moſes face to face;</hi> not that there was ſuch a <hi>likeneſs;</hi> but only, that God was then <hi>preſent</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> after the moſt <hi>illuſtrious</hi> and ſignal manner; revealing himſelf with the <hi>greateſt</hi> and familiar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy to him.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes God again is endued with a <hi>ſoul,</hi> with acts of <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>abhorrency</hi> belonging to it. See <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 14. and <hi>Pſal. 11. 6. He that delighteth in wickedneſs, doth my ſoul abhor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sometimes God is deſcribed with <hi>hands, The right hand of the Lord bringeth mighty
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:47052:61"/>
things to paſs;</hi> that is, his <hi>power</hi> is very wonderfull in <hi>operation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sometimes God is ſaid to have <hi>eyes,</hi> Pſalm 11. 4. <hi>For his eyes are upon the ways of man, and he ſeeth all his goings,</hi> Job 34. v. 21. See alſo <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139. 2. That is, God moſt <hi>clearly</hi> knows and <hi>underſtandeth all</hi> the actions and deſigns of men, and perfectly diſcerns the <hi>riſe</hi> and progreſs, and the conſequence of his <hi>thoughts,</hi> even <hi>before</hi> they do actually <hi>ſpring</hi> up in his Soul; thus <hi>David, Thou, O Lord, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt my thoughts long before,</hi> Pſal. 139. v. 1. But what need I <hi>introduce more</hi> Texts of Scripture, to prove that <hi>God</hi> is <hi>often</hi> deſcribed to us after the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion</hi> of a man; ſuch a <hi>ſenſible</hi> repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelf to us, is an <hi>infinite</hi> conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention in the <hi>Almighty;</hi> but then, let us be moſt <hi>extreamly</hi> carefull, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him under no <hi>humane</hi> ſhape or figure; as <hi>ſome</hi> very <hi>groſly picture</hi> God Almighty. Whereas God did purpoſely <hi>appear</hi> to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> without <hi>any</hi> body or <hi>figuration</hi> of parts, to prevent all <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>ſimilitude</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in <hi>our</hi> repreſentations of him; which muſt of <hi>neceſſity</hi> be the higheſt <hi>diminution</hi> and injury to the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> nature and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the <hi>Great</hi> God. When therefore you hear of God's <hi>hand,</hi> there muſt be
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:47052:61"/>
preſent to your mind an <hi>Idea</hi> of his active, or his <hi>creative</hi> Power. And when you read of his Almighty <hi>arm</hi> ſtretched out ſtill, you muſt to your ſelf form a <hi>notion</hi> of his <hi>irreſiſtible</hi> ſtrength and dominion. And when <hi>feet</hi> and <hi>walking</hi> are attributed to God, ſuch metaphorical expreſſions ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt to you, that God, by the <hi>immenſity</hi> of his preſence, is every where; for how can ſuch <hi>bodily</hi> parts, or the peculiar offices of them, be in the <hi>leaſt</hi> degree neceſſary to ſuch an <hi>infinite</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Being? Why ſhould God have <hi>eyes,</hi> who is <hi>Sight</hi> it ſelf? or, Why ſhould he have any <hi>feet,</hi> to go or walk, who by the <hi>infinity</hi> of his divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is <hi>omnipreſent?</hi> and, How can God poſſibly go or come, who at the ſame <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> of time, equally <hi>fills</hi> every place; that he cannot be <hi>abſent</hi> from <hi>one</hi> part of the World, and <hi>preſent</hi> to the other part of it? and pray, What <hi>occaſion</hi> has God for a <hi>hand</hi> or an <hi>arm,</hi> who performs <hi>all</hi> things by the mere <hi>efficacy,</hi> and virtue of <hi>his will? Let there be light, and there was light.</hi> Why ſhould God have <hi>ears</hi> to <hi>hear,</hi> who perfectly <hi>knows</hi> all the ſecret motions of our very thoughts, and all their <hi>conſequences,</hi> even before the <hi>actual</hi> determinations of them? or, tell me, What <hi>occaſion</hi> has God for a <hi>tongue,</hi> whoſe very <hi>thoughts</hi> execute
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:47052:62"/>
his high <hi>commands,</hi> and <hi>accompliſh</hi> all his pleaſure. <hi>Such</hi> parts and members as <hi>theſe,</hi> are indeed very <hi>neceſſary</hi> to us, becauſe all our <hi>purpoſes,</hi> and all <hi>our</hi> deſigns are vain and <hi>ineffectual,</hi> and cannot be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, without the <hi>mediation</hi> of ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans; but the Almighty <hi>will</hi> of God commands <hi>obedience,</hi> and a moſt <hi>ready</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and compliance from <hi>every</hi> thing in the Creation, and by his pleaſure <hi>only,</hi> they <hi>receive,</hi> or <hi>loſe,</hi> their <hi>being,</hi> their <hi>life</hi> and <hi>operation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hoſ. 11. 8, 9. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, Ephraim? how ſhall I deliver thee, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? how ſhall I make thee as Admab? how ſhall I ſet thee as Zeboim? mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together. I will not execute the fierceneſs of mine anger, I will not return to deſtroy Ephraim; for I am God, and not man.</hi> Thus are <hi>humane</hi> paſſions attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to God <hi>himſelf;</hi> and, How is he <hi>repreſented</hi> here expoſtulating with himſelf as a Being <hi>full</hi> of mercy and <hi>compaſſion;</hi> and moſt <hi>infinitely</hi> deſirous to <hi>abſtain</hi> from puniſhment, even when their <hi>ſins</hi> did <hi>highly</hi> deſerve the greateſt <hi>infliction</hi> of <hi>temporal</hi> evils? as if God had ſaid, Thou <hi>deſerve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> deſtruction no leſs than <hi>thoſe</hi> wicked <hi>cities</hi> See <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 23. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 23. Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:47052:62"/>
my <hi>commiſeration</hi> is <hi>ſo</hi> infinite to thee, that I cannot ſuffer my <hi>ſelf</hi> to be <hi>ſo</hi> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty rigorous, as to ſhow my <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> in thy <hi>ruine</hi> and deſtruction. How full of <hi>condeſcenſion</hi> are ſuch <hi>paſſionate</hi> expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? how uſefull and how <hi>beneficial</hi> are they, to <hi>aſſure</hi> us of his infinite <hi>love</hi> and <hi>affection</hi> to the <hi>ſons</hi> of men; That he is not, as <hi>ſome</hi> repreſent him, a God <hi>inexc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> or void of <hi>compaſſion,</hi> or that he takes any <hi>complacency</hi> in the <hi>miſery</hi> of his Creatures; but he even ſpares us, when we <hi>deſerve</hi> puniſhment, and in his <hi>wrath,</hi> thinketh upon <hi>mercy.</hi> And now, if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God did not thus <hi>condeſcend</hi> to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover</hi> himſelf in ſuch mighty pathetical <hi>ſtrains</hi> of love and tenderneſs to us, we might <hi>fanſie</hi> there was ſome kind of <hi>truth</hi> in thoſe impious and pernicious doctrines which tell us, God deſign'd to <hi>make</hi> man, to make him <hi>miſerable,</hi> even from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but how <hi>unworthy</hi> are <hi>ſuch</hi> notions of God, who is <hi>infinite</hi> in goodneſs and mercy? how <hi>contradictory</hi> to his <hi>loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs</hi> to us? <hi>Not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come, and be ſaved.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Eph. 4. 30. <hi>Grieve not the holy Spirit of God;</hi> where the Paſſion of <hi>ſorrow</hi> is applied to the Holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> as a <hi>perſonal</hi> act; and cannot, with any <hi>propriety,</hi> be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:47052:63"/>
aſcribed to a <hi>mere power</hi> or <hi>faculty,</hi> as <hi>ſome</hi> fanſie the Holy Spirit, and not to be a <hi>real</hi> Perſon. <hi>Grieve not then the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> the third Perſon in the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> leſt <hi>he</hi> withdraw his <hi>comfort,</hi> his joy, and <hi>conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> from your heart; leſt the bleſſed <hi>influence</hi> of his <hi>grace departeth</hi> from you, as from an <hi>unpleaſant</hi> converſation.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 6. 6. <hi>God</hi> is ſaid to <hi>repent.</hi> See alſo 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 11, 29. Not that there is the <hi>leaſt</hi> change or <hi>alteration</hi> in God, but only in the object, in the <hi>works</hi> of his hand, which were once <hi>good,</hi> but <hi>now</hi> are <hi>evil;</hi> for God himſelf is <hi>unchangeable,</hi> and always the <hi>ſame;</hi> but 'tis his <hi>eternal</hi> will and pleaſure, that <hi>wicked</hi> men ſhould be <hi>miſerable,</hi> and <hi>good</hi> men <hi>happy;</hi> either <hi>here,</hi> in <hi>this</hi> world; or at <hi>leaſt</hi> in the <hi>world</hi> to come; which always is <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed</hi> in <hi>ſome</hi> reſpect or other, though we are ſometimes <hi>unable</hi> to make the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery</hi> of it, we cannot look into the <hi>hearts</hi> of men, and there <hi>ſee</hi> their <hi>joys,</hi> or their <hi>ſorrows,</hi> growing up in their minds; and therefore how often do we make a <hi>falſe</hi> eſtimate of the <hi>condition</hi> of the ungodly man, and <hi>fanſie</hi> him to be at <hi>eaſe</hi> and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et in his thoughts, and to live with <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> and ſatisfaction; who, upon reflection upon his <hi>paſt</hi> actions, and upon <hi>expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:47052:63"/>
of death and judgment, is often a man of <hi>ſorrows</hi> and <hi>acquainted</hi> with grief, full of trouble and anxiety; and thinks <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> unhappy, and <hi>miſerable,</hi> even beyond <hi>all</hi> expreſſion.</p>
                     <p>Thus, when God is ſaid to <hi>deſcend,</hi> which implies a <hi>local motion,</hi> a motion from one place into another; yet the phraſe by interpretation ſignifies, that God did there reveal and manifeſt himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. 5.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 18. 21. <hi>I will go down and ſee whether they have done altogether accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cry of it, which is come to me, and if not, I will know;</hi> here God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>diſcourſeth,</hi> as a <hi>man</hi> to his <hi>neighbour;</hi> as if he was <hi>not</hi> a Being of <hi>infinite</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but did receive his <hi>notice</hi> and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of worldly affairs, by a <hi>gradual</hi> courſe of thinking and obſervation; and by <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> enquiries into <hi>ſecond</hi> cauſes. Thus God ſuffers himſelf to be <hi>diſcribed</hi> like a Judge, who <hi>repairs</hi> to the place where the <hi>matter</hi> in queſtion was <hi>tranſacted,</hi> that by his <hi>perſonal</hi> appearance, he may more fully and eaſily <hi>aſſure</hi> himſelf of the <hi>innocence,</hi> or the <hi>guilt,</hi> of the <hi>accuſed</hi> perſon; and <hi>one</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why God makes uſe of ſuch a <hi>form</hi> of ſpeaking, is, to certifie us, that there is not always <hi>one</hi> event to the righteous, and to the <hi>wicked;</hi> but that he <hi>rewards</hi> or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:47052:64"/>
man, according to the <hi>rules</hi> and equity of Juſtice; and not with unadviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>raſhneſs</hi> and <hi>indeliberation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And the Lord called unto Adam, and ſaid, Where art thou?</hi> Not that this <hi>kind</hi> of queſtion in the <hi>leaſt</hi> ſignifies, that God <hi>poſſibly</hi> could be <hi>ignorant</hi> where <hi>Adam</hi> was; but this way of ſpeaking is rather a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal</hi> citation, or a <hi>ſummons</hi> to <hi>Adam</hi> who ſeems <hi>unwilling</hi> to come and appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>offended</hi> God; being <hi>extreamly</hi> conſcious of his <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>guiltineſs,</hi> and of his <hi>fall</hi> from the <hi>happy</hi> ſtate of <hi>innocence;</hi> and now beholding a mighty <hi>train</hi> of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, which were to <hi>follow</hi> him as a juſt <hi>retribution</hi> for his <hi>diſobedience.</hi> One of the Fathers is of opinion, this expreſſion, <hi>Where art thou?</hi> is rather a <hi>ſevere</hi> kind of reprehenſion to <hi>Adam;</hi> as if God ſaid, to <hi>terrifie</hi> him more exceedingly, From what <hi>grace</hi> and innocence art <hi>thou</hi> fallen? Come then, and <hi>appear</hi> before me; <hi>Where art thou?</hi> and behold <hi>Adam</hi> was <hi>afraid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And God bleſſed them, ſaying, Be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and multiply, and fill the waters in the ſeas, and let the fowl multiply in the earth;</hi> which kind of phraſes denote no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but his <hi>divine</hi> appointment, of the <hi>encreaſe</hi> of his Creatures in their <hi>kind</hi> for certainly you can never be ſo <hi>unkind</hi>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:47052:64"/>
to your <hi>own</hi> ſence and reaſon, as to fanſie <hi>God</hi> ſpeaks to his <hi>irrational</hi> Creatures, as if <hi>they</hi> were <hi>capable</hi> to <hi>hear,</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> his pleaſure; but God rather <hi>dictates</hi> to their proper <hi>natures;</hi> and by natural inſtinct and <hi>inclinations</hi> he has given them <hi>power,</hi> and virtue, and <hi>efficacy,</hi> to <hi>propagate</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their <hi>kind.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 5. 6. <hi>I will command the clouds, that they rain no more upon it:</hi> and now, who <hi>ſuppoſes</hi> that God himſelf preſently ſent <hi>ſtrict</hi> orders to the Clouds, to keep <hi>back</hi> their <hi>fall</hi> of waters; for the <hi>expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> imports no more but <hi>this,</hi> that God, by the <hi>courſe</hi> of <hi>natural</hi> cauſes, ſo <hi>diſpoſeth</hi> things in heaven, and earth, that at <hi>ſuch</hi> a time the Clouds of <hi>heaven</hi> ſhould be <hi>void</hi> of water; ſo that he orders <hi>ſecond</hi> cauſes, and the <hi>operations</hi> of them, not according to the <hi>preſent</hi> exigency, but by his <hi>infinite</hi> proſpect into <hi>futurity,</hi> he does antecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo <hi>manage</hi> every thing, that nothing falls out <hi>unexpectedly,</hi> but according to his <hi>will</hi> and pleaſure.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 18. 10. <hi>He rode upon a Cherub, and did fly; yea, God did fly upon the wings of the wind;</hi> which expreſſion <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys</hi> to our mind a more <hi>ſenſible</hi> notion of ſpeed; God did not <hi>ride,</hi> but <hi>fly,</hi> even upon the <hi>very</hi> wings of the <hi>wind,</hi> which
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:47052:65"/>
is the <hi>higheſt</hi> degree of <hi>ſpeedy</hi> motion that <hi>poſſibly</hi> can be <hi>deſcrib'd,</hi> to <hi>frame</hi> in us an <hi>Idea</hi> of his <hi>incredible</hi> ſwiftneſs.</p>
                     <p>And now, becauſe God is ſo <hi>indulgent</hi> to ſubmit himſelf to <hi>our</hi> Capacities, muſt we preſently pretend to <hi>deſcribe</hi> him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>narrow proportions</hi> of man. How does God <hi>baffle</hi> us, how does he put us to <hi>ſilence,</hi> when he is <hi>pleas'd</hi> to ask us <hi>queſtions</hi> beyond the <hi>compaſs</hi> of our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? <hi>Hath the rain a Father, or who hath begotten the drops of dew?</hi> Job 38. 28. that is, Am not I, the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of theſe, and is there <hi>any</hi> one beſides?</p>
                     <p>Job 38. 19. <hi>Where is the way, where the light dwelleth? and as for darkneſs, where is the place thereof?</hi> that is, No man knows the particular <hi>points</hi> of the Sun's <hi>riſing</hi> or <hi>ſetting;</hi> and now, that God may make us ſtill <hi>more</hi> ſenſible of our <hi>ignorance, Haſt thou,</hi> ſays God, <hi>entered into the ſprings of the ſeas? or haſt thou walked in the ſearch of the depth?</hi> that is, Thou art <hi>perfectly</hi> a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to the whole <hi>courſe</hi> of nature. Verſ. 22, 23. <hi>Haſt thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the treaſures of ſnow? or haſt thou ſeen the treaſures of hail, which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved againſt the time of trouble, againſt the day of war and battle?</hi> All which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, that we are <hi>unacquainted</hi> with the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:47052:65"/>
                        <hi>ſecret cauſe</hi> and origin, <hi>uſe,</hi> and <hi>producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of theſe things; and how, and when, God lays in his <hi>mighty</hi> treaſures of <hi>ſtorm</hi> and tempeſt, to <hi>confound</hi> his Enemies. The falling of <hi>ſnow</hi> and <hi>rain</hi> may ſeem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>accidental,</hi> and according to the <hi>uſual</hi> courſe of nature; but I am <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> that the <hi>wind</hi> and the <hi>waters</hi> are laid up, as in a <hi>treaſury;</hi> and when God pleaſeth, he ſends them <hi>abroad,</hi> as well for the <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of <hi>ſome,</hi> as for the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of <hi>other</hi> people. Thus do I conclude <hi>this</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure with theſe difficult and <hi>amazing</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, to let you know, that although God <hi>condeſcends</hi> to ſpeak to us in a <hi>familiar</hi> way; yet <hi>ſometimes</hi> too he thinks it <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient</hi> to let us <hi>know</hi> our <hi>diſtance,</hi> and our <hi>ignorance</hi> too, when he propoſeth <hi>ſuch</hi> queſtions to us; as declare his <hi>infinite</hi> power and <hi>greatneſs</hi> Such <hi>queſtions</hi> as are above our comprehenſion, and ſo they ſhould make us more <hi>ſenſible</hi> of our <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>infirmity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>CHARIENTISMUS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Charientiſmus,</hi> a Figure when we return a very <hi>mild,</hi> and <hi>gentle</hi> anſwer, although we are not <hi>inſenſible</hi> of the <hi>provocation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>John 18. 23. <hi>Jeſus anſwered him, If
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:47052:66"/>
I have ſpoken evil, bear witneſs of the evil; but if well, why ſmiteſt thou me?</hi> How does our <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Saviour not render <hi>evil,</hi> for <hi>evil?</hi> How does he <hi>patiently</hi> ſuffer the <hi>affront,</hi> and meekly <hi>expoſtulate</hi> for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury he received? and, How does the <hi>ſoft</hi> Anſwer turn <hi>their</hi> wrath <hi>away?</hi> Prov. 15. 1.</p>
                     <p>When St. <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>interrupted</hi> by <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> with a <hi>reproachfull</hi> language, telling him that he was <hi>mad,</hi> Acts 26. 24. How does our Apoſtle return a ſoft and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Anſwer to him, not without the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt deference? <hi>But he ſaid, I am not mad, moſt noble Feſtus,</hi> v. 25.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 26, 27. When the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> importuned <hi>our</hi> Saviour to <hi>work</hi> a <hi>wonderfull</hi> Cure upon <hi>her</hi> daughter, who was <hi>tormented</hi> with an <hi>evil</hi> ſpirit, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour tells her that, <hi>It was not convenient to take the childrens bread, and caſt it to dogs;</hi> that is, It was not <hi>proper</hi> to work <hi>thoſe</hi> Miracles among the <hi>heathen,</hi> which were chiefly deſign'd for God's <hi>own peculiar</hi> People, the <hi>Jews;</hi> obſerve, how <hi>they</hi> are <hi>here</hi> called <hi>the children,</hi> and the <hi>heathen</hi> are termed the <hi>dogs.</hi> And <hi>what</hi> expreſſion can be more <hi>harſh,</hi> more <hi>ſevere,</hi> or more likely to <hi>provoke</hi> the <hi>meekeſt</hi> Soul to ſome <hi>undecent</hi> and <hi>paſſionate</hi> expreſſion. But how <hi>extreamly civil,</hi> how <hi>courteous,</hi> how
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:47052:66"/>
very <hi>obliging</hi> is <hi>her Anſwer?</hi> and ſhe ſaid, <hi>Truth Lord;</hi> and ſo ſtill gives him the greateſt Title of reſpect and honour; 'Tis true, my Lord, I cannot deny what you pleaſe to ſay; <hi>Yet the dogs eat of the crumbs which fall from their maſters table:</hi> as if ſhe had ſaid, The dogs do receive the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders and ſcatterings which fall from the table; ſo even I my ſelf, who am a Gentile, or call me, if you pleaſe, by the vileſt name; ſo long as you will but <hi>ſuffer</hi> me to enjoy the <hi>ſame</hi> favour with the <hi>Jews;</hi> I can eaſily <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with any <hi>ſuch infamous</hi> or <hi>reproachfull</hi> language. Such <hi>humiliation,</hi> ſuch an humble <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of Soul, and ſuch <hi>importunity,</hi> can never be <hi>unacceptable</hi> to Almighty God; and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf <hi>cannot</hi> but <hi>favour ſuch</hi> deſires. And you find, our Saviour <hi>himſelf</hi> was in no <hi>ſmall</hi> admiration, and <hi>mightily</hi> ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with this <hi>meek</hi> and humble <hi>inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> eſpecially after ſo <hi>great</hi> a provocation; for the very ſound of the word, ſo applied, is very <hi>ignominious;</hi> and ſo Chriſt preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells her, <hi>O woman, great is thy faith! be it unto thee even as thou wilt:</hi> Thus an <hi>importunate</hi> Prayer, accompanied with ſuch a <hi>deep</hi> ſence of our <hi>own unworthineſs,</hi> is <hi>ſtill</hi> the <hi>neareſt</hi> way to <hi>receive</hi> and enjoy all the <hi>bleſſed</hi> conſequences of <hi>our Petitions;</hi>
                        <pb n="106" facs="tcp:47052:67"/>
and Heaven <hi>it ſelf</hi> is <hi>overcome</hi> with ſuch a <hi>pleaſing violence.</hi> Thus, you ſee, the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> was not <hi>inſenſible</hi> of the <hi>provocation;</hi> and yet, how very <hi>courtly,</hi> how <hi>genteel</hi> is her <hi>Anſwer? True, my Lord; yet the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dogs eat of the crumbs which fall from their maſters table;</hi> and let me beg you to be ſo kind, as to ſuffer me now, with them, to enjoy ſuch a kind of favour, ſuch a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, and ſo Chriſt himſelf breaks out in amazement of ſuch a moſt <hi>kind, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, unexpected reply; O woman, great is thy faith:</hi> thy belief is mighty <hi>ſtrange</hi> and wonderfull to me, and <hi>ſo</hi> very <hi>forcible,</hi> ſo <hi>prevailing</hi> with me, that I cannot <hi>poſſibly</hi> deny what you <hi>deſire.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>APODIOXIS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Apodioxis.</hi> This Figure, not without <hi>ſcorn</hi> and indignation, <hi>rejects</hi> any ſort of <hi>argument,</hi> as very <hi>abſurd</hi> in it ſelf, and not <hi>reducible</hi> to <hi>practice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 23. How does Chriſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> when he importunately <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired</hi> our Saviour <hi>not</hi> to ſuffer <hi>perſecution; Get thee behind me, Satan, thou art an offence unto me: for thou ſavoureſt not the things of God:</hi> This is a reflection upon <hi>our</hi> Apoſtle of the <hi>higheſt</hi> nature, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly nothing <hi>leſs,</hi> than the <hi>greateſt</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:47052:67"/>
could <hi>extort</hi> ſuch <hi>expreſſions</hi> from Chriſt <hi>himſelf.</hi> And now, Who would think that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who was ſo <hi>extreamly</hi> diſpleaſing to our <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Saviour, and ſo <hi>highly</hi> condemned by him, as to call him <hi>Satan,</hi> a word of the <hi>greateſt</hi> infamy and reproach; ſhould, of <hi>all</hi> the Apoſtles, be the only <hi>head</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church; as if the <hi>reſt,</hi> were not as <hi>equally</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the <hi>foundation</hi> of Chriſtianity as St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf; whereas <hi>all</hi> the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference that was given to <hi>this</hi> Apoſtle, was rather with <hi>reſpect</hi> to his <hi>age,</hi> than to any <hi>authority</hi> and power he <hi>received</hi> as an <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> Indeed, was there any <hi>preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence</hi> among the Apoſtles, I ſhould think St. <hi>John</hi> deſerves to be called the very <hi>chief</hi> of them all; becauſe he is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and <hi>ſtyled</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>the diſciple whom Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus loved,</hi> with <hi>more</hi> expreſſion of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and <hi>affection,</hi> than <hi>all</hi> the reſt: and, Who can be ſo well <hi>qualified,</hi> to be <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream</hi> in the Church, as <hi>that</hi> Perſon, who was <hi>deareſt</hi> to his Saviour? And therefore certainly moſt <hi>deſerving</hi> in himſelf: Whereas St. <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>guilty</hi> of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> in his <hi>obſtinate</hi> denial of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> even to <hi>abjuration</hi> of him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 74. even <hi>when</hi> he had given his <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi>
                        <pb n="108" facs="tcp:47052:68"/>
the higheſt <hi>kind</hi> of aſſurance, that though <hi>all</hi> the Apoſtles did <hi>forſake</hi> him, yet, for <hi>his</hi> part, he was reſolved, <hi>not</hi> to doe the <hi>like;</hi> and yet was he the <hi>firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerter</hi> of him.</p>
                     <p>Acts 8. 20. <hi>But Peter ſaid, Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou thoughteſt that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</hi> This was an <hi>imprecation</hi> of the higheſt nature.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 50. 21. <hi>Thou thoughteſt that I was ſuch a one as thy ſelf; but I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thee,</hi> for thy ſins, <hi>and ſet them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matth. 7. 16. <hi>Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thiſtles? How then can you, being evil, ſpeak good things?</hi> Matth. 12. 34. and the very <hi>abſurdity</hi> of the <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> was too manifeſt to require an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>LITOTES.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Litotes.</hi> This Trope we make uſe of, when we ſay not ſo <hi>much</hi> as we <hi>think;</hi> yet ſuch a way of <hi>ſpeaking</hi> is often much more <hi>forcible,</hi> and makes <hi>ſtronger</hi> impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon us. 'Tis, in ſhort, a ſort of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure extreamly <hi>decent,</hi> and never uſed without <hi>modeſty</hi> and <hi>diſcretion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="109" facs="tcp:47052:68"/>
                        <hi>What, ſhall I praiſe you in this? I praiſe you not.</hi> Rom. 11. 21. Which was a <hi>ſofter</hi> way of <hi>reprehenſion,</hi> to tell his <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> when they were <hi>guilty</hi> of very great <hi>irreverence</hi> in the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Sacrament, that he could not much <hi>commend</hi> them, upon <hi>that</hi> account; and though the expreſſion ſeems very <hi>mild,</hi> and favourable, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teel, What ſhall I <hi>ſay</hi> unto you? <hi>I praiſe you not.</hi> Yet it <hi>really</hi> ſignifies thus much, I do highly <hi>blame,</hi> and <hi>diſcommend ſuch</hi> kind of <hi>practices.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I hear there be diviſions among you, and I partly believe it?</hi> As if the Apoſtle was not <hi>willing</hi> to tell them he was <hi>certainly</hi> aſſured of it; but rather <hi>chuſes</hi> to ſay, that his <hi>information</hi> was from <hi>ſome</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and report abroad, and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares he had <hi>ſome</hi> reaſon to <hi>believe</hi> there was <hi>ſeparations</hi> among them, and this he mentions in <hi>ſuch</hi> a way, to correct and <hi>reform</hi> them more <hi>effectually</hi> and make them ſtill more <hi>ſenſible</hi> of the ſin and <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of <hi>diviſion;</hi> and ſo is, as it were, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing</hi> to think them ſo <hi>ill</hi> Chriſtians, as to be <hi>guilty</hi> of ſo great and ſo <hi>dangerous</hi> a ſin.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 51. 17. <hi>A broken and a contrite heart, O Lord, ſhalt thou not deſpiſe:</hi> which is ſpoken with a <hi>mighty</hi> ſence of his
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:47052:69"/>
own <hi>unworthineſs,</hi> and the expreſſion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys a great <hi>deal</hi> more, than barely that God will not <hi>reject</hi> or <hi>diſregard</hi> him that is ſo <hi>penitentially ſorrowfull</hi> for his ſins; for it ſignifies, that God will <hi>graciouſly</hi> pardon and <hi>receive</hi> ſuch a <hi>perſon</hi> into his <hi>favour</hi> and friendſhip.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 9. 12. <hi>He will not forget the cry of the poor and humble;</hi> that is, God will be certainly <hi>mindfull</hi> and <hi>remember</hi> their afflictions and miſeries, and at laſt <hi>ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> puniſh their <hi>cruel</hi> Oppreſſors.</p>
                     <p>Job 31. 16. <hi>If I have withheld the poor from their deſire.</hi> Verſ. 17. <hi>Or have eaten my morſel my ſelf alone.</hi> Verſ. 19. <hi>If I have ſuffered any to periſh for want of cloathing, or let the poor go naked, without a covering<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> Thus, with <hi>what</hi> modeſty and <hi>reſervation</hi> does holy <hi>Job</hi> ſpeak of his own <hi>juſtice,</hi> his <hi>hoſpitality,</hi> his <hi>charity</hi> to the <hi>poor,</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>ſome extenuation</hi> of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>SARCASMUS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sarcaſmus.</hi> A moſt <hi>ſevere</hi> way of <hi>mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery</hi> and deriſion, not unlike an <hi>Irony.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs that 'tis commonly <hi>malicious,</hi> or <hi>more</hi> ſcoffing in its kind.</p>
                     <p>Pſalm 103. 3. <hi>They that carried us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way captive required of us a ſong; and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:47052:69"/>
they that waſted us, required of us mirth; ſaying, Sing us one of the ſongs of Sion.</hi> This muſt be ſpoken not without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and <hi>ſcorn,</hi> and deriſion to them; to deſire at a <hi>time</hi> ſo very <hi>unſeaſonable,</hi> when they were <hi>ſlaves</hi> and captives, <hi>mourning</hi> under <hi>great</hi> oppreſſions, to <hi>commemorate</hi> their <hi>former</hi> days of joy and <hi>liberty;</hi> ſuch a <hi>requeſt</hi> muſt needs be <hi>highly provoking,</hi> and give them ſtill but a <hi>freſher</hi> ſenſe of the <hi>preſent</hi> miſeries; eſpecially conſidering the <hi>perſons</hi> who <hi>importune</hi> them to be <hi>joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and pleaſant; for they were the <hi>lords</hi> and <hi>maſters</hi> over them; and therefore <hi>they</hi> tell them <hi>their</hi> petition was then <hi>extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> improper, and moſt <hi>diſagreeable; How ſhall we ſing the Lord's ſong in a ſtrange land?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Exod. 14. 11. <hi>And they ſaid unto Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Becauſe there were no Graves in Egypt, haſt thou taken us away, to die in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs?</hi> A <hi>ſarcaſtical</hi> way of ſpeaking, as if they ſaid, We could <hi>die,</hi> and be in our <hi>graves</hi> with <hi>leſs</hi> trouble in our <hi>own</hi> land; why then are you ſo <hi>barbarous</hi> to us, as to <hi>tire</hi> us out with long and <hi>tedious</hi> journeys, only to <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> us in the <hi>wilderneſs;</hi> wherefore are you ſo <hi>unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull,</hi> why do you <hi>deal</hi> ſo <hi>unkindly</hi> with us?</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:47052:70"/>Gen. 3. 22. <hi>And the Lord ſaid, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the man is become like one of us.</hi> Was not this a ſevere reflection upon the <hi>fall</hi> of <hi>Adam?</hi> and a <hi>mighty</hi> reproach to his <hi>weakneſs</hi> and infirmity, when he liſtned to the <hi>falſe</hi> ſuggeſtions of the <hi>Devil,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, <hi>Ye ſhall be as gods, knowing good and evil.</hi> Gen. 3. 5. See <hi>Matt.</hi> 3. 7. <hi>James</hi> 2. 19.</p>
                     <p>Nahum 3. 14. <hi>Draw thy waters for the ſiege, fortifie thy ſtrong holds, go into the clay, and tread thy mortar, make ſtrong thy brickhill:</hi> that is, Go, and make all theſe warlike <hi>preparations</hi> for a ſiege; go, and <hi>repair,</hi> and fortifie thy breaches; all this is nothing elſe but a jeer, <hi>mockery</hi> and deriſion; for the Prophet tells them in the very next Verſe, <hi>They ſhall be deſtroyed, there ſhall the fire devour thee, and the ſword ſhall cut thee off.</hi> See alſo the like <hi>Sarcaſm,</hi> Nahum 2. 1.</p>
                     <p>Matth. 27. 29. <hi>And when they had platted a crown of thorns, they put it upon his head, and a reed in his hand; and they bowed the knee before him, and mocked him, ſaying, Hail King of the Jews.</hi> Such a kind of <hi>ſceptre</hi> and <hi>crown</hi> they beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, to <hi>betray</hi> him to <hi>more</hi> diſgrace and <hi>infamy;</hi> and when he appeared moſt <hi>ingloriouſly</hi> and <hi>unlike</hi> a Prince, then do
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:47052:70"/>
they moſt <hi>contemptibly</hi> pretend to pay him the <hi>higheſt</hi> honour and <hi>reverence.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="illustration_of_speech">
                     <head>PATHOPOEIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pathopoeĭa<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> This Figure excites a moſt <hi>exceſſive</hi> Paſſion in the <hi>ſoul</hi> of Man, ſuch as <hi>ſorrow, joy, deſire,</hi> and the like.</p>
                     <p>Hoſea 11. 8. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, Ephraim? how ſhall I deliver thee, Iſrael? how ſhall I make thee as Admah? how ſhall I ſet thee as Zeboim? mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> What a mighty <hi>pathos</hi> have <hi>theſe</hi> words? how are <hi>theſe</hi> expreſſions <hi>extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> paſſionate? what <hi>tenderneſs?</hi> what <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions?</hi> what <hi>riches</hi> of mercy and <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> does God <hi>himſelf</hi> ſhow to <hi>his</hi> people, even when <hi>their</hi> fins are become <hi>unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable?</hi> yet then his <hi>love,</hi> his <hi>compaſſion</hi> is ſo <hi>exceſſively</hi> great, that he cannot ſuffer <hi>himſelf</hi> to <hi>deſtroy</hi> them, as thoſe <hi>wicked</hi> places, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 23. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 23. But the Lord <hi>repreſents</hi> himſelf in a very <hi>great</hi> diſorder and <hi>confuſion,</hi> and as it were <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> and ſwayed by <hi>different</hi> Inclinations; ſometimes as a <hi>juſt</hi> and a moſt righteous Judge; and then, <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the earth doe right?</hi> And now again, he conſiders alſo, that he <hi>himſelf</hi> is a <hi>God</hi> full
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:47052:71"/>
of <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>compaſſion;</hi> and then ſays, <hi>I will not execute the fierceneſs of mine anger, I will not return to deſtroy Ephraim; for I am a God, and not a man.</hi> Methinks <hi>ſuch</hi> tender and <hi>affectionate</hi> expreſſions as <hi>theſe</hi> give no <hi>great</hi> countenance to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>reprobation;</hi> for if God from <hi>all eternity</hi> decreed man to be <hi>miſerable;</hi> why ſhould God <hi>himſelf</hi> expreſs ſuch an <hi>infinite</hi> concernment upon the <hi>proſpect</hi> of his <hi>ruine</hi> and deſtruction? why ſhould the Father of Mercy <hi>weep</hi> and <hi>lament</hi> over him, when he was <hi>loſt</hi> beyond <hi>all</hi> recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſo <hi>long</hi> ago, and by his very decrees, if they are in the right<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which were ſent unto thee; how often would I have gathered thee, as the hen gathereth her chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens under her wing, and ye would not.</hi> Read here the <hi>tender</hi> ſenſe of God, upon the <hi>miſery</hi> of his People: how willing, how deſirous he is, to be <hi>their</hi> Saviour, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the very <hi>ſame</hi> care, the <hi>ſame</hi> affections for their <hi>preſervation,</hi> as the moſt <hi>fond</hi> Parent has for her own <hi>beloved</hi> Children.</p>
                     <p>1 Cor. 4. 14. <hi>I write not theſe things to ſhame you; but as my beloved ſons, I warn you.</hi> And can there be <hi>any</hi> thing ſaid more <hi>paſſionately?</hi> What can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:47052:71"/>
with more <hi>kindneſs</hi> and more <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</hi> or more <hi>ſenſibly</hi> diſcover his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>concernment</hi> for their Salvation. See alſo 2 Cor. 2. 4.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For out of much affection and anguiſh of heart, I wrote unto you with many tears, not that you ſhould be grieved, but that ye may know the love which I have more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly unto you:</hi> This is a <hi>paſtoral</hi> Care, worthy <hi>our Apoſtle;</hi> this <hi>ardency</hi> of love and affection, is moſt <hi>incomparable: how</hi> does St. <hi>Paul,</hi> with an <hi>infinite</hi> tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>inſinuate</hi> to his <hi>dear Corinthians,</hi> the <hi>reaſons</hi> why he was ſo <hi>extreamly</hi> troubled for <hi>their</hi> ſakes, was not in the <hi>leaſt</hi> to make <hi>them ſorrowfull,</hi> and to draw <hi>tears</hi> from <hi>their</hi> eyes; but only to <hi>diſcover</hi> his moſt <hi>tender</hi> love and compaſſion for them, not willing in the <hi>leaſt</hi> that any ſhould <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> but that <hi>all</hi> ſhould <hi>repent</hi> and be <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 31. 1. <hi>What, my ſon? and what, the ſon of my womb? and what, O ſon of my deſires?</hi> Asif his <hi>mother Bathſheba</hi> was at a <hi>mighty</hi> loſs, what ſort of <hi>inſtructions</hi> to give to her <hi>ſon Solomon,</hi> or what <hi>precepts</hi> are moſt <hi>proper</hi> and convenient for him; and the queſtion implies the <hi>care,</hi> the <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitouſneſs,</hi> and the <hi>fondneſs</hi> of a <hi>tender<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="116" facs="tcp:47052:72"/>
                        <hi>John</hi> 21. 15. Our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> with a <hi>mighty</hi> paſſion, ſeems to <hi>ask</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> no leſs than <hi>three times, Simon Peter, loveſt thou me?</hi> Inſomuch that the Apoſtle <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> was very much <hi>troubled,</hi> that his <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> ſhould <hi>ſo</hi> very often <hi>queſtion</hi> his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him; <hi>and Peter was grieved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaid alſo the third time, Loveſt thou me?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 49. 15. <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking child?</hi> Yea, <hi>they</hi> may <hi>forget,</hi> yet will I not <hi>forget thee.</hi> Thus God <hi>himſelf</hi> puts a <hi>queſtion</hi> concerning the moſt <hi>unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> thing; for a <hi>mother</hi> to be <hi>unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> of the Child of her <hi>womb;</hi> and yet tells, us, though this be <hi>extreamly</hi> difficult, and the <hi>greateſt</hi> violence to <hi>humane</hi> nature; yet ſuch <hi>inhumanity</hi> is <hi>poſſible:</hi> yet <hi>never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs,</hi> God <hi>aſſures</hi> his People, that 'tis <hi>not poſſible</hi> for himſelf to be <hi>ſo unkind,</hi> or <hi>ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull</hi> of them.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Something extreamly kind I feign would ſay,</l>
                        <l>But find my words can never force their way.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Jer. 31. 20. <hi>Is Ephraim my dear ſon? is he a pleaſant child? for ſince I ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, I do earneſtly remember him
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:47052:72"/>
ſtill, therefore my bowels are troubled for him.</hi> And now, can you <hi>perſuade</hi> your ſelf, that <hi>ſuch</hi> moſt tender <hi>thoughts</hi> as theſe, can <hi>proceed</hi> from God, if he was a <hi>cruel</hi> Being? does ſuch <hi>affectionate</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage <hi>declare,</hi> that God takes any <hi>delight</hi> in the <hi>miſery</hi> of his <hi>creatures,</hi> or that he can in the <hi>leaſt,</hi> be <hi>acceſſary</hi> to their <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency,</hi> or to their <hi>eternal</hi> ruine and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, when he <hi>diſcovers</hi> himſelf ſo <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately</hi> kind and <hi>tender,</hi> that he <hi>languiſheth,</hi> when we are in the <hi>leaſt unhappy,</hi> or when <hi>any misfortune</hi> comes upon us?</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If my <hi>Ephraim</hi> but complains,</l>
                        <l>I have ſenſe of all his pains.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rivers of water run down my eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men keep not thy Law:</hi> This is an <hi>exceſſive</hi> paſſion of <hi>grief;</hi> Can any <hi>ſorrow</hi> be <hi>like</hi> to this <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>ſorrow?</hi> Can there be a <hi>greater</hi> demonſtration of his <hi>love</hi> to God, than to be ſo <hi>infinitely afflicted,</hi> to ſee <hi>ſome</hi> ſo very <hi>diſreſpectfull,</hi> ſo <hi>diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> to God's <hi>Commands? Greater love hath no man than this.</hi> Let <hi>others</hi> then take <hi>delight</hi> to <hi>blaſpheme</hi> his Name; let <hi>others crucifie</hi> their <hi>Saviour</hi> again, and <hi>once</hi> more put him to <hi>open</hi> ſhame, while the <hi>godly</hi> Man is more <hi>happily</hi> employed,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:47052:73"/>
and <hi>pours</hi> out his <hi>ſoul</hi> in <hi>weeping</hi> and <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations,</hi> and with the Prophet, crys out in the <hi>moſt</hi> paſſionate manner, <hi>Oh that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the manifold ſins and provocations of thy people Iſrael!</hi> Jerem. 9. 1.</p>
                     <p>Gal. 4. 19. <hi>My little children, of whom Itravail in birth again, until Chriſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in you:</hi> firſt, he <hi>ſalutes</hi> them with the <hi>kindeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>affectionate</hi> Appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>My little children:</hi> Then, as if he <hi>ſuffered</hi> the greateſt <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>anguiſh</hi> for them, not <hi>unequal</hi> to thoſe of a <hi>woman</hi> in <hi>labour, Of whom I travail, until</hi> the Image of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Righteouſneſs, <hi>be formed</hi> in your <hi>ſouls.</hi> And the <hi>meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor</hi> is very <hi>proper;</hi> for the <hi>moral birth,</hi> to be <hi>regenerate,</hi> and to be <hi>born</hi> again; is no leſs <hi>difficult,</hi> no leſs <hi>painfull</hi> and <hi>labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> than the <hi>natural</hi> birth, or our fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>formation</hi> in the <hi>very</hi> womb.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
